<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://backend.bibliotecaitaliana.it/DTD/bibit.dtd">
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scritti su Parga</title>
            <author>Ugo Foscolo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>191010 Kb in UTF-8</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Biblioteca Italiana</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <idno>bibit000699</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso
                        personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Collezione BibIt</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Scritti sulle isole Ionie e su Parga</title>
               <title type="part">v.</title>
               <author>Foscolo, Ugo</author>
               <editor id="ed">Gambarin, Giovanni</editor>
               <publisher>F. Le Monnier</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Firenze</pubPlace>
               <date>1964</date>
               
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Tutti i materiali paratestuali della fonte cartacea non riconducibili alla
                responsabilità dell'autore dell'opera sono stati soppressi nella versione
                digitale</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction method="silent" status="medium">
               <p>Livello medio: controllo a video con collazione con edizione di
                        riferimento</p>
            </correction>
            <quotation form="data" marks="all">
               <p>I simboli di citazione e di discorso diretto presenti sulla fonte cartacea
                        sono stati rappresentati sulla versione digitale</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>I trattini di sillabazione a fine riga sono stati soppressi e le parole
                        ricomposte</p>
            </hyphenation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="CGB">
               <bibl>Classificazione generi BibIt</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date>800</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="CGB">
               <term>Testi storici e storiografici</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06-08T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Novadata systems</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Digitalizzazione - OCR</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04-23T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Monica Gasbarri</name>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Correzione linguistica</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05-23T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Ilenia Sabelli</name>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Codifica XML - Codifica manuale</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06-17T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Carla Deiana</name>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Validazione</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 n="On Parga">
            <head>ON PARGA</head>
            <p>ART. I. 1. <foreign lang="grc">Ιστορία 
Σουλίου καὶ 
Πάργας, 
περιέχουσα τήν 
χρονολογίαν καὶ 
τοὺς αὐτῶν 
πολέμους μετὰ τοῦ 
Ἀλῆ πασῖα</foreign>: viz. <title>The History of 
Suli and Parga</title>, <hi rend="italic">containing their Chronology as well as their Wars against 
Ali Pacha</hi>. Venice, 1815.</p>
            <p>2. <hi rend="italic">A Series of Historical and Political authentic Documents, beginning 
from the year 1401 and ending with the year 1818, to be presented to the Parliament of Great 
Britain in behalf of the Citizens of Parga</hi>.</p>
            <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings in Parga and the Ionian Islands, with a series of 
Correspondence and other justificative Documents</hi>. By Lieutenant–Colonel C. P. DE 
BOSSET. London, 1819.</p>
            <space type="stacco narrativo"/>
            <p>THE concerns of this interesting and injured little State were brought before Parliament 
in the course of last Session: But, before the discussion had gone any length, its fate was understood 
to be sealed: — and the subject sunk again into that obscurity which naturally covers the 
transactions of a remote and inconsiderable community. It is worth while, however, we think, in this 
instance, at last to withdraw the veil; and to expose, in full day, a transaction in which this country 
is but too much implicated, and which seems to afford a striking illustration of those new principles 
of international law by which we are to be rewarded for thirty years of suffering and 
bloodshed.</p>
            <p>
               <emph>Parga</emph>, which General Vaudoncourt conjectures, upon slight enough 
grounds, to be the ancient <emph>Ephyra</emph> — is situated on the coast of Epirus, at 
the foot of the mountains of Albania, and contained a population of about five thousand souls. No 
unequivocal remains of Grecian art have been found, we believe, within its narrow district, though a 
few coins of the lower empire have been picked up; and the traces of antique buildings may be 
distinguished at the place still popularly known by the name of Ancient Parga (<foreign lang="grc">Παλαιὸ Πάργα</foreign>). In 
the decline of the Roman power, the new city was built on a rock, washed on three sides by the sea, 
and backed by a precipitous cliff, on the summit of which is placed its impregnable citadel. It 
commands, of course, a very magnificent prospect, including on one hand the whole territory of 
Parga and the mountains of Albania, by which it is bounded from east to west; in a southerly 
direction, the eye ranges over a part of the Ionian Sea; on the left are seen the Isle of Santa Maura 
and the famous Sapphic promontory of Leucadia; further on,

<quote rend="block">
                  <lg lang="lat">
                     <l>Jam medio apparet fluctu nemorosa Zacynthos</l>
                     <l>Dulichiumque Sameque et Neritos ardua saxis,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>

together with the dark mountains of Cephalonia; on the right, at the distance of twelve miles, are the 
Islands of Paxo and Antipaxo. The country is extremely fertile and salubrious, abounding with 
springs and rivulets, and exhibiting, in its slopes and hollows, innumerable groves of oranges, 
olives, cedars and cypresses. The people were agricultural, and very warlike both by land and water. 
Without this last quality, indeed, they could not have enjoyed an hour of independence; for they 
were surrounded on all sides by lawless and ambitious neighbours; and the lofty mountains which 
divide them from the Albanian clans and the Turkish frontier, were for four hundred years the, 
scene of almost daily contentions.</p>
            <p>It would be useless, and not very easy, to inquire into the history of this little settlement, 
anterior to its connexion with Venice. But, in the year 1401, it was confederated with that proud 
republic; and continued to enjoy honourable and entire independence in that alliance, till the 
subversion of the greater State in 1797. It is well known, that from the time of Mahomet II., Venice 
was not only the great bulwark of Christendom against the growing power of the Turks, but 
exercised an almost unlimited authority over the eastern shores of the Adriatic, and the maritime 
and insular cities of Greece. For this dominion they were indebted far more to their policy than their 
arms: For, taking advantage of the dissensions that always prevail among such small communities, 
they offered themselves first to one, and then to another, in the imposing character of mediators or 
allies; and, entering into treaties of perpetual friendship and federation, were gradually converted 
from generous protectors to absolute masters and tyrannical oppressors.</p>
            <p>With Parga, however, they comported themselves differently: and the determined valour 
of its inhabitants concurring with their own obvious interest to preserve one willing and well 
affected ally in that turbulent neighbourhood, insured from them the faithful observance of 
stipulations which, in other circumstances, they were accustomed to violate with very little scruple. 
On the 21st day of March 1401, the treaty of federation, thus singularly fulfilled, was first 
subscribed and sworn to between the two States. For the protection of the weaker power it was 
agreed, that the Venetians should maintain a body of Italian or Sclavonian troops within the walls of 
Parga; — but, to prevent the abuse of a power thus dangerously posted, it was solemnly 
stipulated, that the Pargiots should govern themselves freely and independently, according to the 
laws and constitutions of their ancestors, and by judges and magistrates of their own election; 
— that they should not be liable to serve by sea or land, in the militia or galleys of Venice, 
— nor to engage in any war but in defence of their own territory and the Venetian 
settlements in Albania; — that they should pay no taxes nor customs on export or import, 
and be chargeable only with half the ordinary duties when trading to the ports of Venice. This treaty 
was again confirmed with the same solemnities in August 1447, — and observed, to the 
mutual satisfaction of both parties, till the end of that century. In 1500, in spite of the Venetian 
assistance, the city was burned by the Turks — and again in 1560. On this last occasion, the 
inhabitants were massacred or dispersed, and the whole territory laid waste and, desolate. The 
scattered remnant of its people took shelter among the wandering tribes of the neighbouring 
mountains, but, by little and little, ventured back to their ancient possessions; and after several 
years, came at length to rebuild their houses and temples on the spot where their ancestors had 
fallen. They then sent deputies to Venice to demand their assistance, and the renewal of their 
ancient alliance; requesting, among other things, that the Senate should assist in fortifying their city, 
and should also lend them a sum of money to enable the poorer part of the citizens to rebuild their 
habitations. The Senate was not only just, but generous. It undertook the whole expense of erecting 
the fortifications; and, instead of a loan from its treasury, it sent, as a free gift, the requisite 
materials for the construction of their houses. When the particular points of the embassy were 
adjusted, a new charter, ratifying and confirming all the former treaties, was regularly signed on the 
5th of February 1571. It was afterwards repeatedly renewed; and was always religiously fulfilled, 
not only in its letter, but its spirit, till the final extinction of Venice by the ambition of France and 
Austria in 1797.</p>
            <p>To explain the interest which concurred with the spirit of the people to produce this 
exemplary and unexampled fidelity to its engagements in a powerful ally, it may be necessary to 
consider for a moment the nature of the Venetian possessions to the east of the Adriatic, and the 
condition of the countries in their immediate neighbourhood. This great trading and political 
republic, it will be recollected, was mistress of the Ionian islands, and of various other islands and 
continental cities beyond them, — the secure possession of which was not only necessary to 
her maritime and political greatness, but essential to her commercial prosperity. The Turk had by 
this time spread himself over Greece, and was pressing heavily upon the Christian frontier both by 
land and water. To supply her insular settlements with provisions, it was necessary, at all events, 
that Venice should hold a variety of places on the shore of the Continent; and, by a judicious 
selection of these, she had also the prospect, from the singular situation of the country, of holding in 
check, and preventing the further progress of the Ottoman. On the coast of Albania, she had 
therefore established five fortified settlements — <emph>Bucintro</emph>, anciently 
<emph>Buthrotum</emph>, the most central and convenient access to the interior of the country; 
— <emph>Gomenitza</emph>, a large town, and the chief market of the vicinage, from 
which, up to this day, <emph>Corfu</emph> derives its principal supplies; — 
<emph>Prevesa</emph>, a very strong place, and commanding the whole channel leading to the 
gulf of <emph>Arta</emph>; — <emph>Vonitza</emph>, anciently called 
<emph>Lionnœa</emph>, considered as the key of Acarnania; — and, in the middle of 
these four, and as it were the keystone of the whole range, <emph>Parga</emph>, such as it has 
been already described. It was of importance that the attachment of a place so strong, and so 
situated, should be secured; and it was soon discovered that this could not be done without giving 
the inhabitants an interest in their fidelity, and making the power and tranquillity of their protectors 
the basis of their own prosperity and independence. If Parga was hostile, the other cities on the 
coast could not be maintained; and if they were all abandoned, not only would the insular dominion 
of Venice and her commerce be exposed to the greatest disadvantages, but the most effectual barrier 
against the Turk would be in a great measure destroyed. To understand this, it will be convenient, 
and we think not uninteresting, to cast an eye on the condition and extraordinary history of the 
district now called <emph>Albania</emph>, which has so long served as a frontier against the 
advance of the Mahometans.</p>
            <p>It is very singular, that this mountainous but populous region, placed as it is in a very 
favourable climate, and surrounded from the earliest times by the most warlike, as well as the most 
civilized nations of the earth, has never to this day been either <emph>conquered</emph> or 
<emph>civilized</emph>; but continues to the present hour to exhibit the same extraordinary 
picture of untamed and unpolicied life — the same eternal disssensions of hostile clans 
— the same scenes of predatory war and piracy, and contempt of art and industry, by which 
it appears to have been distinguished from the remotest periods of history. Though its natives have 
taken part in almost all the great revolutions to which human affairs have been subjected in the old 
world, and have frequently contributed materially to their success, they have never been an united, a 
polished, or even an agricultural people. From the first to the last, their occupation has been war 
— individual, predatory, mercenary and vindictive war; and the only habits they have 
cultivated, are those that belong to that vocation. In the most ancient times, they furnished a part of 
the first grand piratical expedition of the Argonauts; and fought among the myrmidons under the 
walls of Troy. They invaded the territory of infant Rome with Pyrrhus — and that of Greece 
in her glory with «Philip. They formed a considerable part of the armies with which 
Alexander conquered the world. In later times, under their famous countryman <emph>George 
Castriotto</emph>, better known by the name of <emph>Scanderbeg</emph>, they checked the 
proud arms of the Ottoman, and drove him back from the shores of the Adriatic; and in the 
following age, followed a still more formidable chief of their nation, the warlike 
<emph>Abraham</emph>, in his rapid career of conquest over Syria, Mesopotamia, and Arabia. In 
more modern times, they have repeatedly supported the Porte against the most formidable assaults 
of its rebellious Pachas, and still more frequently enabled these rebels to set at defiance the utmost 
efforts of their masters. In our days, they cont ibuted mainly to the defeat of our second descent on 
Egypt, by their sanguinary attack on our forces at Rosetta. It was by their means that Ali extended 
his conquests over the greater part of Greece; and they are at this moment busy in endeavouring to 
secure the sovereignty of Egypt for Mahomed Ali. In all these different scenes and periods, the 
character and habits of the Albanian have been as unvaried as they are remarkable; and the striking 
picture which Mr Hobhouse has drawn of them, would have been equally true, we believe, 3000 
years ago, as it is as this day.

<quote rend="block">
                  <p>‘They are distinguished, even in a land of barbarians, for the singular cruelty and 
implacability of their disposition. The men of one mountain watch those of a neighbouring hill, and 
neither sow nor reap, nor tend their flocks, singly or unarmed. Should one of them wander beyond 
the precincts of protection, he would be stalked like a deer, — and that without seeing his 
enemy. In many parts of the country the sowing and reaping of the harvest is delegated to the 
women, the old and the infirm; and only those labours which require the strength and skill of man, 
such as the felling of timber, and the cultivation of the vineyard, fall to the lot of the young 
mountaineer. Averse from every habit of active industry, it is with less unwillingness that they 
wander on the mountains, or in forests, with their flocks and herds: for the life of the shepherd is a 
life both of laziness and peril. But the delight of an Albanian, when unoccupied by the wars of his 
Pacha, or his village, is to bask in the sunshine, to smoke, to doze or to stroll slowly round the 
garden of his cottage, tinkling his tuneless lute. Yet though idle, he is still restless and ready to seize 
his gun, and plunge into the woods at the first summons of his chief. In the pursuit of riches, there is 
no toil or danger which they will not encounter; but they prefer the life of the soldier to that of the 
husbandman, and with much greater alacrity support the labours of war than those of 
agriculture.</p>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Even the civilizing conquests of Rome passed over them in vain. Flaminius, when he 
effected his famous settlement of Greece, attempted to give them civil institutions, and to raise them 
to the rank of allies, — but abandoned the project as impracticable; and he and his 
successors were satisfied with occupying the passes to their country, and shutting them up in their 
mountains, to wreak their predatory rage on each other. The issue of the servile war under 
Spartacus, and the expedition of Pompey against the pirates of the Mediterranean, greatly increased 
the population of this colony of outlaws, and made it of course still more necessary to watch, and 
still more hopeless to subdue them. In later times, the sanguinary conquests of the Turk had a 
similar effect; and among the Christian fugitives who were swept from Greece by the desolating 
advance of the Infidel, may be reckoned the first founders of Parga.</p>
            <p>At the period of the French Revolution, the country may be said to have belonged partly 
to the independent clans of the mountains, partly to the Turkish Beys and Pachas really or 
nominally tributary to the Porte, and partly to the Republic of Venice. The independent clans have 
always followed, avowedly and almost exclusively, the trade or occupation of robbery; and the 
name of <foreign lang="grc">Κλεφτης</foreign> is given and 
assumed among them without the idea of reproach. On the borders of Dalmatia they are mostly 
Christian; some Catholics; but the greater part, of the Greek church. They speak Sclavonian; have 
no chief or judge but their bishops; and have always adhered to the interests of Russia. In the central 
parts of the country, the independent clans speak the Arnaut, which is unquestionably the oldest, 
and probably the primitive language of the country; and generally profess Islamism — 
though without any very rigid observance of its rites or injunctions; and often beat and insult their 
Dervises as freely as the Papas of their neighbours. On the frontiers of Greece, again, all the 
independent clans are Christians; and very zealous votaries of the Patriarch of Constantinople. They 
are more skilful warriors, perhaps, and more determined robbers, than any of the rest; and, until 
their independence was broken, and their numbers thinned by the sanguinary conquests of Ali 
Pacha, were the most formidable disturbers of the peace, and the most bloody persecutors of the 
unbelievers, that ever existed even in this turbulent region. The part of Albania which is claimed by 
the Porte, is ruled like the greater part of its outlying provinces, by Pachas and Beys, who, while 
they profess a nominal subjection to its authority, actually govern as absolute princes, and are 
engaged in perpetual wars with each other, for the extension or defence of their territories. The 
victors are generally native chiefs, who employ their hereditary influence against those who are sent 
from Constantinople, and then bribe the Divan to wink at their usurpations, with a part of the booty 
of the vanquished; a policy which seldom fails with that venerable cabinet, especially when backed 
by the consideration, that it might not be quite safe or easy to chastise their rebellion, and that those 
eternal wars among the Pachas, probably prevents any one from obtaining such an ascendancy as 
might encourage him openly and entirely to throw off the pretence of subjection — and thus 
put an end to the chance either of tribute or of bribes. The portion of the country under the dominion 
of Venice, has been already sufficiently described.</p>
            <p>The ultimate fate of this singular region, and especially of the little State whose 
extinction we mean to record, forms a part of the history of Ali Pacha, and of his relations with the 
French revolution. That celebrated chief, indisputably the greatest of the Turkish viceroys, and the 
most brutal barbarian of his age, has been rendered interesting, and in some measure familiar to 
English readers, by the lively and detailed accounts of him that have lately been given to the public, 
both by Mr. Hobhouse and Dr. Holland. Yet his early history, and the unprincipled ferocity of his 
character, have neither of them been well understood: and our readers, we believe, will easily 
excuse us for presenting them with the following brief sketch of them, which we have had the 
means of obtaining from persons of the best information.</p>
            <p>His ancestors were chiefs of the independent clan of the Toozides — 
Mahometans settled in Tepeleni. His grandfather, in the capacity of a Bey appointed by the Porte, 
ruled over a pretty extensive district, adjoining to his hereditary domain, and fell at the siege of 
Corfu. His son, however, was not allowed to succeed to his command, and was plundered by the 
neighbouring Pachas of almost all his possessions. On his death, the young Ali, who was born about 
1750, found himself under the guardianship of a mother, fierce, proud and warlike as any of her 
tribe, — and easily prevailed on her, when only in his sixteenth year, to commit to him the 
command of that faithful domestic band, by the help of which the Albanian widow had imperfectly 
preserved her independence. With those household troops, the youth repeatedly attempted to make 
reprisals on some of his oppressors, but was singularly unfortunate in all his early enterprises. In his 
very first campaign, he was completely routed, and taken prisoner by the Vizir Kourd Pacha, who 
was so much struck with his beauty, vivacity and apparent gentleness, that he was induced to look 
on the whole affair as a piece of youthful folly, and to send him away with a paternal rebuke. In less 
than a year, however, he was again in arms, and again defeated; and his mother's hoards being by 
this time exhausted, he betook himself to the vocation of a robber, to collect funds for a larger army. 
Even in this laudable pursuit, however, he had neither luck nor conduct, — but was speedily 
discomfited and made prisoner by the Vizir of Joannina, who was urged by all the neighbouring 
chieftains to leave the young bandit to the last sentence of the law. But the Vizir was desirous of 
finding occupation for those turbulent chiefs, of whom he was very reasonably jealous; and 
therefore thought fit not only to dismiss his prinner, but secretly to supply him with the means of 
carrying on his depredations. He was destined, however, to acquire his military skill in the school of 
adversity. He was again attacked, and so totally routed, that he was obliged to seek refuge alone 
among the rocks of the mountains, and actually to pledge his scimitar to buy himself a meal. On his 
return in this low condition to his mother's house, he was received by the Amazon with a Spartan 
spirit of disdain, and told that he should put on the habit of a woman, and confine himself to the 
tasks of the Haram. He found means, however, to appease her fiery temper, and again took the field 
at the head of 600 men. But his adverse star was still in the ascendent, — and he was again 
defeated and forced to fly in the night with the broken renmant of his forces. In this disastrous state, 
he went into a ruinous building to rest himself, and meditate, on his cheerless prospects, and 
remained a long time buried in deep thought,and scoring the ground unconsciously with the stick 
which he held in his hand; when it was stopped in its motion by something solid just under the 
surface, — and on stooping to examine the nature of the obstacle, he found a casket 
containing a large quantity of gold. This anecdote he himself communicated to General 
Vaudoncourt; and the occurrence was too critical as well as extraordinary, to be readily forgotten. 
With the money thus strangely obtained, he raised a force of 2000 men, turned suddenly on his 
pursuers, gained his first victory, and returned in triumph to Tepeleni.</p>
            <p>From this period he has been almost uniformly successful, — but has as 
uniformly stained his successes by the most incredible treachery and cruelty. The very day of his 
return to his home, he persuaded the chief men of his followers, that his brother had acted 
perfidiously, and been in correspondence with their enemies, and immediately went with them to 
his apartment, and with his own hand stabbed him to the heart before them. Next day, however, he 
laid the blame of the murder on his mother; who he said had poisoned his unhappy victim, to 
deliver him from a dangerous rival, — and then rewarded this imputed excess of maternal 
partiality, by deposing her from the authority she had hitherto exercised, and shutting her up a close 
prisoner in the haram, — where she speedily died of rage and vexation.</p>
            <p>To maintain and employ his troops, he now resumed his occupation of robbery on a 
more extended scale, and laid under contribution the whole country of Epirus and Macedonia, and 
blockaded the roads leading from the declivities of Pindus into Thessaly. His ravages at last excited 
the attention of the Divan; and the Dervendgi Pacha (or Protector–General of the High 
Roads), was ordered to march out against him. The wily robber, however, contrived first of all to 
defeat his advanced parties, and then to proffer his assistance against the Vizir of Skutari, at that 
time in rebellion against the Porte. The offer was accepted; and the rebellious Vizir being brought to 
submission, the services of Ali were represented in such advantageous colours to the Divan, that he 
was not only forgiven, but received into especial favour; — under the shadow of which he 
speedily recovered all that had been wrested from his father, and pillaged and plundered at his 
pleasure the Beys who had united against him. He was still but twenty years of age, when, after all 
these exploits, he obtained in marriage the daughter of the Pacha of Argiro Castro. Soon after, a 
quarrel arose between two of his brothers–in–law, which he thought would be best 
terminated by instigating the younger to assassinate the elder — which was accordingly 
done, and gave rise to a civil war; from which, however, the abhorrence of the people prevented 
him from deriving all the benefits he expected. In consequence, however, of a subsequent feud, he 
obtained possession of the town of Charmova, where he stabbed the governor, massacred the, 
inhabitants, and sacked and ruined the place. He next attacked the Greek clans of Liebovo, and 
subdued them after a sanguinary resistance; and by these two conquests made himself master of the 
whole valley of the Chelydnus.</p>
            <p>A little time after, the Porte wished to rid itself of Selim Pacha of Delvino; and Ali took 
charge of this commission, on condition of being named Pacha in his place. Accordingly, he 
insinuated himself into his confidence, as well as that of his son Mustapha, and was enabled to 
surround them with his own satellites. He then caused the father to be beheaded, and the son to be 
arrested; but, in spite of these vigorous and judicious measures, he was compelled to fly from the 
indignation and vengeance of their subjects. The merit of his conduct, however, was not overlooked 
at Constantinople; and the Porte considering him as a skilful and intrepid servant, named him 
Lieutenant of the Dervendgi Pacha. The principal, a native of Constantinople, being quite ignorant 
of the country, was dazzled by the hope of dissipating the brigands, by taking for his lieutenant the 
most celebrated of their number. Ali provided them with diplomas; and the chiefs of the robbers 
became legitimate conquerors. This traffic and his own exactions brought him in a large sum of 
money. The Divan, however, finding at last that no road in European Turkey was free, divested the 
Dervendgi Pacha and his Lieutenant of their office. The first, on his return, was regularly beheaded 
at Constantinople: but Ali having prudently sent a good share of his plunder to some of the principal 
ministers, and followed this up with an offer to join the Grand Vizir in the war broken out at this 
period (1787) between Austria, Russia and Turkey, was not only pardoned, but praised and 
promoted. During the war, his military experience, and the valour of his Albanians obtained for him 
general esteem, and at the same time tended greatly to enrich him. But in order to secure to himself 
a retreat in case of disasters, he entered into a secret and treasonable correspondence with Prince 
Potemkin, under the pretext of negociating for the release of one of his nephews who had been 
made prisoner. He has still the imprudent vanity to show a wath set in diamonds presented to him 
by Potemkin, in testimony ‘of esteem for his bravery and talents.’</p>
            <p>After the peace, being possessed of considerable riches, he began regularly to entertain 
agents at Constantinople, in order to watch the rising or declining power of the different ministers, 
and bribe their patronage. By these means he obtained the title of Pacha of Trikala, a small district 
in Thessaly. His vicinity terrified the Greek merchants of Joannina, who feared his exactions. A 
complete anarchy, however, reigned at that time in the town; the government of which was vacant, 
and the subject of bitter contentions and busy intrigues, both among however, composed all 
differences; and the people, and the various competitors for the rule, sent a joint supplication to the 
Divan, that they might have any Pacha but this dreaded freebooter; and actually obtained a 
<emph>firman</emph> prohibiting him from entering the city. By means of his agents, Ali was 
apprised of this order before those who had obtained it: and took his measures with the promptitude 
and audacity which belonged to his character. He presented himself with his troops at the gates of 
the city, and exhibited a <emph>firman</emph> from the Grand Signior, appointing him Dervendgi 
Pacha, and ordering him to enter Joannina without delay. The inhabitants, though stunned with this 
intelligence, did not dare to refuse obedience; and Ali and his forces were quietly garrisoned in the 
citadel. His firman, the reader will easily understand, was a daring forgery of his own, — 
and almost immediately detected. But being now in the military occupation of the city, he 
compelled the inhabitants, under threats of a general massacre, to subscribe an urgent petition for 
his appointment as their governor; and this petition being forwarded to Constantinople along with a 
large sum of money extorted by him from the subscribers, produced such an effect, that he was 
confirmed in the government, and thus became master of the place, which has since been 
distinguished as his capital. Not being quite sure, however, of the forgiveness of the Porte, when all 
things should be known, he thought it as well to make himself strong by alliance, and secured the 
interest of the French resident at Prevesa, through whom he afterwards endeavoured, though 
without success, to open a correspondence with Louis XVI. in the character of an independent 
sovereign.</p>
            <p>Such was the career of Ali up to the era of the French Revolution. The increase of his 
power, and the boldness and desperation of his character, had long given the greatest uneasiness to 
the Venetians, upon whose continental settlements he scarcely disguised his pretensions. All they 
could do was to find work for him in the interior, and to foment insurrections among the clans and 
chieftains whom he had subdued, and was oppressing. Though nominally a subject of the Porte, 
they knew well that his conduct was looked upon with jealousy by that government, and found little 
difficulty in stipulating with them, ‘that Ali should not be permitted to erect any fort on the 
continent within a mile from the coast,’ — a stipulation so rigorously enforced, that, 
while Venice had an existence, he was never able even to fortify his custom–house at 
Salamora, though at the very bottom of the Bay of Arta. It was the possession of Parga that enabled 
the republic to maintain this control over the most faithless and daring of barbarians. Impregnable 
from its position and defences, it was closely connected by the ties of religion, and the relations of 
trade, with all the Christian tribes in the heart of Albania; and naturally became, not only the asylum 
of all who were driven from their homes by the violence of Ali, but the seat of those plots and 
cabals by which his government was continually menaced and disturbed. The Venetians winked at 
all those proceedings, and even encouraged them; but, being at peace with the Turk, they never 
allowed their garrison to take arms against its pretended subjects; and represented the hostilities in 
which the Pargiots were perpetually engaged with the forces of Ali, as mere acts of 
self–defence against the assaults of a banditti, whom no regular government could possibly 
avow. Ali, in his turn, could not but feel the importance of this little settlement; and openly avowed 
his animosity to its brave possessors. No stranger went to see him at Joannina, to whom he did not 
pour out his abuse of the Pargiots. According to him, they were mere robbers and harbourers of 
outlaws; and no part of maritime Greece could be at peace till they were exterminated. Mr. 
Hobhouse seems to have been somewhat influenced by those invectives, in the account he has given 
of this warlike community; but both Col. de Bosset and Mr. Dodwell, who had far better 
opportunities of observation, vindicate them from those aspersions, and represent them as 
remarkably industrious, gay, and hospitable — the men handsome and sober, with more 
than the characteristic bravery of the climate — and the women chaste and unwatched, and 
cheerfully devoted to their primitive tasks and pastimes. All observers indeed concur in stating, that 
the smiling, aspect of this little territory, and the busy prosperity of its inhabitants, formed but lately 
a striking contrast to the wastes and ruins with which it was everywhere surrounded. And now it is 
the very centre and seat of desolation! The voice of gladness has everywhere ceased in its fields; 
and it is more waste and ruinous than any other spot in this region of havoc and oppression! But we 
must resume the thread of our narrative.</p>
            <p>In 1797, Venice fell before the arms of France — and the Ionian Isles paseed of 
course under their dominion. The ready treachery of Ali had already made overtures to Bonaparte, 
and offered to join him against the Turk, provided he would engage for his ultimate protection. The 
conqueror received these proposals favourably, and allowed him to embark troops, and transport 
them to different points of the coast; and, at the same time, furnished him with engineers to conduct 
his sieges, and repair his fortification. In 1798, the Porte having declared war on France on account 
of the invasion of Egypt, the sincerity of Ali was brought to the test. He accordingly recruited his 
forces, and drew out all his powers; and, assuring the agents of Bonaparte that he was waiting for a 
favourable moment to strike a fatal blow at the common foe, he demanded instant payment of 
80,000 livres as the value of provisions which he said had been furnished by him to Admiral Bruix. 
The Governor of Corfu having no money to make payment, presented him with battering cannon in 
exchange; and the double traitor having made all he could of his dissimulation, wrote to the French 
Adjutant–General Roze to come over to him without delay, that they might confer upon the 
best means of opposing the Russian and Turkish fleet that was advancing against them. Roze, who 
was the intimate friend and frequent guest of Ali, went without suspicion or attendants; when he 
was instantly seized, thrust into a dungeon, tortured to extort information, and then sent mangled to 
Contantinople, where he speedily died.</p>
            <p>Having thus taken his part in the quarrel, he proceeded instantly to besiege all the 
French (formerly Venetian) settlements on the mainland; and, by prodigious superiority of numbers, 
and the arms which he had thus treacherously obtained, he speedily succeeded with the most of 
them. Bucintro fell the first — and he proceeded with near ten thousand men to Prevesa. 
This position was more defensible — and the French engineers were busy erecting batteries 
to protect its approaches, when the natives insisted that it would be much better to dig through a 
narrow isthmus by which the enemy must advance — and, although it was explained to 
them that this operation could not possibly be accomplished in time to be of service, they all 
deserted the batteries, and rushed out to work at the excavation. Ali was upon them before any thing 
effectual was done — and, although the defence was obstinate, and the victory most 
sanguinary, he forced his way at last over the dead bodies of his opponents. He took brutal and 
bloody vengeance for their resistance. On the day of the assault, men, women and children were 
butchered till night–fall — and the next morning all the inhabitants fit to bear arms, 
were marched out to the edge of the great ditch they had begun to dig on the isthmus, and there 
barbarously slaughtered. The city itself was set on fire. The very day of this exploit, the conqueror 
addressed the following letter, the original of which, written in Romaic, with a mixture of Albanian, 
now lies before us, to the inhabitants of Parga.

<quote rend="block">
                  <p>‘Learn, men of Parga, the victory of this day, and the fate of Prevesa. In now 
writing to you, I would have you to understand, that being my neighbours, I do not desire war with 
you — but only that two or three of you should come to me, that we may confer about 
making you fellow–subjects of my sovereign. Whatever form of government you wish, I 
will grant to you. But if you refuse, I will deal with you as enemies — and the blame be on 
your own heads.’</p>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The Pargiots made no answer; — and another letter was sent the day following 
— omitting the proposal of subjection to the Turk, but requiring them to massacre or drive 
out the French garrison among them. The following answer which we think was read to the House 
of Commons by Sir Charles Monck, was instantly returned.

<quote rend="block">
                  <p>‘TO ALI PACHA. We have received your two letters, and we rejoice, that you 
are well. The compliance which you require of us, you will not easily obtain; because your conduct, 
exhibited to us in the fate of our neighbours, determines us all to a glorious and free death, rather 
than to a base and tyrannical subjugation. You write to us to fall upon and slay the French. This is 
not in our power; but if it were, we would decline to do it; for our country has boasted her good 
faith for four centuries past, and in that time often vindicated it with her blood. How then, shall we 
now sully that glory? Never. To threaten us unjustly is in your power; but threats are no 
characteristic of great men; and, besides, we have never known what it was to fear, having 
accustomed ourselves to glorious battles for the right of our country. God is just; we are ready; the 
moment comes when he who conquers shall be glorified. So fare you well. Parga, Oct. 16, 
1798.’</p>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>Ali stormed at this reply; but the place was too strong to be attempted by force, and he 
set himself to assail it by art and intrigue. The united arms of the Turks and the Russians had now 
effected the conquest of the Seven Islands; and it became necessary for them to settle their future 
government. By the treaty of,1800, they were erected into an independent republic, under the 
special protection of the two allies; — but unluckily for Parga and the other continental 
towns which had hitherto formed a part of them, Ali found means to have it settled that these should 
all be given up to the Porte. That all these places, with the single exception of Parga, had already 
been won by the arms of Ali, was, no doubt, an apology for this arrangement — and the 
jealousy which existed between the two allied powers of Russia and Turkey, made it difficult to 
come to any very satisfactory arrangement. But there is no doubt that, in consenting to this cession, 
the Russian negociators trusted too much to the chapter of accidents, and reckoned too securely on 
the opportunities which the perfidy and oppression of Ali would afford for resuming possession of 
those continental settlements — by the assistance especially of the Suliotes, whose territory 
lay immediately behind that part of the coast, who had always been faithful to the interests of 
Russia, and upon whose mountain retreats Ali had never been able to make any serious 
impression.</p>
            <p>The result showed but too fatally the errors of this sanguine calculation, — the 
occupation of the coast having enabled the ferocious Ali in a very few years utterly to exterminate 
the heroic warriors of Suli, over whom, till he obtained that commanding position, he had never 
gained any decided advantage. There never was a more bloody or brutal course of warfare than that 
which is detailed by a native of Parga, in one of the works before us, as terminating in the 
extirpation of his brave brethren of Suli; — we can only afford to give the closing scene as a 
specimen. The scanty remnant of the Suliote warriors occupied a strong position on a mountain, 
where for six days they maintained themselves against the desperate attacks of the Mussulmans, 
under the command of an heroic ecclesiastic of the name of Samuel, who had acted as their leader 
for nearly three years. Their provisions and water being cut off, they were at last obliged to 
capitulate, and obtained leave to retire to Parga; and Samuel with four of his officers remained to 
deliver up their stores and ammunition to the commissioners of Ali. They had no sooner entered the 
place, however, than he set fire with his own hand to the magazine, and blew himself and the whole 
party to atoms. The greater part of those who were retreating to Parga, were massacred, without 
distinction of sex or age — a group of women who were pursued to the brink of a precipice, 
dashed their children over the cliffs, that they might not live in servitude to the infidels. One family 
of eight women and three infants — for all the men had fallen in battle — had 
obtained from one of the sons of Ali a promise to be allowed to remain unmolested in the dwelling 
they then occupied; but, a few days after, a party of his soldiers came and insisted on carrying off 
the younger women, and threatened the older ones with death. The desperate inmates having 
obtained a short time for preparation, brought out three barrels of gunpowder which had been 
secreted in the house, and drew in a circle round them. The younger women calmly recited their 
prayers; and the mother, after blessing her unpolluted daughters, and the infant orphans of her sons, 
set fire to the train, and blew the whole in the air! The Pargiots collected their bones, and interred 
them honourably, with an inscription commemorating the manner of their death; and thus was the 
tribe of the Suliotes exterminated in 1803!. But we must return to the treaty of 1800.</p>
            <p>The Pargiots, after many vain entreaties to be incorporated with the new republic, 
succeeded at last in having certain conditions inserted into the treaty, by which the sovereignty, or 
patronage rather, of their State was to be ceded to the Ottoman. The chiefs of the Seven Islands, 
who knew that their subsistence depended chiefly on that community, and the Russians, who were 
far from wishing to put them thus at the mercy of the Porte, exerted themselves in support of their 
just pretensions. And it was at last solemnly stipulated in the definitive treaty, ‘That they 
should retain all the privileges they had enjoyed of old under the Venetians — <hi rend="italic">that no mosque should be built within their territory, nor any Mussulman be allowed 
to settle or hold land within it</hi> — that they should pay no taxes but those which had 
been anciently paid to Venice, and should enjoy their laws both civil and criminal exactly as before 
— and, finally, that to secure the political rights of the new sovereign, a bey or officer of 
rank should be sent from Constantinople, whose functions, and the place of his residence, should be 
determined with the advice, and <hi rend="italic">to the entire satisfaction of the republic of the 
Seven Islands</hi>.’</p>
            <p>This treaty, and the course of succeeding events, were found sufficient to control the 
violence and perfidy of Ali, and to exclude the Turks from the territory of Parga, till the possession 
of it was ceded to the English, and its fate referred to the Congress of Vienna. An Aga, but without 
any troops, occasionally resided in the place; and a Bey on the neighbouring coast rather helped to 
keep Ali faithful to his engagements, than assisted him to infringe them. There can indeed be no 
better or more practical proof of their independence, than that they were allowed, three years after, 
to give refuge to the remnant of the Suliotes when driven finally from their territories by the arms of 
Ali.</p>
            <p>The power of this ferocious chief, however, was now greatly augmented. The Divan, in 
its dread of the establishments of Russia in the islands, lost for a time its jealousy and distrust of the 
most powerful and faithless of its subjects, and appointed him Governor–General of the 
whole of Romelia, with supreme authority over all the Pachas of the Grecian provinces. This great 
power he rendered immediately subservient to his ruling passions of avarice and revenge. He kept 
two–fifths of the contributions he levied for government, for his own use — and 
punished the least delay of payment by brutal and bloody plunder. On one occasion he is said to 
have extorted in this way upwards of ten millions of piastres — and added 20,000 sheep to 
his numerous flocks. In the midst of this wealth and grandeur, however, he found time to avenge on 
the unfortunate inhabitants of Gardiki, an affront which some of them had put upon his mother and 
sister about forty years before. He surrounded their city with his forces, and starved them into a 
capitulation, promising solemnly that they should not be reduced into slavery. When he entered the 
place, he ordered all those who had been concerned in this antiquated offence, and their 
descendants, to be brought before him. Most of the actual delinquents, of course, were dead 
— but their progeny appears to have been numerous; for when their numbers were counted, 
it appeared that there were no fewer than 739 males, and nearly as many of the other sex. The males 
were bound and fastened in regular ranks, in an enclosed area; and the women round the outside of 
the walls. Ali then entered the enclosure, and immediately blew out the brains of the first man he 
came up to. His attendants followed his example; and the whole were butchered on the spot, in the 
hearing of their wives and daughters. They were allowed to rot where they fell — and their 
bones are there yet; — the monster merely shutting up the enclosure, and putting an 
inscription over the door, signifying that it was not to be opened again till his agents, who had been 
despatched all over Greece for that purpose, had collected more of the offenders, to share the fate of 
their associates.</p>
            <p>He looked, however, with unfeigned terror on the growing strength of the Russians; and, 
after the battle of Austerlitz, and the peace of Presburg had restored the ascendancy of France, he 
had the audacity to renew his overtures to Bonaparte — who sent to him, in the capacity of 
consul–general, a certain M. Pouqueville, who, in a gasconading book of travels, had 
enlarged very freely on the vices and infirmities of the Pacha. The English consul, in hopes of 
producing a quarrel, contrived that Ali should hear of this book; but a Mussulman laughs at printed 
abuse, and Ali did not chuse at that moment to hazard a rupture with France for the pleasure of 
decapitating M. Pouqueville. From this time his dependence on the Porte may be said to have been 
merely nominal; for though, in his intercourse with the Divan, he still assumes the style of a 
delegate, he has not only acted in all things at his own discretion but has quietly retained all his 
dignities, without seeking any confirmation of them from the successive Sultans he has outlasted: 
— and though he finds it convenient to send large sums of money every now and then to 
Constantinople, it is rather in the capacity of the munificent ally of every new vizier, than of a 
tributary of the Empire. Nothing, indeed, could be more wretched than the anarchy, or more 
despicable than the feebleness, that had now overtaken this great State, and paralyzed even its most 
meritorious exertions; — insomuch that, when a great force was levied, with the popular 
approbation, to repress the insults of the Russians, the forces, upon reaching the Danube, actually 
found themselves without a leader or instructions — and so thought the best thing they 
could do or instructions — and so thought the best thing they could do was to enlist, in 
pretty equal moieties, in the ranks of the Ayan of Schecunla and the Pehluvian Aga, who were very 
eagerly desolating their country with civil war, in the very face of the common enemy. Ali, in this 
stirring scene, endeavoured to take advantage of all parties; and, in order to come at their secrets, 
made it a practice to open the despatches of all the diplomatic agents in his neighbourhood. In 1807 
alone, he assassinated three couriers; and then, to clear himself of blame, hanged the wretches by 
whose agency the crime had been committed. He was especially anxious, however, to stand well 
with Napoleon — and not quite liking the tone of M. Pouqueville, despatched Mahomet 
Effendi to him in the capacity of his ambassador. This worthy Mussulman had been formerly a 
Dominican friar, and head of the Inquisition at Malta. When he took that island in his way to Egypt, 
Bonaparte had carried the good father along with him as an interpreter. On his return home, his 
reverence was unluckily captured by a Corsair, who gave him in a present to Ali: and he, finding in 
him a decided vocation to Islamism, placed him at the head of his Divan. He danced attendance on 
Bonaparte through the campaign which terminated at Tilsit — and struggled hard to get the 
Ionian islands for his master at the peace. But it pleased the high contracting parties, at this time, to 
spare the young republic; and the eloquence of Mahomet was in vain. Baffled in this great object, 
Ali insisted that Parga at least should be delivered up to him, in terms of the treaty of 1800, as the 
only representative of the Ottoman Porte on the spot: — for the Bey, who had faithfully 
fulfilled that treaty, had been obliged to remove before the advance of the Russians; and at one time 
an order was issued to comply with this request. But, on further consideration of the matter, 
Bonaparte instructed his ambassador to reply, with more regard both to truth and justice than was 
afterwards shown by the Congress, ‘that Ali having violated all the clauses of the treaty 
1800 in favour of the Ex–Venetian towns, the whole stipulations of that treaty, as to those 
towns, must be held as annulled; and that neither he nor the Porte had now any claim to the military 
occupation of Parga.’ In reality, every one of those stipulations had been disregarded as to 
all the towns of which Ali had got possession; and it was merely because he had not been allowed 
to enter Parga, that its rights had been respected.</p>
            <p>Disappointed in his hopes from France, he now paid his court to the English; and 
certainly did receive from us more countenance than either his character or services deserved. Lord 
Collingwood at one time relied on his cooperation in our expedition against the French forces in the 
Seven Islands; but it was soon found that he was not to be depended on; and in fact he never did any 
thing for us whatever, except supplying us with provisions at a dear rate — a favour which 
he extended at the same time to our enemies, even in violation of our blockade. The notice we took 
of him, however, induced Bonaparte to show him a little more attention — after his fashion; 
and accordingly, he sent him several engineers to fortify his seaports, who took the opportunity to 
make a survey of his strengths, and to spy out all the vulnerable points in his positions.</p>
            <p>At last Bonaparte was overthrown; and the French power no sooner ceased to be 
formidable, than Ali darted at once like a raven on his prey, and, so early as March 1814, surprised 
the little town of Agia, which is in the territory of Parga; massacred all the inhabitants; sent the 
women and children to the slave market; raised a fort to maintain his conquest, and marched in open 
hostility against Parga itself. The French, as successors to the Venetians, had a garrison of 200 men 
in the citadel, to whom the inhabitants instantly applied for assistance against this assault. But the 
commander, an Arab who had entered the French service in Egypt, pretended that France, being at 
peace with the Porte, could not fight against a Turkish commander, and declared that he could take 
no part in the business. The inhabitants, thus left to themselves, went out, men and women, to meet 
the invaders; and kept up so hot a fire on their ranks — the women charging and handing 
their muskets to the men — that after a sanguinary struggle, in which one of his nephews 
was slain, Ali was forced to retire, and betake himself to negociation with the French, who being at 
that time blockaded by us at Corfu, he thought could easily give up this more insignificant position 
to purchase his assistance against us. It rather appears, however, that his propositions were rejected. 
But the most material fact to be noticed is, that the Pargiots now made an application to our 
commanders to be taken under British protection, and, after some hesitation, General Campbell sent 
an aid–de–camp to hold a conference with their deputies at Paxo, where, being 
joined by Captain Hoste of the <emph>Bacchante</emph>, and Captain Black of the 
<emph>Havannah</emph>, it was agreed, that they <hi rend="italic">should be taken under the 
protection of Great Britain, and share the fate of the Seven Islands</hi>; provided they would, in 
the first place, send a written declaration, signed by the principal inhabitants, that this was their own 
wish; and, secondly, they should themselves displace the French flag, and mount that of England on 
their citadel, as soon as the two frigates appeared before the town. The deputies agreed to these 
terms, and got a flag, with which they succeeded in getting back to their city in the night; and 
immediately assembled a meeting of the principal inhabitants, to deliberate on the propositions 
which had been made to them. Among these was an aged citizen, regarded among them with great 
veneration, on account of his steady patriotism and extensive knowledge, — though his 
great age and austere disposition had for many years withheld him from taking any very active part 
in their affairs. After listening to the statements of the deputies and other citizens, he is said to have 
delivered the following very remarkable speech, of which we shall endeavour to present our readers 
with a literal translation from the vulgar Greek, in which it is printed in the volume of documents 
before us. In point of political wisdom and manly vigour, as well as in its general tone and manner, 
it seems to us to bear a very striking resemblance to the business speeches we meet with in 
Thucydides; while in some points, on which it would be painful to dwell, the speaker seems to be 
inspired with something of a prophetic spirit.

<quote rend="block">
                  <p>‘Fellow Citizens — The expulsion of the French appears to me to be so 
necessary, that I will not waste words in recommending it. But I exhort you well to consider, before 
you yield yourselves up to the English, that the King of England now has in his pay all the Kings of 
Europe, — obtaining money for this purpose from his merchants; so that in that country the 
merchants and the King are but as one: whence, should it become advantageous to the merchants to 
sell you, in order to conciliate Ali, and obtain certain commercial advantages in his harbours, <hi rend="italic">the English will sell you to Ali</hi>. If, however, you still persist in surrendering 
yourselves to England, beware how you confide in the promises of military men, whose trade, what 
ever may be their dignity, is but that of a servant; therefore, being taught only to obey, they seldom 
have wisdom to weigh their promises, and never have power to fulfil them — as you do, 
because you are all free men. But go and present yourselves before their King: if he mean to be the 
master of this city, let him swear it upon the Gospel of Christ. Yet I would not entirely trust even 
him. For within these twenty years, Christian princes have openly turned their subjects and friends 
into merchandise, and have shown but little regard to the Gospel. But suppose you are once in the 
hand of England — you may be governed well, or you may be governed ill. But the 
<emph>well</emph> is uncertain; and if <emph>ill</emph>, you will have bereft yourselves of all 
remedy. The King of England has not that sword of justice in his hands, that he can, like Napoleon, 
Alexander, or the Sultan, decapitate the misgoverning Pachas of his distant provinces. On the 
contrary, his justice is feeble; because, being surrounded by contending parties, he is compelled to 
lean for support upon one party to–day, and to–morrow upon another, and yet to 
pay regard to all; while each party, in its turn, conceals as much as it can; defends, and often praises 
the blunders of its partisans; so that a governor may treat you as slaves, and yet be fearless of 
punishment. Nor would you, o men of Parga, — I say <emph>you</emph>, because I hope 
soon to lay me down in the peace of God, and be buried by your hands in this church, — nor 
would you be able to obtain redress. This our city is small and poor, and simple and ignorant: 
whence then shall it have power, how find money? and where the learned citizens, who, being sent 
to the King of England, might show him the truth? However, this Parga still possesses those arms 
which have, for so many generations, prevented a single armed Mussulman from entering her walls. 
I say not this that you should be proud of the defeat which that butcher of the Christians lately 
sustained at your hands; for that victory came from God, — God who will not cease to 
protect you as heretofore, and who can do so because he is just, and because he is almighty; whilst 
the Russians and the French, just and unjust, powerful and weak by turns, have, as the fruit of their 
protection, exposed you to inconceivable perils, and kept you for several years in perpetual anxiety. 
These English too are but men: and may you not live to see them expelled from all countries which 
they have no longer money to pay, caged up in their island, and preying upon each other from want? 
Why then recur to foreign aid? Parga is sufficient both to nourish and to defend you. Ali cannot take 
her by land: he cannot blockade her by sea, by which your countrymen in the Islands can always 
supply you with food, and which, in case of extremity, will always afford you an easy escape; 
though I, for my part, let the danger be ever so great, would never exhort you to go forth vagrants 
and beggars, with your wives and children, into a foreign land. Let us all die here at home; and, 
when no way of safety remains for the city, set it on fire, that these Infidels may only triumph over 
our ruined houses and mangled carcasses. However, this danger cannot last long: for as much as Ali 
is now old, and his head is always under the sword of the Sultan, whose wrath, though it has so long 
slept, should it at length awake, no Turk will be able to escape. At all events, as long as you remain 
masters of your own city, so long will you be able to follow that line of conduct, which, under the 
mercy of God, circumstances may render fit. The Infidels, indeed, may force you to give them 
battle, and reduce you to great extremity: yet you will slay many of them to appease the blessed 
souls of so many Christians slain by them. But, once garrisoned by strangers, you will be subject to 
the will of another; you will not be able to use — good fortune, should it ever befal you; and 
you will for ever lose the right of defending your country, and even of burying yourselves beneath 
its ruins near your dear forefathers.’</p>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In spite of this remonstrance, the majority of the meeting resolved to accede to the 
propositions of the English, and to sign the declaration required; upon which the old man refusing 
to set his hand to it, finally reminded them to be careful in enforcing the condition expressed in the 
English offer, that they should follow the fate of the Seven Islands. ‘For you may be 
sure,’ added he, ‘that the English will employ every art of sophistry to subject as 
much as they can of Greece to the Porte, in hope of strengthening it against the dreaded 
preponderance of the Russians. Perhaps when they have once acknowledged your natural 
dependence upon Corfu, they will be unable to betray you, without sacrificing at the same time all 
the Seven Islands to the Infidels; a sacrifice which would cover them with infamy, — 
although, in proportion as men are powerful, they care less for dishonour.’ He then made 
his admonition be recorded in the archives of the city; and the assembly coming out of the church 
before daylight, drew up and addressed to the English commander the following explicit 
declaration.

<quote rend="block">
                  <p>‘We, undersigned Primates of Parga, engage, on behalf of the population, that at 
the moment when the frigates of his Britannic Majesty shall appear before our fortress, we will 
subject our country and territories to the protection of the invincible arms of Great Britain, and will 
plant on the walls of our fortress her glorious flag — it being the determination of our 
country to follow the fate of the Seven Islands, as we have always been under the same jurisdiction. 
— 17th March, 1814.’</p>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>In the course of the day; the <emph>Bacchante</emph> appeared in the roadstead; and 
the British flag was displayed, not from the ramparts of the citadel, but from a low spot near the 
shore. Our officers were not satisfied with this; and, after some negotiation, intimated that unless 
the inhabitants hoisted the British flag on the proper flagstaff of the citadel, they would make sail 
the day after, and leave them to their fate. The French commander had threatened to blow up the 
town by firing the magazine, if any attempt was made to dislodge him; and some speedy and 
decided measure therefore now became necessary. Next morning very early, a widow, pretending 
business with the commander, went into the citadel with the flag concealed under her clothes. She 
was followed by a lad who used to sell fruit and vegetables to the soldiers, and was accordingly 
admitted without suspicion. After ascertaining that everything was in the situation on which his 
friends had reckoned, he gave the signal, by pronouncing, as in the course of crying his vegetables, 
a Greek word on which they had previously agreed; and instantly the sentinels were knocked down, 
and a crowd of armed citizens sprung at once upon every point of the works, some mounting by 
escalade, and others by different passages. In a few minutes they were complete masters of the 
place; and the British flag was triumphantly hoisted on the top of the castle. The 
<emph>Bacchante</emph> immediately came up to the fort. The French garrison were allowed to 
capitulate honourably; and, on the 22d of March, Sir Charles Gordon landed with detachment, sent 
off the French to Corfu, and with his troops took full and solemn possession of the place. Some 
time after, Lord Bathurst, by command of the Prince Regent, expressed to the king's commissioners 
for the government of the Ionian islands, the royal approbation of what had been done in regard to 
the occupation of Parga.</p>
            <p>We come now to the last act of the tragedy. The Congress of Vienna was in session 
when this little republic, and the greater part of the Ionian islands, had been thus taken possession of 
by the English; and their policy in 1814 being to strengthen Austria, as a counterpoise both to 
France and to Russia, all those places would probably have been made over to that power, along 
with the Istrian, Dalmatian, and Venetian provinces that were then assigned to her. But after the 
return of Napoleon, the tardiness of Austria, and the great influence acquired by Russia in the 
Congress of Paris after the victory at Waterloo, led to a different, and, in so far as the Pargiots were 
concerned, much more fatal arrangement. The islands were left to us: but it was agreed, in 
pretended conformity with the treaty of 1800, that the ex–Venetian towns on the coast 
should be given up unconditionally, and in full sovereignty to the Porte — or, in other 
words, to Ali, who took the title of its officer, and was already in possession of all of them but 
Parga. In conformity with this arrangement, Parga was totally extinguished, and its bare and 
deserted walls delivered over to the barbarian, by the agents of that free government to whose 
honour it had committed itself! By what motives our negotiators were induced to consent to this 
miserable sacrifice, it would now be idle to inquire. The common opinion on the Continent is, that 
Lord Castlereagh was cajoled into it by the Russians, who wished to abase our national character, 
and to embroil us with the Turks, by making us dependent on such a neighbour as Ali for the 
provisioning of our forces in the islands. But for our parts, we have no great faith in those 
refinements of Machiavellian policy; and are of opinion, that the worst and most fatal acts of public 
men are far more frequently the fruit of mere ignorance and inattention, than of deep–laid 
schemes of perfidy or ambition. We think it by no means unlikely that the Noble Lord was actually 
ignorant of the compact made between our officers and the Pargiots, and are almost certain, that he 
was not at all aware of the vast importance of that place for the victualling of the islands which we 
were to retain; — while it is difficult to imagine, that he was correctly informed either as to 
the tenor of the treaty of 1800, on which he professed to act, or as to the events that had 
subsequently occurred to discharge all claims under it. Such ignorance, we certainly think, is not 
less criminal in a minister, than the intentional violation of his duties which leads to the same 
results; but it is rather more credible; and requires to be even more loudly reprobated, both as more 
likely to recur, and more possible to be prevented.</p>
            <p>We have spoken of all those occurrences in the calm and dispassionate tone of history; 
and trust we shall not be thought to deviate from it when we add, that an arrangement more 
ungenerous, cruel, and unjust to those who were the objects of it, and at once more dishonourable 
and injurious to those who conducted it, cannot well be imagined, than that we are now considering. 
In the <emph>first</emph> place, it was most impolitic and injurious to our interests, as possessors 
of the Ionian islands; because Parga was almost the only remaining channel through which they 
could be supplied with provisions; — and the Turk, who was known to be thirsting to regain 
them, would thus not only have a prodigious advantage in the event of hostilities, but would be 
constantly tempted to seek a pretext for hostility, in order to make use of this advantage. In the 
<emph>second</emph> place, it was in the face of a treaty recently entered into by our officers, 
and subsequently approved of by our commissioners in the islands, and by the Lord Bathurst, in 
name of the Sovereign. We know very well that it may be argued, that our officers had no proper 
powers to enter into such a treaty; and that the approbation of the Prince Regent, however generally 
expressed, should be understood as applying only to the military occupation of a place previously 
held by the French. But when it is considered, that the place had actually been delivered up to us on 
the faith of that treaty, and retained, to our great profit, for upwards of a year, without the least 
surmise that any of its articles were to be objected to, — and especially that the consequence 
of our tardy disavowal of it was, <emph>not</emph> to replace things <foreign lang="lat">in statu 
quo</foreign>, as ought to have been done upon the most rigorous application of the rules of 
diplomacy — but to make over to their bitterest enemy, as a property or conquest of our 
own, that which, but for such a treaty, we should never have had the power to dispose of — 
it must appear that there never was a case in which this special pleading, or quibbling rather, on the 
law of nations, could be resorted to with so ill a grace or so little plausibility. — But, in the 
<emph>third</emph> place, the treaty of 1800 to which we pretended to recur, had been annulled 
and abandoned by all the parties to it, and especially by the Turks, over and over again, from the 
year when it was adopted down to the year 1815. The leading stipulation in that treaty was the 
establishment of the Seven Islands, under the joint protection of the Porte and Russia. But, so early 
as 1802, the Porte admitted Great Britain as a guarantee of their independence; and, after the peace 
of Tilsit, they were all turned into French colonies, with the assent of Russia. It was sufficiently 
manifest then, that the whole of that original treaty was abrogated and gone. If any thing more, 
however, was wanting, it was supplied by the transactions of 1809, when the Turks themselves 
concluded a peace with Bonaparte, by which they confirmed to him the whole of those conquests, 
including Parga, in which he had placed a garrison. Soon after, Lord Colingwood took from him 
Zante and Cephalonia; and the Turk then professing neutrality, our ambassador at Constantinople 
solemnly protested, ‘that some of the Ionian islands having been delivered from the French 
by our arms, without the assistance of any of the other powers by whom they should have been 
protected, his Majesty has a right to proceed to the settlement of those islands without consulting 
them — and that he will accordingly do so, if the Porte will not now renew its guarantee for 
their protection;’ and not only was this guarantee refused, but their pretended neutrality 
openly violated — not only by supplying the enemy at Corfu with stores and provisions, in 
defiance of our blockade, but by allowing our merchantmen to be taken and condemned as prizes by 
the French privateers within the bounds of the Ottoman ports and harbours. Possession was 
accordingly retained of these conquests, and of the others made in 1814, without any reclamation or 
complaint on the part of the Turks. In the Congress of that year, the basis of the whole proceeding 
was, that all conquests made from France by any of the allies should be at the disposal of the whole 
powers armed against her. But the Porte was not of this number, having all along remained at peace 
with Napoleon, and therefore had no right nor interest in any partition of those conquests. 
Accordingly, the independence of the Seven Island, and <emph>of their dependencies</emph>, 
was expressly stipulated by several treaties signed with Prussia, Russia, Austria and France; and, in 
the Congress of Paris in 1815 and 1816, the Turk had no minister or accredited agent, and was no 
party to their proceedings — so that nothing could be more preposterous and unmeaning, 
than to refer, as to a document of binding authority, to a treaty long ago and repeatedly annulled by 
all the parties to it — and to a stipulation in it, introduced solely for the benefit of a power 
that was in fact making no claim — and of whose claims it was at any rate impossible to 
take cognisance, without utterly disregarding the very basis and foundation of the whole scheme of 
adjustment. If we had any right at all to dispose of Parga, it was on the supposition that we had 
taken it by force of arms from France; — but all conquests <emph>from France</emph> 
were to be distributed among the powers allied to control her — and the Porte neither was 
one of these powers, nor one of the parties assembled to deliberate on the partition. She neither had 
any right, nor pretended to any.</p>
            <p>But, in the <emph>fourth</emph> place, and finally, — if all these things had 
been otherwise — if we had had no interest to keep Parga from the Turks — if they 
had never renounced and annulled the treaty of 1800 — if they had been belligerents allied 
against France, and parties to the Congress which was to dispose of what that alliance had wrested 
from her; we say, with the most unlimited confidence, that all this would have afforded no 
justification, or apology even, for the act of which we are now speaking, and would still have left it, 
though stripped, no doubt, of some aggravations, one of the most flagrant instances of impolicy and 
oppression of which history has preserved any record; — and that because what was then 
done in pretended implement of the treaty of 1800, <emph>was no implement of that 
treaty</emph>, but a mere sanction to the Porte to violate it in all that gave it a colour of justice, as 
it had already shown its determination to violate it. That treaty, no doubt, after stipulating as its 
main object for the independence of the Seven Islands, did also provide that the political dominion 
or patronage of the ex–Venetian towns on the coast should be given up to the Porte; 
— but then it was an integral part and express condition of this stipulation, ‘that no 
Mahomedan should acquire property or settle in any of those towns — nor build mosques 
within their territory — nor change their laws or internal polity, nor levy taxes or duties 
beyond those that were payable of old by the Venetians; — and that the powers and 
functions of the bey or officer who was to attend to the interest of the Ottoman in the place, should 
be determined to the entire satisfaction of the republic of the Seven Islands.’ — 
These were the stipulations of the treaty of 1800; — but when we thought fit to revive that 
treaty in 1815, and to plead the necessity of adhering to it, as a reason for disavowing the compact 
by which, and by which alone, we had got possession of the place in question, <emph>we did not 
think fit to renew any one of these stipulations</emph> — but gave up those who had 
trusted every thing to our generosity and honour, without even a recommendation to the mercy of 
their most inveterate enemy. Nor could we possibly suppose that these conditions would, without 
express stipulation, be fulfilled for Parga, which had been broken in every other quarter. Ali had 
taken possession of the other towns referred to in the treaty of 1800, not in virtue of that treaty, but 
by force of arms — and all, except one, before the treaty had been thought of. It was 
notorious that he had dealt with them all like conquered places — built mosques and 
seraglios within them — subverted the laws — alienated the property, and enslaved 
the people. He had afterwards made the same attempt repeatedly on Parga — and had only 
been prevented from reducing it to the same condition, by the valour of its inhabitants, and the 
extraordinary strength of its position. In these we have seen that the wisest of its citizens were still 
for confiding, when it was given up to us, and to our promises of protection in 1814 — and 
in less than two years after, it was transferred <emph>unconditionally</emph> to Ali, who never 
disguised his intention to treat it like a conquered place, nor pretended the least regard to the 
stipulation in its favour contained in that treaty of 1800, in conformity to which we held ourselves 
bound to place it at his disposal! — Nothing, we think, but utter helplessness could have 
extorted from us a sacrifice so lamentable and degrading; — and if England, in the Congress 
of 1815, to which the Turk was not so much as a party, had actually been in such dread of the Turk 
as to be obliged to do an unjust and dishonourable act to appease him, we cannot help thinking, that 
it would have been less humiliating to have made the melancholy submission directly and openly, 
than to seek to disguise it under the pretence of fulfilling a treaty no longer in existence, and which 
we did not even attempt to enforce, in those reciprocal conditions under which alone the party to 
whom we yelded, could ever have pretended a right to its fulfilment.</p>
            <p>If minor considerations could have any chance of being listened to, when those higher 
ones had failed, it might also, one would think, have occurred, that the Porte could not be very 
seriously desirous to increase the power of a subject already so formidable — and that the 
whole history of Ali had shown, both that concessions increased his insolence, and that he could 
never be a good neighbour to those of whom he did not stand in awe. It is true that, like other 
savages, lie hates those whom he is compelled to fear; but it is not less true, that fear is the only 
feeling by which his ferocity can be controlled. The Russian commanders always treated him with 
insult, and were always flattered and courted in return. One of them struck one of his Beys in his 
presence, upon which the tyrant quietly withdrew, and propitiated the offender with presents. In the 
same way, after murdering General Roze, who had treated him with uniform kindness, he submitted 
to the daily checks and menaces of Pouqueville, by whom he was replaced. The instances of his 
abusing the good nature of the English are innumerable. Having been permitted by Sir Hudson 
Lowe to repair two customhouses on a point opposite to our island of Santa Maura, he instantly 
changed them into two strong forts, with batteries commanding the island, and capable any day of 
reducing it. On another occasion, he seized on a citizen of Prevesa, who was brother to the 
contractor who supplied our troops in Santa Maura with bread, andthreate ned <emph>to roast him 
alive</emph> if the contractor would not give up his son to serve as an eunuch in his seraglio. This 
brutality was notorious in our quarters; but it was not thought fit to interfere — and the poor 
man was obliged to sacrifice his child to save the life of his brother. One of our own officers was 
afterwards fired at, and grievously wounded, by three of his soldiers — and we were 
satisfied with having the assassins delivered up at Parga, — to be immediately returned to 
their master, who continued them in his service, and employed them on the same frontier which 
they had polluted by so base a crime.</p>
            <p>This strange forbearance of the English — the resort of travellers of our nation to 
his court — the formal visits paid him by his majesty's commissioners, and not returned, 
gave an unfortunate plausibility to the false reports which he industriously circulated as to the entire 
devotion of our government to his views, and the bribery by which he had secured the good offices 
of all our commanders on the spot. He had even the audacity to print in his gazettes, that Sir 
Thomas Maitland had been invested with the order of the Crescent, entirely through his influence, 
and on account of his attachment to him and to the interests of the Porte. When it was first 
rumoured, therefore, at Parga, that they were to be delivered up to their ancient enemy, the most 
dreadful apprehensions were entertained, — and an earnest supplication addressed to the 
British commander in the garrison, who answered, in March 1817, by orders of Sir Thomas 
Maitland, that as he had not yet received the regular instructions of his government, he could give 
them no definitive answer; but that they might depend on his doing all in his power for their 
advantage, provided they did not forfeit their claim to his protection by any violence or bloodshed 
on their own part.</p>
            <p>The substance of the arrangement was now generally known; and as nobody doubted, or 
affected to doubt, of the manner in which Ali was to treat the place when made over to him, the 
humanity and honour of our commissioners could suggest nothing farther than to offer an asylum in 
the islands to such of the citizens as might not be disposed to remain, and to stipulate that Ali, on 
behalf of the Turkish government, should pay a fair price for the lands, buildings and plantations 
that might be thus deserted by their owners; — and Sir Thomas Maitland accordingly 
authorized the British commander to exhibit a letter, in which ‘he pledged himself that the 
place should not be yelded up till the property of those who might chuse to emigrate should be paid 
for, and they themselves transported to the Ionian Islands;’ and a proclamation was 
afterwards published at Parga, in which the same obligations are expressly undertaken in name of 
the British government. Ali did not venture openly to oppose a measure of justice, thus powerfully 
supported and enforced; and appointed Hamed Bey to act as his commissioner in making the 
necessary surveys and valuations along with Mr. Cartwright, who was named on behalf of our 
Government. But he had recourse to every resource of intimidation and chicane to prevent it from 
being brought to a conclusion. Mr. Cartwright applied to the British commander in the citadel, to 
give him a general idea of the total value of the possessions that might be left; and was answered, 
that, on the supposition that the whole people were to emigrate, it would probably amount to 
between 400,000 and 600,000 l. Sterling. The commander afterwards directed a particular survey 
and valuation to be made of the lands, houses and plantations, and found that the total considerably 
exceeded the largest of the sums which we have mentioned. These valuations, however, were 
objected to, as having been made without proper authority; and something less than a third part was 
ultimately awarded. In the mean time, Ali surrounded the city with his troops — insisted on 
his commissioner being received with fifty horsemen — and not only did all he could to 
seduce some of the lower citizens to rise upon the English garrison, and admit him unconditionally 
into the town; but proposed to them to poison our water and provisions; and reported to every one, 
that he never would pay one farthing, but would shortly make good his entry by force, and that the 
Divan had agreed with Sir Robert Liston to give our generals 60,000 l. to put a stop to the plan of 
emigration; and this produced such a panic and alarm in the settlement, that scarcely any one would 
proceed with the cultivation of his fields: and a great proportion sold their neglected lots at an 
undervalue to greedy adventurers. The commissioners, however, at last met in June 1816, and soon 
after published each of them a proclamation, — ours repeating so far the assurances of a 
safe–conduct and fair compensation for the property of those who might chuse to emigrate, 
but leaving the question of emigration to their own free and unbiassed determination — and 
that of Hamed urging the citizens to remain in their native town, and declaring that they should 
enjoy all liberty, security and comfort; — although, when urged by our officers, as well as 
the Pargiots, to put his name and seal to this declaration, he positively refused to do so, and would 
give no further explanation. After these proclamations had been circulated for some days, all the 
citizens of Parga were brought, one by one, before the two commissioners, and called upon, with 
much solemnity, to declare their final resolution, — when they <emph>every one</emph> 
answered, ‘that they were resolved to abandon their country, rather than stay in it with 
dishonour; and that they would each disinter and carry along with them the bones of their 
forefathers.’</p>
            <p>The commissioners then proceeded to their surveys and valuations; but they soon 
differed with each other, and with the Governor, and were respectively superseded. A conference 
then took place between Ali and General Maitland in October, which resulted in a suspension of all 
proceedings till May 1818, when a new commissioner was appointed on our part, before whom, and 
the agent of Ali, the whole citizens again repeated their fixed determination to leave their country, 
in the same terms as in the preceding year; and new disputes arose about the mode of valuing the 
churches, public buildings, and property belonging to incorporations. The Pargiots, who were now 
reduced to the greatest distress, sent over a statement of their case, with the necessary documents, to 
be laid before the British Parliament; but having addressed them to a person who was not a British 
subject, he did not think himself entitled to make any formal application in their name, though we 
have reason to believe that the notice which has been taken of their case in Parliament originated in 
this communication. In the mean time, the proceedings went tardily on; and at last, in June 1819, 
General Maitland, in consequence of the depreciation of property by the neglect and despair of its 
owners, finally declared the compensation to be paid by Ali for the Turkish government to be 
142,425 <hi rend="italic">l</hi>. Sterling; and, shortly after, intimated to the citizens, that he was 
ready to provide for their transportation to the islands.</p>
            <p>As soon as this notice was given, every family marched solemnly out of its dwelling, 
without tears or lamentation; and the men, preceded by their priests, and followed by their sons, 
proceeded to the sepulchres of their fathers, and silently unearthed and collected their remains, 
— wich they placed upon a huge pile of wood which they had previously erected before one 
of their churches. They then took their arms in their hands, and, setting fire to the pile, stood 
motionless and silent around it, till the whole was consumed. During this melancholy ceremony, 
some of Ali's troops, impatient for possession, approached the gates of the town; upon which a 
deputation of the citizens was sent to inform our Governor, that if a single Infidel was admitted 
before the remains of their ancestors were secured from profanation, and they themselves, with their 
families, fairly embarked, they would all instantly put to death their wives and children, — 
and die with their arms in their hands, — and not without a bloody revenge on those who 
had bought and sold their country. Such a remonstrance, at such a moment, was felt and respected, 
as it ought by those to whom it was addressed. General Adam succeeded in stopping the march of 
the Mussulmans. The pile burnt out — and the people embarked in silence; — and 
Free and Christian Parga is now a stronghold of ruffians, renegadoes, and slaves!</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="Appendice on Parga">
            <head>APPENDICE ON PARGA</head>
            <p>I. — <foreign lang="grc">Ιστορία 
Σουλίου καὶ 
Πάργας, 
περιέχουσα τήν 
χρονολογίαν καὶ 
τοὺς αὐτῶν 
πολέμους μετὰ τοῦ 
Ἀλῆ πασῖα</foreign>: viz. <title>TheHistory of Suli 
and Parga</title>, <hi rend="italic">containing their Chronology as well as their Wars against Ali 
Pacha</hi>. Venice 1815.</p>
            <p>II. — <hi rend="italic">A series of Historical and Political authentic Documents, 
beginning from the year 1401 and ending with the year 1818, to be presented to the Parliament of 
Great Britain in behalf of the Citizens of Parga</hi>. This collection of Documents, intended to be 
published in 1818, is still inedited.</p>
            <p>III. — <hi rend="italic">Proceedings in Parga and the Ionian Islands, with a 
series of Correspondence and other justificative Documents. By Lieutenant — Colonel C. P. 
DE BOSSET</hi>. London 1819.</p>
            <p lang="fra">LE DÉBAT sur Parga dans la Maison des Communes, ayant commencé trop 
tard pour en empêcher la cession aux Turcs, tomba de lui–même; et la transaction est encore 
enveloppée de ténèbres. Maintenant il s'agit de satisfaire la curiosité publique sur un événement si 
éclatant, et d'en examiner l'importance à l'égard du droit des gens, et connoître les système 
diplomatique que trente ans de révolutions et de guerres ont fini par établir en Europe.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Pour instruire utilement nos lecteurs et les mettre en état de décider la 
question il suffit de leur tracer l'histoire des Albaniens, de Ali Vizir et de Parga.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">D'après les recherches et les excavations entreprises par le Lieut. 
Col. de Bosdet, qui le premier a examiné le pays, il en resulte</foreign> that no antique coins nor 
any vestiges of Grecian ruins are traced in the small district of Parga, which might lead to a 
probable conjecture upon its history in remote ages. The only remains of antiquity are of Roman 
origin, near a little church, where a few coins of the lower empire are occasionally found. The city 
was once situated beyond the limits of its actual territory, at the spot called <foreign lang="grc">Παλια Παργα</foreign> (<title>Ancient 
Parga</title>), which still exhibits the ruins of some dwellings. In the imminent fall of the lower 
empire the Pargiottes built their new city on the coast of Epirus, on a conical rock, the base of 
which is washed on three sides by the sea. It is thus situated between two bays, which afford 
landing places for the shipping of the country and the commerce of the Ionian Islands with the 
continent; et le rocher par lequel elle est backed du côté de terre est haut, rapide, escarpé et 
entrecoupé de ravins de manière à la rendre imprennable. This natural fortress is crowned by a 
citadel, where the commandant of the garrison resided. It embraces a magnificent prospect, 
including on one hand the whole territory of Parga and the mountains of Albania, by which it is 
bounded; from east to west, in a southerly direction, the eye ranges over a part of the Ionian Sea; on 
the left are seen the Isle of Santa Maura and the Promontary of Leucade, from whence Sappho 
precipitated herself; further on

<quote rend="block">
                  <lg lang="lat">
                     <l>Jam medio apparet fluctu nemorosa Zacynthos</l>
                     <l>Dulichiumque Sameque et Neritos ardua saxis,</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>

together with the dark mountains of Cephalonia: on the right, at the distance of twelve miles, are the 
Islands of Paxo and Antipaxo. The inhabitants of Parga were never more than five thousand, and in 
the times of the plague and long wars never less than three thousands. Their principal occupations 
were always agriculture, navigation and war. By the industry of the people and the fertilizing 
influence of the springs and rivulets, which water the soil in every part, this spot is the most smiling 
to the travellers in Greece. The neighbouring people, labouring under lingering diseases, land at 
Parga to enjoy the remedies of the purity and salubrity of the water and air. In the little valley, 
formed by the undulating hills; are plantations of citrons, oranges and especially cedars. The 
remainder of this little country, with the exception of some fields and vineyards, is covered with 
olive trees, varied by the oak, plane — trees, and cypresses scattered over the land. <foreign lang="fra">Les habitans ne jouissoient des bienfaits de la nature, et de l'industrie qu'en les 
défendant les armes à la main</foreign>, and the steep mountain which separates them from the 
Albaniaii clans and from the Turkish dominions, was, for more than four centuries, <foreign lang="fra">le champ de batailles journalières</foreign>.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Les Vénitiens étoient maîtres du commerce de l'Adriatic et de l'Archipel. 
Leur politique contribua plus que leur puissance à les rendre arbitres de la Grèce, déchirée alors par 
le carnage des guerres civiles et par les gouverneurs militaires, rebelles à leur souverain, et qui sont 
les avant–courreurs de la dissolution des empires. Les Vénitiens, sans affecter de faire des 
conquêtes et sans épuiser leur trésor en des guerres lointaines, prenoient sous leur protection les 
villes, qui impuissantes de résister à leur discorde intestine, et aux ennemis du dehors, avoient 
recours à la République. D'abord le Sénat Vénitien commençoit en médiateur et pacificateur des 
villes, ensuite il s'engageoit de former avec elles une confédération perpétuelle. L'alliance du faible 
et du fort manquoit rarement de produire son effet naturel: et les peuples protegés finissoient par 
être des colonies et des provinces tributaires gouvernées d'après le caprice et l'avarice des 
Patriciens que l'on envoyoit de Vénise. Chaque ville faisoit un traité séparé, obtenoit des privilèges 
différens de ceux de leurs voisins, s'administroit par des lois péculières, et en se réunissant toutes à 
Vénise, elles continuoient d'être divisés entr'elles. En perdant le pouvoir de se désoler par des 
guerres réciproques, elles perdoient aussi la liberté de se confédérer entr'elles pour repousser des 
armées étrangères, ou pour se soustraire au joug de leurs communs oppresseurs. C'est ainsi que les 
Isles Ioniennes, le Péloponnèse, Candie et Cypre, et même les villes italiennes, qui s'étoient réunis 
spontanément à Vénise, oublièrent peu–à–peu d'être des alliées, et subirent le 
traitement des sujets d'autant plus sévère qu'ils étoient redoutés pour les anciens droits qu'ils 
pouvoient réclamer. Le sort de Parga fut en cela tout–à–fait différent. Ses habitans 
furent reçus comme protégés et congfédérés de Vénise le vingt–unième jour de Mars, l'an 
1401, avec les concessions de se gouverner selon les institutions et les lois de leurs ancêtres 
— de n'être jugés que par des juges choisis parmi eux — de n'être jamais cedés en 
échange aux autres puissances — d'être totalement exempts de taxes, de capitations, de 
customs of import and export, et de ne payer que la moitié des dutien, lorsqu'ils trafiquoient dans 
des ports de le rapublique — de n'être enrollés dans l'armée, ni dans la militia, et de 
combattre uniquement pour défendre leur propre territoire, et les possessions vénitiennes sur la côte 
d'Albanie. Le Sénat avoit le droit d'envoyer un gouverneur résider dans la ville et une garnison de 
soldats italiens ou esclavons. Le pacte fut reconfirmé, le neuvième jour d'Août en 1447, dans une 
chartre signée par le Doge Foscarini. Parga fut brûlé par les Ottomand vers le 1500 et vers le 1560. 
Les citoyens se recouvroient parmis les chrétiens leur voisins habitateurs indépendans des 
montagnes. Après plusieurs années de persévérance ils réussissoient à rebâtir leurs maisons et leurs 
églises sur le même terrein où il n'y était resté que les ossemens de leurs pères. Il prévoyoient que 
s'ils eussent cherché asyle dans les iles Vénitiennes, leur nation se serait amollie par les vices de ses 
hôtes, habituée au même esclavage, et fondue parmi les insulaires jusque à perdre bientôt le 
souvenir de son origine. Les Pargiottes n'envoyèrent des Ambassadeurs à Vénise pour renouveler la 
confédération que lorsqu'ils se virent en état d'exiger les anciens privilèges: ils y ajoutèrent la 
demande que leur ville fusse fortifiée au dépens des Vénitiens, et que le sénat prétât une somme 
d'argent à acheter du bois pour rebâtir les maisons des familles pauvres. La fortification fut décrété 
et mise en exécution en élevant les murailles et la citadelle que l'on voit encore de nos jours: et au 
lieu de l'emprunt, le sénat leur fit présent d'une quantité de bois de construction. Les actes de cette 
ambassade et la nouvelle chartre qui ratifiait les anciennes furent signées le cinquième jour de 
Février 1511 par le doge Mocenigo. Et si ensuite quelque gouverneur de Parga imitait ses collègues 
qui, dans les îles, abusoient du pouvoir, les Pargiottes held him under arrest until justice was 
obtained from Venice. En exposant leurs raisons ils rappelloient toujours au sénat que les pactes 
avoient été jurées sur l'évangile. L'intérêt de la partie puissante et le courage déterminé de la partie 
faible, fesoient respecter les serments, et les privilèges de Parga se conservèrent jusqu'en 1797 
époque de la ruine de Vénise.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">L'importance que les Vénitiens mettoient à avoir des possessions 
fortifié et des sujets dévoués sur les côtes de l'Albanie, est difficilement sentie, hormis par ceux qui 
connoissent l'histoire et le caractère des habitans de cette contrée. C'est une région entrecoupée en 
toute direction de hautes montaignes qui en même temps l'entourent et la défendent de toute part 
excepté du côté où elle est baignée par la mer Ionienne; et ce rivage aussi est ou escarpé de rocher, 
ou défendu par des fortifications militaires</foreign>. The inhabitants of those savage mountains, 
which the fancy of ancient poets has delighted to paint in the most terrific colours, appear the 
ferocious off–springs of a rugged soil They are distinguished, even in a land of barbarians 
for the singular cruelty and implacability of their disposition.</p>
            <p>They never lose sight of their revenge. Amongst them a murderer is pursued by the 
family of the deceased: neither time nor future benefits can obliterate the injury which can only be 
expiated by the blood of the offender, or of one of his kin. Thus the protection of an individual often 
becomes the concern of his village, and the friends of the provoked party also flying to arms, the 
enmity spreads from families to towns, and from towns to districts. The men of one mountain watch 
those of a neigbouring hill, and neither sow nor reap, nor tend their flocks singly or unarmed. 
Should one of them wander beyond the precincts of protection he would be stalked like a dear, and 
that without seeing his ennemy. — In many parts of the country the sowing and reaping of 
the harvest is delegated to the women, the old and the infirm, and only those labours which require 
the strength and skill of man such as the felling of timber, and the cultivation of the vineyard, fall to 
the lot of the young mountaineer. Averse from every habit of active industry, it is with less 
unwillingness that they vander on the mountains or in forests with their flocks and lerds: for the life 
of the shepherd in a life both of lazines and peril. But the delight of an Albanian, when unoccupied 
by the wars of his Pasha, or his village is to look in the sunrise, to smoke, to doze or to stroll slowly 
round the garden of his cottage tinkling his tuneless lute. Yet though idle, he is still restless and 
ready to seize his gun, and plunge into the woods at the first sommons of his chief. In the pursuit of 
riches, there is no toil or danger which they will not encounter; but they prefer the life of the soldier 
to that of the husbandman, and with much greater alacrity support the labours of war than those of 
agriculture.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Cette description qu'en fait des voyageurs récents est à peu près la même que 
les écrivains de tout âge nous donnent des Albanais. Les vicissitudes des siècles n'ont changé 
presque rien ni au caractere, .ni presque pas au langage de ce peuple. Ils parloient anciennement un 
jargon melé d'illirien et de gree, inintelligible aux Grecs et aux Illyriens; et comme cette contrée a 
été de tout temps le repaire des outlaws de toutes les nations, leur langage a participé des mots 
Latins, Teutoniques, Turcs, et Arabes aussi bien que de toute les langues que l'on parle 
actuellement en Europe. Le grand nombre de racines:des mots appartenant a tant de tribus 
différents, dont quelques–unes ont conservé leur langue primitive, ont mis en doute les 
savants sur l'origine des Albanais. En effet outre leur dialecte commun, l'on parle dans quelques 
villages l'esclavon, dans d'autres le grec vulgaire, et dans d'autres le Wallach. Le fond de la nation 
consiste d'Illyriens, et de Grecs. Il paraît que quelques bandes indisciplinées Illyriennes en émigrant 
vers le sud ont mis un terme à leur course vagabonde parmis ces montagnes; en même temps que du 
côté de la Grèce arrivèrent les outlaws que la civilisation et les constitutions des républiques 
grecques forçoient ou de renoncer à la piraterie et au brigandage, ou de se réparer vers les 
montagnes ou ils pouvoient continuer de mener une vie indépendante, guerrière et prédatoire. Ils 
font encore aujourd'hui la guerre en brigands, en aventuriers, et en soldats mercénaires, comme ils 
l'ont faite des temps le plus reculés. On en compte quelques–uns d'eux parmi les 
Argonautes qui d'un port non loin de l'Albanie firent la première expédition maritime de la Grèce. 
Leurs fils allèrent contre Troie parmi les troupes invincibles d'Achilles, et leurs descendants 
envahirent le territoire de Rome avec le roi Pyrrhus. Ils servirent à ébranler la liberté de la Grece 
avec Philippus, et à conquérir une grande partie du monde avec Alexandre. Dans le XV siècle 
guidés par George Castriotto leur concitoyen, connu sous le nom de Scanderberg, ils fermèrent aux 
Ottomans l'Albanie, et les passages de l'Adriatique; et dans le XVI siècle, en suivant Abraham qui 
fût aussi leur concitoyen, ils ont parcourru en conquérants la Syrie, la Mésopotamie, et l'Arabie. Ce 
furent eux qui ont prêté souvent leur service lorsque des chefs entreprennants ont fait des émeuttes 
dans l'empire Ottoman; les Janissaires redoutés par leurs souverains, redoutent les Albanais. 
Mustapha Bairactar les employa, il y a peu d'années, à dompter la garde du Sultan, et la garnison de 
Constantinople. En général il préfèrent de vendre leurs services aux Pachas qui aspirent de se rendre 
indépendants de la Porte. Ils ont aidé Ali Vizir de Jannina à usuper une grande portion de la Grece, 
et maintenant ils continuent de se battre pour rendre Mahomed Ali souverain absolu de l'Egypte. Le 
Pacha peut contenir tous ses sujets, hormis la garde Albanese. Il la craint, et pour se faire craindre il 
en exagère le nombre. L'exacte description que le Dr. Holland donne de leur tactique suffit à 
convaincre qu'ils ne pourroient pas résister long temps aux armées disciplinées des européens. Mais 
il ne se laissent presque jamais amener à une bataille campale; ils évitent les grandes pleines où nos 
manoeuvres et nos artilleries peuvent les cerner ou les éparpiller. Leur manière de combattre leur a 
été apprise par la nature de leur montagnes qu'ils défendent depuis leur enfance avec des combats 
journalieres, des ruses perfides, et une bravoure opiniâtre, qui quelquefois a été fatale aux armées 
les plus disciplinées. L'issue malheureuse de la seconde expédition anglaise en Egypte a dépendu 
en grande partie de la défaite que les Anglais reçurent à Rosetta par les Albanais.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Leur caractère qui n'a jamais cedé ni aux loix, ni aux douceurs de la 
civilisation, les faisait considérer, même du temps de la république Romaine comme des ennemis de 
toutes les nations. C'est l'expression avec laquelle ils sont désignés par Polibius contemporain de 
Flaminius. Ce général, qui était en même temps le plus adroit des politiciens, se fit un parti en 
Grece ayant l'air de lui redonner la liberté, et il s'y prit de manière à l'asservir indirectement aux 
Romains. Il tacha alors de donner aux Albannais des institutions civiles, et d'en faire des alliés et 
des sujets à Rome; mais il s'apperçut bientôt qu'il était plus facile de les détruire avec le fer, que de 
les gouverner par des loix. Il les abbandonna à eux–mêmes; et à mesure que la puissance 
croissante de Rome leur empêchait de parcourir en larrons le continent et la mer de la Grèce, et de 
profiter des guerres de petits–états, ils tournèrent leurs armes et leurs rapines contre eux 
mêmes. Trois générations après Flaminius, Strabon les décrit réduits sur les montagnes vivant de 
pillages, et sans d'autre repaire que des cavernes, tandis que leurs villes, et leurs campagnes dans 
les plaines étoient dévastés et incendiés par leur propres ravages. Mais les Romains en se souciant 
fort peu de l'intérieur de l'Albanie et de ses habitans, et en les enclavant parmis les camps 
permanens de leurs légions, prenoient le plus grand soin pour en fortifier toutes les côtes. Ils les 
croyoient le point intermédiaire entre l'Occident et l'Orient; et ils considéroient les Iles Ioniennes 
comme le seul chemin pour porter leur commerce, leur influence politique et leurs conquêtes en 
Asie. Des qu'ils commençoient à étendre leur puissance en Italie, Pyrrhus en sortant de l'Albanie 
les a mis a deux doigt de leur perte; et la gloire d'avoir forcé ce Roi à se retirer fit pour la premiere 
fois connaître le nom des Romains à la Grece. Ensuite ils ne pousserent leur armes vers l'Orient 
qu'après avoir délogé de la Macédoine, de l'Epirus, et des côtes de la mer Ionienne les successeurs 
de Pyrrhus et d'Alexandre. En combattant en Grèce jusqu'aux temps de Sylla, et en Dalmatie sous 
les premiers empereurs, les romains forcèrent les débris des armées des vaincus à émigrer de leur 
patrie; et quelques hordes....</p>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <p>This was and is still now in many districts the profession of the habitants of Mount 
Tomarus as well as of the Pindus and Laomus. Among them the name of <foreign lang="grc">Κλέφτης</foreign>(<emph>Robber</emph>), 
is no dishonour. <foreign lang="fra">Ceux d'entr'eux qui habitent le west de l'Albanie et sont près 
de la Dalmatie, et qui sont fameux sous les noms de Montenegrini</foreign> (<emph>the 
inhabitants of the Black Mountain</emph>) <foreign lang="fra">sont en partie catholique; et en 
grande partie de la religion grecque: ceux–ci n'ont d'autre juge, d'autre prince, d'autre 
général que leur évèque: ils parlent l'esclavon. Quelques–uns sont des chrétiens, mais la 
plus grande partie professent l'Alcoran, sans en remplir trop scrupuleusement les pratiques, et sans 
même savoir de quelle maniere et à quelle époque leurs ancêtres l'ont embrassé: leur orgueil autant 
que leur ignorance leur font désavouer leur subjection aux Turcs lorsque dans le XV et le XVI 
siècle rien ne pouvant leur résister en Grèce, ils mettoient au fil de l'épée tous tous les vincus qui 
refusoient de connaître la mission divine de Mahomet. Les Arnauts ont cependant droit de vanter 
leur ancienne origine; ils le prouvent par le mépris insultant avec lequel ils traitent les Turcs. Les 
prêtres, toute religion qu'ils prêchent, ne sont pas trop respectés; et un Dervis est souvent chassé et 
battu par eux autant qu'un ecclésiastique grec, et ils marient souvent les Chrétiens et les 
Mahométans. Les clans indépendants qui habitaient vers l'est sur les montagnes voisines de la 
Grèce sont tous des chrétiens, qui reconnaissent le patriarche de Constantinople: avant qu'ils fussent 
mis sous le joug et le fer par Ali Pacha, ils étaient les guerriers les plus redoutables aux Pachas 
Turcs, et les voleurs les plus déterminés; et qui par esprit de religion et de liberté faisaient une 
guerre à outrance contre tous leurs voisins qui n'étaient pas des chrétiens. Les Souliotes les plus 
braves entre eux, ne furent domptés qu'en 1803. Ils n'étaient pas plus de trois milles; mais leurs 
montagnes presque inaccessibles, l'habitude qu'ils avaient i les défendre, et leur courage, obligerent 
Ali Pacha à employer toutes ses ruses, toutes ses forces, et vingt–neuf ans de guerres pour 
les disperser.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p lang="fra">La partie de l'Albanie sous la Porte est distribuée à des Pachas, et à des Beys, 
qui tout en professant leur dévouement aux ordres du Sultan, tachent de se rendre maîtres 
indépendents de leurs provinces, et,ils les gouvernent en princes absolus. Ils faisaient la guerre 
entr'eux pour accroître leur territoire. Les Pachas et les Beys qui avaient hérités des districts et des 
villes usurpées par leurs peres, et dont les familles descendoient d'anciens tribus Albannoises, se 
servaient des guerriers de leurs tribus pour enlever la province des nouveaux Pachas envoyés de 
Constantinople. Du butin sur le Pacha vaincu, on en envoyait une partie au Divan, qui se laisse 
aisément corrompre; et qui en même temps est épouvanté par les victoires, et la puissance du 
conquérant. Peut–être aussi que c'est la politique de la Porte de laisser en guerre civile des 
Pachas qui, s'ils étaient soumis a un seul, lui donneroient les moyens de se soustraire ouvertement 
au Divan, et de s'allier avec les puissances Européenes pour séparer la Grèce de l'empire Ottoman. 
Ce qui en effet arrive aujourd'hui que les révolutions de tant d'états, et la faiblesse de la Porte et les 
negociatioris mal calculés des diplomates Européens ont rendu Ali formidable à son Maître.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">La partie de l'Albanie qui étoit possédée par les Vénitiens, 
consistait en cinq villes sur les côtes vis–à–vis les îles Ioniennes</foreign>. 
— <emph>Bucintro</emph>, anciently <emph>Buthrotum</emph>. It is situated to the N. 
E. almost opposite to Corfu, near a marsh which renders it extreemely unhealthy, but it was not 
thereby rendered less important to the Venitiens in consequence of the facility of its 
communications with the interior of Albania. They took great care to keep up fortifications of this 
place, and had garrison always on foot there. A small cutter anchored in the harbour was sufficient 
to guard the entrance extremely narrow in this place of the channel. — 
<emph>Gomenitza</emph> an open town which served as a market to the christian Albanians, 
whence the islands of Corfu in great measure derived its supplies of grain and cattle. — 
<emph>Prevesa</emph>, built near <emph>Actia Nicopolis</emph>. This place extremely 
flourishing under the goverment of the Venitians where they had a governor, and maintained a 
garrison in the fort, served for the purpose of closing to the Turks all outlett from the gulf of Arta; 
the channel leading into the gulf being so narrow that it can be defended by cannon of the smallest 
size: it is in general shallow, and the deepest water runs immediately opposite to Prevesa; so that all 
vessels with the exception of fishing boats, are obliged to pass under the fort and a low battery 
standing at the entrance of the town. — <emph>Vonitza</emph> anciently called 
<emph>Lionnea</emph>. This small town built on the side of the gulf of Arta, stands at the feet of 
the mountains of Acarnania, and was the least important of all Venitians possessions. Its relations 
were confined to Acarnania, a savage country, insecure and covered with forests. Hence it was 
considered in no other light than as a post intended to guard the gulf, and an anchoring place for the 
Venitian vessels desirous of passing into the inner parts of it. — <emph>Parga</emph> is 
precisely in the middle; it has on one side Bucintro and Gomenitza, and on the other Prevesa and 
Wonitza. Being defended by, a good castle, and surrounded by almost inaccessible rocks, was not 
only useful to the provisions of Corfu, and to the defence of the Ionian Islands, but was besides of 
the greatest importance to the policy of the Venitians. Parga was a secure asylum for the ennemis of 
Turcs, and the principal seat of the insurrectional movements with which the Venitians agitated the 
Albania against the increasing power of Ali Pacha.</p>
            <p>Ali's grand–father is the first of the family, whose name occurs in the public 
records of the Otoman Empire. He was one of the Beys killed at the siege of Corfu, and belonged to 
the clan of Toczides, an Albanian one of the mahometan religion in the town of Tepeleni. The 
father of Ali was also a Bey but having fallen under the displeasure of the Porte, had been divested 
of his rank, and dispoiled by the Beys his neighbours of greatest part of his inheritance. After a 
courageous defence he died of fatigue and a broken heart, leaving several young children among 
which was Ali born about the year 1150. Successfull policy and the most impenetrable 
dissimulation blended with cruelty, constituted the character of the mother of young Ali. No other 
than her faithful Toczides now remained whom nothing had been able to sever from the family of 
their chieftans. Surrounded by those old followers of her husband, and with her sons fighting under 
her orders, the Albanian widow defended the remainder of her estates. Having been taken prisoner 
by the inhabitants of Gonitza, her ransom absorbed the greatest part of the treasures she had been 
able to save. Ali had scarcely attained his sixteenth year, and in order to break through the tramels 
of dependance, and to seize some means to improve his own condition, and reducing his equals and 
his friends to slavery, he confided to his mother a project he had formed of deviding his enemies 
and defeating .them in detail. He accordingly solicited the command of her little army. She 
hesitated; but Ali's courage which was always calm and cruel suitable to the feeling of his soldiers; 
his address in flattery; and the apparent sweetness of his character towards his friends, gained him 
the regard of the servants of his house, and of the principal leaders of the clan. His mother allowed 
him a few of her soldiers and some money, which ennabled him to assemble some followers. He 
was several times beaten, tand taken prisoner by the vizir Kourd Pascha, a native Turk of a mild 
easy character which the old age had rendered still more indulgent towards the faults if young 
people. The age of Ali, the beauty and sweetness of his phisiognomy, his lively and naturel talenis 
and the misfortunes of his family created an interest in the old Vizir, who laughing at his daring 
project, was satisfied with reprimanding him, and sent him away.</p>
            <p>Ali submitted again under the guardianship of his mother, and having been habituated 
by her to disguise his sentiments, he bore all her reproaches in silence. Whilst he affected a blind 
deference to her orders, he sought his justification among her soldiers, whom he was anxious to 
bind to his future interest. His mother began to be alarmed, and when he repeated his solicitations, 
she accorded a certain degree of approbation to his projects, and wishing to get rid of his presence, 
she gave him a new supply of money. Ali again levied troops and entered into a fresh campaign, 
which was more unfortunate than the first. In order to collect money to unite a numerous army he 
now undertook the persuits of a robber, but he was soon defeated and taken prisoner by the vizir of 
Joannina. The Beys of Joannina as well as almost all the Pachas of Albany insisted on capital 
punishment upon him, but the Vizir dreaded the Beys of the very section over which he himself 
presided, at all times ripe for a revolt; and he could not confide in the Pachas his neighbours whose 
conections with the Venitians rendered them extremely liable to suspicion. He released Ali in order 
to afford them a fresh occupation, and assisted him secretly to colect the remains of his scattered 
troops and to keep the field. He was beaten afresh, and his soldiers in such manner were killed and 
dispersed, that he was obliged to seek refuge alone on the rocks of a mountain. There he found 
himself under the necessity of pledging his scymitar to an Albanian hunter, in order to procure 
himself some bread. On his return to Tepeleni his mother reproached him with cowardice, and 
threatened to make him assume a woman's dress, and employ him in the harem. But he employed 
the force and obtained from her the money necessary to raise six hundred men. His first battle was 
again unsuccesful, and he retired with the remnant of his troops in the vicinity of a deserted chapel. 
He entered into the solitary pile to repose, as well as to reflect on the enterprise he was still able to 
attempt. He remained a long time in a standing posture mechanically furrowing up the ground with 
his stick. The resistance of a solid body, and the sound which issued from it, recalled his attention 
from the object of his meditation and sorrow. He bent down, and having dug farther into the ground 
he found a casket, concealed, very likely, during one of the revolutions which have so frequently 
desolated that country. This narrative was related by himself to general Vaudoncourt, adding that 
the gold which the casket contained, enabled him to levy two thousand men. Having been 
successful in a second battle he returned victorious to Tepeleni.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">Depuis cette période il a été constamment heureux, mais il n'a 
jamais épargné aucun des moyens qui, surtout parmi les barbares, contribuent à la fortune des 
usurpateurs</foreign>. The very day he entered in Tepeleni he persuaded the chiefs of his army that 
his elder brether was treacherous to his country, and under a correspondence with their enemies; 
went with them into his room, and stabbed him in their presence. The next day, they asserted to the 
multitude that his brother being the offspring of a previous mariage, Ali's mother caused him to be 
poisoned in order to secure to her own son the remains of his father's inheritance, and free from a 
dangerous rival. Yet Ali alleging that she deserved punishment, seized on the authority, and 
confined his mother to the harem where she died unpitied and unnoticed.</p>
            <p>Ali besieged with his troops the whole of the defiles leading from the summits of the 
Pindius chain into Thessaly, the Epirus, and Macedonia, pillaging and ransonning travellers and 
merchants levying contributions on the villages and sacking several defenceless town, The 
Dervendgi–Pacha (<emph>inspector general of the high road</emph>) received orders 
from Constantinople to march out against the robbers. Ali defeated him and contrived to unite their 
forces against the Vizir of Skutary who, at that time, was a rebel against the Porte. This ennabled 
the Dervendgi–Pashaw, to make an advantageous peace with thé Vizir of Skutary, and 
obtained from Ali the protection of the Ottoman Emperor. Ali took possession of his father's 
inheritance, and pretending to punish all the rebel subjects of the Sultan, he soon proceeded to 
humble the Beys his personal ennemies of the town of Gonitza which he took and pillaged. He was 
then rich and dreaded, and malgré que les prêtres turcs allégassent son crime de fratricide comme 
un obstacle à son mariage, the Pacha of Argiro Kastro granted his daughter to him. After his 
Iliariage a dissension took place between two brothers of his wife. The regret and anxiety 
occasioned the death of the father; and his eldest son was by Ali's instigation assassinated by his 
brother. Ali hastened to allay the civil war this murder had given rise to. The people who had 
penetrated his design opposed him by force, and he was compelled to withdraw. But another civil 
war furnished him with the meatis of making himsefl master of the town of Charmova, where he 
made away with the chief of the country, massacred the inhabitants, pillaged and distroyed the 
town. Soon after he entered into a war with the Greek clans of Liebovò, who after several years 
resistance were obliged to submit. Those two expeditions made him master of the whole valley of 
the Chelydnus in front of the inhabitants of Argyro Kastro which he held under observation in order 
to revenge the abbomination expressed by them for the fratricidal act he provoked. A little time 
afterwards the Porte whished to rid itself of Selim Pacha of Delvino; and Ali took charge of this 
commission on condition of being named Pacha in the place of Selim. According he insinuated 
himself into his confidence, as well as that of his son Mustapha, and was enabled to surround them 
with his own satellites. He then caused the father to be beheaded, and the son to be arrested; but 
soon afterwards he was compened to fly from the indignation and vengeance of the vassals of 
Selim. The Porte considering Ali as a blind and a devoted instrument of its capital executions in 
Albania, named him Lieutenant of the Dervendgi–Pacha. Ali till then the chief of the 
robbers provided them with diplomas. The Divan divested the Dervendgi Pacha and his Lieutenant 
of their office. The first on his return was beheaded at Constantinople; and Ali sent there part of the 
money to some principal ministers with an offer to follow the Grand Vizir in the war broken out at 
this period (1787) between Austria, Russia and Turkey. Ali entered into correspondance with the 
Prince Potemkin under the pretext of obtaining the release of one of his nephews who had been 
made prisoner. Ali was fully aware of the projects of Russia on Greece, and of her secret measures 
in Albania and Morea for an expedition in the Mediterranean. Ali has still the imprudent vanity to 
shew a watch set in diamonds presented to him by Prince Potemkin in testimonies “of 
esteem for his bradery and talents”.</p>
            <p>After the peace, being possessed of considerable riches he began to entertain constantly 
some cunning agents at Constantinople in order to watch the rising or declining power of the 
differeut ministers, and bribe their patronage. By these means he obtained the title of Pascha of 
Trikala a small district in Thessaly. His vicinity terrified the greek merchants of Joannina who 
feared his exactions. A complete anarchy however reigned in that town. The governement was at 
that time vacant. The Beys divided in their interest caried war among themselves. However both the 
Beys and the Citizens of Joannina sent negociators near the Divan, in order to obtain any Pascha but 
Ali; and they obtained a <emph>Firman</emph> forbidding him from entering into the city. Ali en 
reçut avis par ses agents de Constantinople; et avant que les dépêches du Divan arrivassent, il se 
présenta avec ses troupes aux portes de Joannina; et il y envoya un Firman dans lequel il était 
nommé général inspector of the high roads with the order to enter Joannina without any delay. They 
did not know that this Firman had been forged by himself; and obeyed. As soon as he was master of 
the city he threatned the Citizens of a general massacre unless he obtained from them a petition 
solliciting the government of Joannina for him. This petition and the money extorted from the 
inhabitants were sent to Constantinople, and his usurpation was sanctioned. Thus Ioannina is still 
his metropolis. But being apprehensive of the jealousy of the Porte, as well as of the endeavours of 
his enemies at Constantinople, he sought the protection of France, wrote to Louis XVI, but the 
French minister declined his proposition.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">Telle a été la carrière politique d'Ali jusqu'aux premières années 
de la révolution française</foreign>. The increase of his power had become a subject of new and 
real inquietude to the Venetians. Indeed Ali scarcely took the trouble to disguise the projects he had 
formed on tho Venitians towns on the continent and even on the islands of Corfu and Santa Maura. 
Stratagems were the means the Venetians resorted to for the purpose of counteracting his views. 
The more he laboured through the weight of policy and negociations to reduce tribes whom it was 
impossible for him to subject by force, the more did the Venitians oppose to him countervailing 
measures, and applied themselves to destroy the effects his promises or threats might have 
produced. They excited all kind of parties against him; granted nearly open protection to his 
enemies, and even an asylum when they were unfortunate. They paid for the provisions of Corfu in 
arms and warlike stores, which they handed over to the Philates, Triamides, Paramithians and 
Soulliots and all other indipendent clans of the christian religion. They excited and favoured the 
excursions of the Acarnanians; and each time that Ali carried his forces to one point of his 
government in order to pacify insurretions, or subject insurgences, the Venitian agents did not fail 
to make the countries situated in an opposite direction rise up, and thereby divide his means and 
attention. They kept up active correspondance with the Pachas of Berat, of Delvino and Avlona, and 
peglect nothing that could prevent them from making a sincere peace with their old rival. To 
remove all suspicions from the Divan, the Venetians represented that they were acting in 
conformity of the interest of the Ottoman empire itself, whose government could not with a 
favourable eye behold the rapid increase of the power of Ali. Hence did they stipulate with the Porte 
that Ali should not be allowed to raise a fort on the continent unless at the distance at a mile from 
the coast. They rigorously abided by this condition; nor was Ali at any time able to fortify, even the 
maritime custom–house of Salamora, although placed in the interior of the gulf of Arta: nor 
permitted they any Turkish vessel to come out of the gulf of Arta and much less to appear in the 
channel of Corfu or in that of Santa Maura, Ithaca, or Cephalonia.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Parga fournissait presque seule les moyens de forcer Ali a respecter ces 
conditions. Etant au milieu des possessions Vénitiennes sur la côte, et à l'embouchure du canal de 
Corfu, elle prêtait le meilleur point de surveillance et de garde contre toutes les entreprises 
maritimes d'Ali. L'élévation du rocher verticalement sur la mer permettait de planter les batteries à 
une telle hauteur à pouvoir atteindre les vaisseaux à la plus grande distance; tandis que son 
escarpement mettait les batteries, la ville et le port à l'abri de tout débarquement. Les connections 
des Pargiottes avec les clans indépendents de l'intérieur de l'Albanie de la religion,grecque, et les 
excursions que ceux–ci faisoient impunément sur les domaines des Turcs tantôt pour les 
surprendre par des embuscades, et tantôt pour en espionner les projets et la marche.... La garnison 
Vénitienne ne se battait jamais, car cela aurait compromis le sénat avec la Porte; c'étoient les 
Pargiottes qui tantôt réunis aux clans chrétiens leurs voisins, et tantôt seuls faisoient des petites 
batailles, que les Vénitiens alléguoient de n'avoir point le droit d'empêcher puisqu'elles étoient 
contre la bandes de brigands envoyés par Ali qui, contre les volontés du Sultan, infestoit les terres 
des voisins pacifiques.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Ali, au contraire, parlait de Parga et a continué de la représenter jusqu'à 
présent, comme le seul obstacle à la tranquillité et même à la morale de l'Albanie. Il n'a presque pas 
reçu d'étranger à Joannina et surtout des Anglais auquel il n'ait assuré que le bonheur de la Grece 
dépendait uniquement de la destruction de cette ville. C'est d'après ces notions que Mr. Hobhouse a 
écrit that the character of the Pargiottes is amongst the worst of the Albanians; that their connexion 
with the christian states has taught them only the vices of civilisation, and that they are no less 
ferocious, but have become more refined in their cruelty and violence; and that their town was the 
refuge of many of the robbers whom Ali has driven from the mountains. — Mais ne 
s'agissait–il pas alors d'être ou voleur ou volé? car il n'y avait d'autre alternative. Les 
Pargiottes soutenoient des bandes chretiennes qu'Ali aurait massacré. Ils se prêtaient à la police des 
Vénitiens qui avait été depuis quatre siècles leurs alliés fideles et leurs protecteurs, tandis qu'Ali 
avait trahi ces amis en commençant par sa mère et son frère. L'auteur qui a fait ce caractère des 
Pargiottes a le mérite d'avoir ammassé dans son ouvrage plus d'information que tous les autres qui 
ont écrit sur l'Albanie, et nous en avons profité; mais en considérant plus murement son travail il 
s'appercevrait qu'il a aussi admis des erreurs dont les autres se sont bien gardés. C'est le danger de 
la vastité de la matière. Lorsque l'on veut tout dire sur une contrée que l'on ne peut pas parcourir à 
loisir, ni y demeurer assez pour la connaître, l'on doit se fier aux rumeurs populaires du moment, ou 
aux rapports des personnes qui ont souvent la vanité de vouloir cacher leur ignorance, et plus 
souvent l'intérêt de défigurer la vérité. Au reste, il est le seul voyageur qui ait méconnu les 
Pargiottes. Tous les autres, et M. Dodwell le plus recent entr'eux, dans le,premier volume de son 
voyage en Grèce qui vient justement de paraître, les peint en peu de mots comme doués d'une 
civilité franche; et avec des moeurs domestiques bien différent de ceux des autres Albanais. Mais 
parmi tous, le Lieutenant Colonel de Bosset nous paraît le témoin plus digne de confiance. Cet 
officier non seulement s'est occupé de la Grèce en illustrant des médailles qu'il a deterré, mais 
ayant été gouverneur de Cephalonie et ensuite chargé du commandement de Parga, se trouva dans la 
nécessité d'étudier le charactère en observant journellement la vie habituelle des Pargiottes; et il en 
a tracé une peinture qui est intéressant à préserver d'autant plus que cette petite nation étant déjà 
annéantie, l'on ne trouvera plus les originaux.</p>
            <p>“The Pargiottes differ materially from their neighbours the Albanians, in 
language, costume, and usage: this difference may be ascribed to their connexions with the 
Venitians and with the Islanders; but with more probability to their origin. They are very hospitable. 
The protection and the asylum which they afforded to all the christian Albanians who escaped the 
sword of Ali, would alone establish the reputation for their hospitality. They profess the Greek 
religion under the direction of a Protopapa (a Dean). In the time of the Venitians, the church 
belonged to the Diocese of Paramithia which town being afterwards under the yoke of Ali, the 
Pargiottes no longer acknoledge the spiritual authority of a Bishop who is subject to their ennemy. 
The state of hostility which has always prevailed between them and the Turcs, has rendered them 
brave and familiarized them to arms and dangers. Yet they are of a gay disposition; their mariages, 
baptisms, and in general all festive occasions are accompanied with dances. The foreign garrisons 
which have occupied Parga at differeut periods, have had little influence on the manner of the 
inhabitants. They never depart from their ancient usages; the men are temperate and commonly 
attain an advanced age; they are in general strong and robust, rather above the middle size. The 
women are chast, though they enjoy the greatest degree of social freedom”. “The 
Pargiotes, adds M. Dodwell, are a remarkable handsome people. Most of the women were sitting 
before their doors industriously occupied in spinning or knitting, and every one had something civil 
to say to us as we passed through their streets. The wives and the daughters of the principal 
inhabitants resort daily to procure water for domestic use at a fontaine about a mile from the town. 
They regard this exercise as a recreation, and it would be difficult to make them renounce so 
favorite a custom. Few sights can be more picturesque than these groupes of young women among 
groves of olive and orange trees, bearing vases of elegant form on their heads. Their dress is a 
jacket of cloth or silk embrodered or trimmed with gold, with a long plaited coat. The hair are 
intertwined with a double cord of red silk and gracefully fastened up behind. Sometimes they cover 
fantastically the head with a coloured handkerchief which varies the antic elegance of this coeffure. 
The costume of the men consists of an embroidered jacket, large breeches of blue cloth; and the 
head is covered with a red skull cap; with a musket, a pair of pistols. They cultivate the vine on the 
high hills, and make a tolerable good wine a part of which they export to the neighbouring isles, 
where they also send fruits of different kinds. The corn and maize which they reap are scarcely half 
sufficent for their consumption; they also cultivate flax for their own use, and tobacco which they 
manufacture and export; this tobacco is much esteemed in the neighbouring countries. The most 
lucrative branch of the commerce of this little state consists in oil, oranges, citrons, and cedrats. 
These articles are mostly sold to the subjects of Ali. The cedrats are to be excepted, a fruit which 
succeded better and is cultivated in greater abundance at Parga than any where else: they are 
gathered green before they have acquired the size of a citron, and are in this state packed with great 
care, and exported in small Pargiotte vessels to Trieste: if they did not obtain a suitable price at 
Trieste, they take them into Poland. In comparing the Pargiottes with the most industrious and 
laborious nations of the north, they would not be distingueshed for these qualities: but considered 
with respect to their neighbours and to their fertile soil, and mild climate, they may be pronounced 
an industrious people. Among other usages there is one which deserves particular mention. When a 
young man has paid his adresses to a female and their respective families have agreed on the 
preliminary arrangements for their union, the destined bride is introduced to the paternal home of 
her lover. But it is only at the expiration of a year that the union of the betrothed is irrevocably 
ratified by the seal of religion. In the interval their mutual intimacy and confidence become 
strengthened, and they enjoy under the same roof that liberty without which it would be difficult to 
know and appreciate each other. If before the expiration of a year one of the parties, alleges well 
founded reasons for breaking off the arrangements, the alfair is laid before the Proto Papa, who by 
the aid of arbitrators commonly taken from both the families, decides definitively. If the physical or 
moral incompatibility on which the appeal is made be clearly proved, the whole affair is placed in 
<foreign lang="lat">statu quo</foreign>, and the young female is taken home to her parents. 
Separation of this kind are owever rare. They commonly attack a kind of opprobrium to one or other 
of the parties, until a more auspicious trial has restored him or her to estimation. If at the end of the 
probatory year they suit each other, and the indication of a pregnancy announces their accordance, 
the nuptials are consacrated in the church with all due solemnity.”</p>
            <p>The wisdom and hapiness of the inhabitants of this little town the prosperity and 
smilling aspect of their land resorted till a few months ago from the contrast of all the country by 
which it was surrounded. Beyond the boundaries of the territory of Parga, every thing bespeaks 
desolation and tyranny. The eye discovers nothing but waste lands, abandoned to some scattered 
flocks. But now the soil of Parga begins to be uncultivated.... <foreign lang="fra">Les événements 
que nous continuerous de disposer par époques feront connaître que tandis que cette petite nation a 
constamment repoussé les ménaces, déjoué les ruses, et méprisé les promesses d'Ali, ces moyens 
ont réussi tour à tour avec les plus grandes Puissances de maniere qu'elles ont aveuglement 
conspiré à la sacrifier à sa vengeance</foreign>.</p>
            <p lang="fra">En s'emparant de Venise les Français occupèrent en 1791 les îles Ioniennes. 
Ali avait déjà dépéché à Bonaparte en Italie des agents confidentiels pour renouer les offres qu'il 
avait fait à Louis XVI de s'allier avec lui contre la Porte, à condition que la France l'aida à se 
rendre indépendant. Bonaparte écrivit au Commandant Militaire des Sept Iles de le traiter en ami. 
On lui permit d'armer des bâtiments, de les charger de troupes, et de naviguer la mer Ionienne pour 
porter la guerre au Pacha de Delvino que les Venitiens avaient aidé à s'opposer aux usurpations 
d'Ali. Il attaqua du coté de la mer, et mit à fil de l'épée des tribus dont ils n'avait jamais pu passer 
les montagnes, et qui ne s'attendaient pas que les Français lui accordassent une navigation que les 
Vénitiens lui avoient constamment defendu. Son plus grand soin fut de s'emparer des villes le long 
de la côte; et les Français lui fournirent des ingenieurs et des sousofficiers d'artillerie pour lui 
apprendre à se fortifier. En 1198 l'expedition de Bonaparte en Egypte ayant mis la Porte en guerre 
avec la France, Ali augmenta ses troupes, tout en assurant les Français que c'était pour illuder le 
Divan; mais que son intérêt et sa parole l'engageoient à entretenir l'alliance avec Bonaparte qui 
aurait sans doute partagé l'Empire</p>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <p lang="fra">remontrant aux Français l'inutilité de la résistance, les aiderent de leur barques pour 
retourner à Corfu.</p>
            <p>Dès que la flotte Russe Ottomane s'empara des Sept Iles, Ali se hâta de garnir avec ses 
Albannais Santa Maura,et Corfu, sous prétexte d'appaiser les factions. En effet, il y en avait une 
pour les Français et qui aspirait à la démocratie, — ensuite une des nobles excitée par les 
commissaires d'Ali et par les Turcs qui leur promettoient une oligarchie sous la protection 
immédiate de la Porte — ensuite un des Prêtres, des campagnards, et de la majorité des 
Grecs qui, à cause de la religion, favorisaient la Russie; enfin les partisans Anglais, qui pour influer 
dans le commerce des îles et pour profiter de toutes les factions s'y mêlaient en médiateurs. Ali était 
sur le point de débarquer à Corfu, lorsque les troupes Russes arrivèrent, et leurs Généraux lui firent 
une opposition à laquelle il n'osa resister. Mais les négociateurs Russes à Constantinople firent 
....</p>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">se promettoient que les chicaties, qu' Ali n'aurait pas manqué de faire 
contre les îles, en leur defendant un commerce libre et paisible sur le continent, auroient bientôt 
fourni des justes occasions de rupture. Ils ont confié dans la position imprennable, et dans la bravure 
indomptable des Suliotes, qui avaient été de tout temps soutenu par la Russie, et Catherine II avait 
souvent reçu en hommage les armes des Beys morts en combattant contre Suli: ét la réoccupation de 
la côte leur parut d'autant plus dâre qu'elle était entre les montagnes de Suli et les 
Sept–Iles. Mais les Pargiotes voyaient plus de près que si Ali eût occupé la côte aurait 
empêché les vivres aux Souliotes, et que leur propre ville une fois abandonnée à la discrétion du 
Vizir, aurait été désolée comme le reste de l'Albanie grecque. Ali qui en plusieurs combats n'avait 
pas pu domter les Souliotes, et qui tremblait de leurs excursions, a reussi au moyen de ses garnisons 
sur la côte à leur couper toute communication avec la mer, et à les reduire à ne pouvoir plus 
subsister. Mr. Eton dans son</foreign>
               <title>Survey of the Ottoman Empire</title>, <foreign lang="fra">donne une narration intéressante de cette longue guerre; et l'issue en a été détaillié en 
gree vulgaire par un citoyen de Parga dans</foreign>
               <title>The history of Suli and Parga</title>
               <foreign lang="fra">publié en 1815 à Venise; et dont nous avons rapporté le titre à la tête de cet 
article. Cet ouvrage nous a été fort utile. pour les pieces officielles qu'il renferme. Les derniers 
jours de cette guerre suffisent à faire imaginer les vingt neuf ans d'acharnement qui l'ont 
précédée</foreign>. The position of a mountain which was the last to yeld, was occupied by the 
Suliots under the orders of Samuel, an ecclesiastic, who had commanded this tribe for three years. 
They fearlessly beheld the advance of the Albanians, whom they incessantly combatted and slew 
during six days. But victuals, and especially water having failed, they were obliged to capitulate, 
and they obtained to retire to Parga. The eccleslastic with only four of his soldiers remained to 
deliver up the ammunition to the officers sent by Ali. Samuel, when be had introduced them into the 
store of provision, instantly set fire to the powder, and blew up himself, his four companions, and 
the musulmans who where with them. In the mean time the inhabitants of Suli who retired with 
their families were hemmed in by 5000 Albanians. They made a desperate resistence which 
permitted a part of them to reach Parga: the others were massacred. A group of women who were 
pursued to the verge of a precipice threw their children down, that they might not become the slaves 
of Ali. <foreign lang="fra">Son fils, Vely Pacha, avait accordé à une famille de 
Souliotes</foreign>
            </p>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <p lang="fra">Ainsi à la fin de l'année 1803 toute la tribu des Suliotes disparut a jamais.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Les Pargiottes l'avaient prévu. Ainsi ils refusèrent d'admettre les Turcs, si le 
traité de 1800 n'eût été préalablement expliqué de manière à les rendre tout–à–fait 
indépendens d'Ali, et eurent recours alors à Corfou. L'amiral Ouchacoff, pour remédier à l'erreur 
des négociateurs russes, favorisa la résistance des Pargiotes. D'ailleurs les habitarits des 
Sept–Iles voyaient qu'Ali étant le maître de Parga aurait été aussi le maître de les affamer; 
car c'était principalement de cette ville que les bêtes à cornes, et les blés leur arrivaient de 
l'intérieur du Continent, aussi ils chargerent leurs députés d'obtenir des elauses additionnels au 
sujet des possessions jadis Vénitiennes sur la côte et singulièrement pour Parga. Les clauses furent 
insérées dans le traité, et il fut stipulé que Parga jouiriit de tous les privilèges comme sous les 
Vénitiens; privilèges que d'ailleurs avaient été reconnus par les Sultans précédents, car la Porte n'a 
jamais voulu renoncer à son titre de souveraineté en Grèce, et dans les traités qu'elle faisait avec les 
Vénitiens, elle usait toujours du droit de confirmer les concessions que ceux–ci faisaient 
aux villes. — Que aucune mosquée ne serait bâtie, ni aucun musulman aurait pu acheter ni 
champ, ni maison, ni entrer avec une suite armée, ni se domicilier dans la ville et le territoire des 
Pargiotes. — Que pour deux ans ils seraient exempt de toute taxe, et ensuite ils 
n'auraient....</p>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <p>.... <foreign lang="fra">ministre vouloit entamer avec la Porte, il répondait</foreign> 
“That he was himself uncertain as to the footing on which he stood with the Divan” 
— Nor our Plenipotentiary deemed that the grand Vizir wished to treat with us by the 
medium of Ali. If the Ministers preserve still the official correspondence of that epoch, they will 
find that Lord Collingwood judging favourably of Ali's dispositions, instructed Captain Harvey of 
the Standard to assist him in whatever enterprise it might be advisable to attempt against the French 
in the Ioniam Islands. But soon afterwards, his lordship entertained no hope that Ali would fulfill 
his promises by interfering in offensive measures against any of those islands; nor even against St. 
Maura which was at his reach. Indeed the expedition was undertaken without any assistance from 
Ali; except the selling of some provisions, which likewise he did to the French, even when they 
were blokaded by our fleet in Corfu.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">A la première nouvelle des revers de Napoléon, Ali se jetta 
improvisémment sur Agia, petite ville appartenante au territoire de Parga: et au commencement de 
Mars 1814 il en massacra les habitans; dépêcha des corsaires pour capturer ceux qui se sauvoient 
vers Corfu; déclara esclaves les enfants et les femmes et les envoya a vendre; y batit un fort; et 
marcha contre Parga. Les habitants demandèrent secours au commandant de la garnison Française. 
Il leur répondit, “que les Français étant en paix avec la Porte, il ne pouvoit pas se battre 
contre des Turcs” — et s'enferma avec ses 200 hommes dans la citadelle. Cet 
officier était Arabe; ayant achevé le péllérinage à la Meque, s'était acquit le titre de Haggi qu'il 
continuait de porter; quoique s'étant baptisé lors de l'arrivé de Bonaparte au Caire, il avait pris le 
nom de Nicola, et avait été placé parmis les officiers des <emph>Chasseurs de l'Orient</emph> 
enrolés en Egypte: et puisqu'il connaissait mieux les Turcs et leur langue, on l'envoya garnir Parga 
avec un bataillon de Français: circonstances toutes qui fesoient soupçonner qu'il s'entendait avec 
Ali. Voyant les Turcs sur les hauteurs, et prêts a descendre sur la ville, les habitants hommes et 
femmes sortirent tous à leur rencontre et les éloignoient par un feu incessant; car tandis que les 
hommes se servoient d'un fusil, les femmes se tenoient près d'eux et en chargoient un autre. Les 
Turcs tour à tour se retiroient et avançoient, en prennant des longs détours pour se placer entre les 
Pargiottes et la ville: mais aussitôt, que leur Bey, un neveu d'Ali, fut tué, ils se dispersèrent. Ali le 
jour après fit enterrer le cadavre vis–à–vis de Parga, en y érigeant un tombeau 
comme monument de vengeance différée, mais certaine. En attendant pour ne s'exposer plus à une 
défaite, il les bloqua du côté de terre, en poursuivant l'issue de ses négociations entamées avec les 
Français. Il est prouvé que le Général Donzelot malgré sa position critique à Corfu, s'y était refusé; 
et il n'y a pas assez de preuves que le colonel Haggi Nicola s'y soit jamais prêté.</foreign> The 
Pargiottes shew only a letter intercepted, written by Ali to Haggi: and in an application they made to 
the commander of our naval forces Capt. Taylor in order to make an attack upon the French 
garrison of Parga, they represented — “that the French blockaded by us at Corfu 
being at that time in great want of provisions, they had no hope of drawing supplies for the garrison 
but from Ali, whose assistance would be effectually purchased by the sacrifice of a fortress which 
could not longer be secured from the occupation of the English.” — Captain Taylor 
thought himself not justified in making what he conceived to be a very hazardous attempt, without 
express orders of his Admiral. On the same time the English resident at Joannina, observed to Lieut. 
Gen. Campbell, the King's Commissioner who commanded the British forces in the Ionian Islands: 
“That if the plan of Ali were permitted to be carried into effect, the French would threw the 
odium on the English, who by their reluctance to proceed against the French garrison of Parga, 
when the British forces were in possession of the opposite islands, and intercepted all 
communications by sea, had the appearance of seconding Ali's usurpations. At this very time the 
congress was sitting at Vienna and had the place given up and the inhabitants put to the sword. It 
was not doubtful in what light the whole transaction would appear to the Allies.”</p>
            <p>These motives for acting with decision were at first disregarded by General Campbell; 
but on repeated application, he dispatched Capt. Angelo his aid–de–camp to hold 
conferences with the Pargiotte Deputies at Paxo, and detached some infantry under the orders of 
Major Sir Charles Gordon, that they might be at hand to help in the attac upon Parga. The 
Bacchante, Capt. Hoste, and the Havannah, Capt. Black, arrived just at Paxo. Captain Hoste, the 
senior officer, not feeling sufficiently authorised to an attack, the Deputies of Parga were promised 
that the town would be considered under the protection of Great Britain, and follow the fate of the 
Ionian Islands at two conditions. First — That they should send a previous declaration 
signed by their principal countrymen as a pledge of acknowledgement of British protection: Second 
— That at the moment when the two frigates shall appear before their town, the Pargiottes 
would themselves take possession of the Citadel and hoist the British Flag. The Deputies acceded, 
and the naval officers furnished the....</p>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <p>.... <foreign lang="fra">et l'Europe en sacrifiant des peuples chrétiens aux barbares, seraitune 
supposition plus ingénieuse que juste. En attribuant les grandes fautes des mortels à leur petite 
capacité, l'on se trompe bien moins que lorsqu'on les impute à de la méchanceté profondément 
calculée. Ce fut un des expédients précipités que la position embarassante du Congrès des Alliés à 
Paris et le désir d'en sortir le plutôt possible rendait inévitable à tout homme qui n'aurait possédé un 
esprit supérieur et une connaissance pratique de l'Europe. Les mapes géographiques ont été souvent 
la source des erreurs des diplomates modernes: les anciens chargeoient de traiter la paix ceux qui 
avoient fait la guerre dans le pays. Apparemment Lord Castlereagh savait que lorsqu'il s'agissait de 
l'expédition de l'Admiral Collingwood sur les îles, nos diplomates ont averti le 
gouvernement</foreign> — “that Corfu, as well from its geographical position as 
physical structure must be considered as one of these commanding places on the globe, which 
necessarily secure or enlarge the Empire of those who possess them.” — <foreign lang="fra">Mais le Général Campbell qui était sur le lieu, a pu reconnoître par sa propre expérience 
que Corfu, malgré ses grands avantages, n'obtenait du bétail et du grain que de l'Albanie; et que 
l'industrie commerciale de la ville de Parga, les connexions de ses habitants avec les marchands 
grecs du continent, leur alliance perpétuelle avec les Sept–Iles, leur loyauté, leur courage, et 
les batteries de leur forteresse auroient en tems de guerre assuré des provisions à Corfu; et il est 
trèsprobable que Lord Castlereagh ignorait au Congrès de Paris la transaction du général Campbell 
avec les Pargiottes, et l'approbation qu'il en avait reçu par Lord Bathurst au nom du Régent. 
Néanmoins en raisonant d'après les principes de la diplomatie, et en interprétant les mots avec 
rigueur, l'on pourrait démontrer jusqu'à un certain point que nos officiers aux Iles n'étoient pas 
accrédités à traiter; et que l'approbation royale ne s'étendait qu'à l'occupation militaire d'une 
forteresse garnie jusqu'alors par nos ennemis.</foreign>
            </p>
            <p lang="fra">En tout cas notre négociateur a adopté pour base un traité qui pour le droit de 
gens, et d'après les actes de nos Légations à la Porte, et les pactes de l'Alliance contre la France 
avait cessé d'être valide. Car après ce traité de 1800, la Porte à la paix d'Amiens a reconnu en 1802 
le roi de la Grande Brettagne — “comme un des protecteurs et gardiens de 
l'indépendance des SeptIles”. A la paix de Tilsit, Napoléon les changea en colonies; et son 
Ambassadeur à Constantinople mit en prison le Chancelier de la Légation Sept–insulaire. 
Notre Ambassadeur le réclama en vigueur du traité d'Amiens et au nom du roi d'Angletere qui 
n'avait pas reconnu les transactions de Tilsit. En effet la Porte en Mai 1809 s'engages officiellement 
— “de couper toute communication avec l'ambassade Française jusqu'à ce que le 
Chancelier ne fut mis en liberté”. — Ce qu'elle ne fit pas; et à la fin de la même 
année elle a stipulé une paix avec Napoléon, en lui laissant les îles, et en s'engageant de 
subministrer des vivres à Corfu contre nos flottes. En même temps Lord Collingwood a pris Zante 
et Cephalonia; et notre Plénipotentiaire à Constantinople à solennellement protesté: “That 
some of the Ionian Islands having surrendered to his British Majesty's arms, without the assistance 
of any other of the powers interested in the independence of the sept–Insular Republik, His 
Majesty has a right to proceed to the settlement of the government of those islands without 
consulting any foreign state: that if the Porte still recognize that Republick, her ancient claims of 
protection would be attended to — if not, not.” — La Porte non seulement 
n'a point répondu, mais elle viola jusqu'à la neutralité à laquelle elle s'était engagée Notre 
gouvernement fut en Février 1810 informé officiellement: “That English ships were 
captured by French privateers in the very Ottoman ports, and the prizes put up publickly to sale in 
Ottoman towns.” Le pacte de l'Alliance en 1814 a placé à la disposition commune des 
Alliés tous les pays que l'on aurait repris à Napoléon. En conséquence, notre protection exclusive 
des, sept–Iles, et de leurs dépendences, fut en 1815 stipulé en quatre traités séparés avec la 
Prusse, la Russie, le roi de France et l'Autriche. Parga a été de tout temps dépendance de Corfu, 
excepté pour le peu d'années qu'elle fut moins <emph>sujette</emph> que 
<emph>vassalle</emph>. Dès que la Porte la laissa à Napoléon, et que les Alliés la reprirent aux 
Français, la Porte n'avait aucun droit au partage des conquêtes des Alliés; car elle fut la seule 
puissance qui dans la guerre universelle de l'Europe continua de rester en paix avec la France. En 
effet elle n'envoya aucun Agent accrédité au Congrès de Paris: et ne pouvait pas porter aucune 
réclamation pour l'accomplissement du traité du 1800, car et par le fait et par le droit elle y avoit 
absolument renoncé.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Mais puisqu'en l'admettant pour base d'un nouveau traité, les Alliés 
l'avoient rétabli en pleine vigueur, et ils ont par cet acte appelé la Porte à avoir droit au partage des 
pays repris à Napoléon, le Divan exigea l'accomplissement de la clause qui en 1800 avait cédé aux 
Turcs toutes les possessions ex–venitiennes sur la côte d'Albanie; sans quoi il refusa de 
reconnaître notre protection des Sept–Iles. Ali continuait de posséder toute la côte, à 
l'exception de la forteresse et du territoire de Parga; aussi la question ne regardait que cette ville; et 
le démêlé avec les Ottomans tomba naturellement sur les Anglais comme possesseurs actuels de 
Parga et les seuls protecteurs des Sept–Iles. Jusqu'alors nos négociateurs ayant reconnu le 
traité 1800, ont commis une erreur commune à tout le Congrès; mais ensuite ils ont transigé avec le 
Divan de rianière à violer ce même traité du 1800 vis–à–vis les Alliés et à donner à 
toutes les nations le droit d'en imputer l'injustice uniquement aux Anglais. Car, en cédant Parga, 
nos Ministres ont rempli les clauses du traité en faveur des Turcs, mais ils n'ont pas exigé 
l'exécution du même traité pour les clauses qui établissent les privilèges des Pargiottes. La Russie 
était alors la garantie de ces privilèges; et en nous transferant l'exécution du traité, elle nous a 
nécessairement transféré aussi l'obligation de la garantie. En stipulant le droit de notre protection, et 
en reconnaissant la validité du traité 1800 avec l'Autriche....</p>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <p lang="fra">fut suflisante aux Français....
qu'Ali faisait avancer par le Divan pour obtenir Parga. Ma si nos ministres ne croient pas 
l'Angleterre assez forte pour pouvoir être juste, ne la font–ils paraître encore plus faible, en 
l'humiliant à céder une ville en force d'un traité sans exiger les concessions stipulées dans le même 
traité? sans remplir notre engagement de les garantir? Le mystère avec lequel on a négocié cette 
cession nous empêche de connaître, si ce sont de grands intérêts et de profondes combinaisons 
politiques qui ont forcé le gouvernement à sacrifier un peuple innocent et notre honneur, ou si nos 
diplomates se sont laissé intriguer et épouvanter par les Turcs. Il est néanmoins 
très–probable que la Porte, tout en préférant de voir une place forte possédée plutôt par un 
Mahométan que par des Chrétiens, n'aurait pas tant insisté pour la donner à un vassal qui en créant 
un pouvoir presque indépendant et en intriguant avec les Rois de l'Europe, est devenu formidable à 
l'intégrité de l'empire Ottoman — et il est hors de doute, qu'Ali a été le seul moteur, le seul 
directeur, et l'âme de cette négociation: et que ses intrigues, son argent et sur tout sa conduite 
envers notre armée dans les Sept–Iles ont prêté à ses agents à Constantinople et aux 
partisans qu'il a dans le Divan, assez d'artifices et de hardiesse pour en imposer à nos 
ministres.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Par toutes les actions de sa vie Ali a montré que ceux qu'il a gagnés par la 
ruse, ont toujours été maltraités plus que ceux qu'il a subjugé avec la force. Ayant inutilement taché 
de tromper les Russes aux Sept–Iles, il souffrait patiemment leurs insultes: et lorsqu'un 
Colonel Russe frappa un Bey en sa présence, Ali s'éloigna sans parler, et envoya des présents. 
Après que l'exemple de l'Ajudant Général Roze eut mis les Français sur leurs gardes, Ali en 
désespérant de leur en imposer, prit le parti de la soumission aux ordres du Consul Pouqueville. La 
bonnehommie des Anglais lui donne assez de hardiesse pour ne point redouter leur puissance. 
Ayant demandé de réparer deux custom houses sur une élévation de la frontiere de Sta. Maura, il les 
changea, à la vue de Sir Hudson Lowe, en deux forts avec des batteries qui commandent l'Ile de 
tres–près, et qu'un jour la réduiront en décombres. Voyant par là que nos officiers se 
souciaient plus de son amitié que de la sûreté des îles, il fit arrêter à Prevesa un citoyen de Sta. 
Maura, frère du boulanger de l'armée anglaise; et menaça de le faire rôtir vif si son frère ne lui 
envoyait son enfant pour son Séraglio. Le boulanger après des démarches inutiles près les Anglais, 
épargna à son frère un supplice cruel en sacrifiant son propre fils à une existence malheureuse. Un 
autre jour, à la vue....</p>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <p>.... Some time afterwards Lieutenent Dalton of the royal Engineer inadvertently passed that 
frontier, and three Albanians soldiers fired at once. Having received several wounds, he fell 
senseless; and they would have murdered him, but for some Pargiotes who hastened to his 
assistance. Ali sent a deputy to Corfu offering the three heads of the delinquents. Sir Thomas 
Maitland demanded them alive; which Ali positively refused. After some negociations, the three 
Albanians were produced at Parga, instead of Corfu, with the previous understanding that they 
should be immediately returned to their master, who afterwards continued employing them at the 
same frontier.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">Les représailles qui repousseroient facilement ces insultes, 
ameneraient des publicités que les ordres des ministres ont très probablement forcés nos Militaires 
d'éviter. Cependant pour grande que puisse être l'utilité de pareils ménagements, le mépris d'un 
voisin sans foi finit toujours par être beaucoup plus dangereux que sa haine: et quoique les barbares 
ne puissent jamais craindre sans haïr, le seul moyen de les tenir en respect, est de leur inspirer de la 
crainte. Lorsque le lieutenant Dalton fut blessé, le lieutenant Col. de Rosset avait été déjà envoyé à 
Parga avec 300 hommes en Mars 1817 pour contenir le désespoir des habitants, et leur annoncer 
que l'Ambassadeur Anglais et le Divan avaient définitivement donné leur ville à Ali. Ils 
demandèrent d'envoyer des députés à Corfu pour exposer leurs raisons, ou si leur calamité était 
inévitable, de mettre au moins en garde Sir Thomas contre les ruses d'Ali qui aurait tâché de rendre 
leur sacrifice plus sanglant. Sir Thomas leur fit répondre par le Lieutenant Col. de Bosset</foreign> 
— “That it was impossible to admit any memorial upon the subject, which must be 
in itself futile” — adding, — “that his Majesty's dispatches on this 
subject to him being miscarried, it was not in his power to quiet the minds of the people of Parga by 
a proclamation relative to what was likely to take place; but that all individuals who might wish to 
emigrate should be paid for their property, and themselves transported to the Ionian islands: and if 
they presume by violence or bloodshed to take the smallest relief into their own hands, their fate 
must be left to themselves; and his Excellency should consider his Majesty's government 
exonerated from the necessities then existing of interfering in their favour, not only for their 
advantage, but for the honour and the character of the British Government.”</p>
            <p lang="fra">Cette réponse, et le peu de satisfaction obtenue pour Mr. Dalton, mais sur 
tout le parti qu'Ali tirait de nos ménagements en leur donnant l'éclat que notre gouvernement 
desirait d'éviter, firent présumer aux Pargiotes que Sir Thomas Maitland s'entendait avec Ali pour 
les exposer à des calamités qu'il était en son pouvoir de leur épargner: et Ali employait tous les 
artifices pour les exaspérer contre nous. Il leur faisait dire que les généraux, et les négociateurs 
Anglais étaient vendus à lui. Ses agents firent imprimer dans les gazettes d'Allemagne et dans des 
papiers publiés en grec vulgaire, que Sir Thomas, pour prix de son amitié envers Ali, et de son 
dévouement à la Porte, avait obtenu l'ordre du Croissant. Cette nouvelle fut réimprimée, et 
peut–être crue dans toutes les Capitales de l'Europe: mais quoique, soit par égard pour les 
Ministres dont la vue était de consumer cette affaire avec le moins bruit possible, soit par un juste 
mépris contre la calomnie, le général Maitland ne l'ait point démentie, peu de gens l'ont crue en 
Angleterre. Toute fois il est à craindre que l'assurance dans son caractère si avantageusement établi 
dans sa patrie, n'ait quelques fois exposé Sir Thomas Maitland à donner lieu à des apparences que 
tout homme d'honneur à le droit de mépriser, mais que tout homme public a le devoir d'éviter. Ali 
s'est procuré des entrevues d'ostentation à Prevesa avec le Général. Maitland; ces visites du Lord 
High Commissioner du Roi d'Angleterre n'ayant pas été payées de retour par le Visir Vassal du 
Sultan, ont fourni à Ali occasion de se vanter de la complaisance des Anglais. Depuis 
long–temps la vanité de quelques voyageurs, la curiosité de quelques dames de rang, le 
besoin que les petits esprits ont d'admirer, le peu d'horreur que l'on sent pour les crimes lorsqu'ils 
étonnent par leur bonheur, amenent des Anglais à la cour d'Ali, et souvent ils lui sont introduits par 
des officiers. Quelques individus aussi ont accepté publiquement des présents, qui n'ayant point été 
rendus par des équivalents selon l'usage des Orientaux, ont donné des supçons qui, par les habitants 
d'un pays où Ali s'est constamment agrandi par la trahison et l'argent, ont été changé en 
certitude.</p>
            <p>The expectation of a calamity seldom fail to produce an actual misery. The landholders 
at Parga would no longer incur expences in cultivating ground of which they were not certain in 
gathering the produce. Every one sought to realize and to conceal his money; all commercial 
undertakings were suspended; and in a few days that class of persons who depend on their daily 
labour and these who relied on the future products of their property, were reduced to the greatest 
distress. The head of the church and all public functionnaries renounced the emoluments of their 
place; and the more opulent collected a fund for the purchase of grain; and another for the relief of 
the lower classes. They made an application at Corfu for a loan, and the Hon. Colonel Stuart 
commanding in she absence of General Maitland, granted them 4000 dollars in grain, on the terms 
they proposed — “That the money should be deducted from the sums they receive 
for their properties from Ali; or if the cession of their town does not take place within the end of 
December next 1817 that the principal inhabitants were to become securities for the payment of the 
money with due punctuality.”</p>
            <p>Nevertheless our anxiety to avoid any appearance that Ali might construe into an 
encouragement to the people to emigrate, made the Pargiottes believe that should a sum of money 
be agreed on, Ali would find subterfuges for not paying it. Lieut. Colonel de Bosset shew them a 
letter in which Sir Thomas pledged himself — “That untill the property of those 
who might wish to emigrate, should be paid for, and themselves transported in the Ionian Islands, 
no cession should take place.” But the Primates wished that a proclamation should be 
published by authority of the British Government. They again insisted on sending a Memorial to 
Corfu: and upon the refusal of the Commandant in consequence of Thomas Maitland's orders, they 
declared — “That they were determinate to go to the head quarters, and that nothing 
but force could prevent them.” The Commandant did not conceive himself authorized to 
employ force and they proceeded to Corfu. Colonel Stuart answered through Mr. Mayer — 
“That he will spare no available means to protect their interest:” and by a 
proclamation published at Parga, assured them that — “The British government has 
engaged to protect all those among the Pargiotes who might be inclined to emigrate, and to procure 
for them an equitable and just compensation for their properties.”</p>
            <p>Meanwhile, Mr. John Cartwright formerly an unsuccesful merchant at Constantinople, 
and then an agent of the Levant Company at Patras, arrived at Joannina appointed to be British 
Commissioner for the Cession of Parga. On the lith of May 1817 he signed with Hamed Bey the 
Ottoman Commissioner a secret Convention in order to make the evaluation and payment of the 
properties. Hamed Bey ne prêtait que le nom; et toute l'affaire était traité par deux sous agents qui 
l'entouraient à ne lui permettre aucune conférence avec M. Cartwright. L'un était Manthò, 
secrétaire grec d'Ali, et fameux pour s'être conservé les faveurs de son maître moyennant l'astuce 
et le sang froid avec lesquels il a trompé et soumis aux Turcs les tribus chrétiennes de l'Albanie. 
L'autre était Changery, fils d'un Prince de Wallachie décapité, appartenant à cette caste de Grecs de 
Constantinople occupés à intriguer près des Turcs, et qui pour obtenir des places de Dragomans, et 
des charges dans la Wallaquie et la Moldavie, se supplantent réciproquement, et “le frère, 
dit Mr. Eton, ourdit des cabales contre le frère; le fils contre le père”. This Changery was in 
1806 sent through the exertions of Sebastiani, to the admiral Duckworth on pretence of treating with 
him, and of thus amusing him, until the military preparations in the Dardanelles against the English 
forces were completted. Being afterwards accused of malversation, he took sanctuary at the court of 
Ali, who appointed him as interpreter in the pending negotiation, with orders to watch strictly the 
two commissioners.</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">Sur la demande de M. Cartwright concernant le nombre des 
familles qui auroient probablement émigré de Parga, et le prix approsimatif de leurs propriétés, le 
Commandant lui écrivit à Joannina — “Qu'apparemment personne ne serait resté; et 
que d'après les information les moins inexactes, et en déduisant les fortes prétensions des 
propriétaires, il pensait que la vente produirait entro 400 et 500 mille livres sterling.” 
— Pour s'en assurer, il prit, sur lui de faire dénombrer et évaluer sous sa surveillance les 
oliviers, les vignes, les champs a blé, les maisons particuliers et publiques, et les églises, en 
inscrivant les sommes en détail sur des régistres séparés. Les nombres des olives trees eccédait 
81,000; et en calculant selon le prix ordinaire du continent et des Iles chaque olivier à 50 Turkish 
piastres (Lst. 2.10 d.) la valeur en montait à 200,000 Lat. De cette évaluation entière de toutes les 
propriétés en résulta une somme excédente 500,000 Lst. A l'arrivé de M. Cartwright le 
Commandant lui remit tous les régistres que I Sir Thomas Maitland ensuite déclara</foreign> 
“to be null and of no force, being fixed without the necessary authorisation.”</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">Tandis qu'Hamed s'approchait de Parga, Ali en faisait entourer le 
territoire par de forts détachements; et 50 hommes de cavalerie allaient entrer dans la ville avec la 
suite du Bey. Le peuple exclamait, que ses protecteurs ne consommeroient point impunément leur 
seconde trahison: et les Primates représenterent au Commandant, “que quand même les 
habitans n'auroient pas soupçonné la garnison de connivence, l'irritation produite par le spectacle 
tout–à–fait nouveau des Turcs armés dans leur ville, et l'ancienne animosité, 
auroient sans doute entraîné à des actes de désespoir.” — Le Commandant 
manquant d'instructions positives, et ayant déjà intimé au nom du général Maitland qu'en tout cas 
de trouble Parga aurait été abandonné à sa destinée, il prévoyait que cette manœuvre d'Ali n'aurait 
pas manqué d'effet</foreign>. “An enterprise of this kind, sais Col. de Bosset, would not 
have placed the fortress itself in the hand of Ali. Yet in order to protect it the garrison must remain 
within its walls: and so long as the fortress was not attacked, the Commandant could not have felt 
justified in commencing hostilities and taking part in the quarrels of the inhabitants against forces 
that entered amicably into a country which by a treaty just concluded, was to be ceded. Yet had the 
views of Ali been realized by creating a focus of discord through the means of a convention, he 
would have entangled in his snares the life and properties of the Pargiotes and the honor of 
England.” — <foreign lang="fra">Le Colonel Stuart approuva l'expédient de ne 
point admettre Hamed Bey dans Parga que sous les conditions — “que sa suite se 
limiterait à 36 individus, dont on envoyerait les noms et les surnoms, pour y rayer des Pargiottes qui 
l'accompagnaient, et qui étaient déjà bandis pour des crimes — que les communications des 
commissaires avec la terre fernie n'auraient lieu que par un point seulement — et que leur 
travail devant, en vigueur de la convention de Joannina, être exécuté <emph>avec zèle, activité et 
promptitude</emph>, leur séjour à Parga ne devait outre–passer que deux mois. M. 
Cartwhright en ayant donné copie à Hamed Bey, ils entrèrent à Parga accompagnés de Changery et 
Manthò; et après un mois ils publièrent deux proclamation.</foreign>”</p>
            <p>The british Commissioner — “confirmed the assurances of a 
compensation at a just and suitable price for the property of the emigrants, although the British 
Government did not interfere with their determination to quit their country and claimed no influence 
either one way or the other.” — Hamed's proclamation “entreated the 
Pargiottes to love their native town and to remain, pledging himself on behalf of the Porte that they 
shall enjoy liberty of all kind, security, honour, and respect, and profound tranquillity.” 
— Yet the british authorities could not prevail on Hamed Bey to affix his name and seal to 
this document which, according to the rules of his government, was of no force without that 
formality. All the Pargiottes were called with solemnity one by one before the two commissioners 
and all declared — “that they prefered to quit their country, and that they would 
disinter and carry away the bones of their fore–fathers.” — A deaf and 
dumb man being interrogated in his turn and having ascertained what' was signified to him, he 
indignantly turned to the Bey and by the most energetick gesture gave him to understand, that he 
sought to retain them in order to cut their throats — then looking kindly towards the English 
officers, pointed to the british flag which was floating on the fortress.</p>
            <p>Ali envoya un député à Malta pour représenter au général Maitland que l'obstination des 
Pargiotes à se soumettre à la Porte était fomenté par le Commandant de la garnison. En attendant la 
réponse, les Commissaires ne commencèrent pas leurs travaux. Changery répétait aux habitants que 
le Divan désapprouvait la Convention de Joannina et que l'on avait convenu avec Sir Robert Liston 
qu'Ali donnerait 1,200,000 piastres turques (L. 60,000) à nos généraux pour trouver un expédient à 
empêcher l'émigration. Ali lui–même, ayant l'air d'en causer avec les marchands de 
passage à Joannina, riait des espérances des Pargiotes, en assurant qu'il attendait de jour en jour le 
Firman d'occuper leur ville par la force. Par une série de dépositions de ces marchands ainsi que des 
coupables et des témoins devant les Magistrats, et dont quelques unes ont été dernièrement publiés, 
il est prouvé que les émissaires d'Ali cherchaient à gagner un grand nombre de pauvres familles 
Pargiotes, pour les soulever contre les Anglais. Manthó avec des lettres flatteuses et des promesses 
de son maître s'introduisit à M. Vlandi magistrat de la Police de la ville, en tachant de le faire 
tremper dans la conspiration. Le fort voisin d'Agia était depuis long–temps le repaire d'où 
l'on envoyait des bandits à empoisonner l'eau de la ville, à mettre le feu au magazin à poudre, et 
exciter tout espèce de trouble pour obliger les Anglais de se retenir dans la forteresse, et les 
Pargiottes à ne pouvoir plus défendre la ville. Cependant Ali ayant peu d'espérance dans ces 
stratagêmes difficiles, il se confiait de mettre le désespoir au moyen de la famine, et il faisait 
décharger et arrêter à Prevesa les barques qui portoient du blé à Parga; tandis que le Col. Stuart 
écrivait de distribuer avec secret le grain qu'il envoyait — “for fear of creating any 
jealousy on the part of the Turks who were already very much inclined tó suspect all our 
motives.”</p>
            <p>
               <foreign lang="fra">Les mesures décidées que le Commandant de la garnison croyait 
devoir prendre pour sa responsabilité, et l'intérêt qu'il montrait pour les Pargiottes, blessoient les 
ménagemens que le Commissaire Anglais désiroit de garder. En sollicitant pour Hamed Bey des 
concessions que le Commandant disait de ne pouvoir accorder sans exaspérer les Pargiottes, M. 
Cartwright expressed his surprize</foreign> — “That an English officer with three 
hundred British troops should take notice of the feelings of such fellows.” — The 
Commandant determined “not to have any further verbal comunication with him” 
— and was relieved in July by Col. Stuart. Mr. Cartwright returned to Patras, and was 
appointed Consul général at Constantinople. Hamed Bey remained in Parga. <foreign lang="fra">La négociation ne fut renouée qu'au mois d'Octobre dans une conférence du général 
Maitland avec Ali à Prevesa; et l'exécution en fut recommencée en Mars 1818 par le Lieutenant 
Col. Maitland, nouveau commissaire. Les habitants furent interrogés solennellement de nouveau sur 
leur désir de partir, ou de rester; et tous répondirent comme l'année précédente. The Ottoman 
Commissioner resisted the evaluation of the churches and their landed estates, as well as thoses of 
the corporations, and possession of the local government, and such lands as were not cultivated and 
built upon. Lieutenant Col. Maitland suspended this evaluation, waiting for further instruction, and 
the inhabitants represented at Corfu</foreign> — “That the churches and the other 
possessions above mentioned were the private inheritance of different families, who had the same 
right upon them as upon all property left to them by their ancestors, according the documents they 
possess — and as to the common property, it was their determination to apply the produce 
of it to the reconstruction of their churches, in any spot which might be allotted to them in the 
dependencies of the Seven Islands.”</p>
            <p lang="fra">Le Général Maitland ayant quitté Corfu sans [se] prononcer sur 
leur Mémorial, les Pargiotes envoyèrent à Londres les records de leur Communauté et leurs 
documents depuis 1401, jusqu'au 1818, à un individu qu'ils présumaient dans le cas de pouvoir les 
présenter au Parlement, ou au Roi d'Angleterre. Il leur répondit — “Que n'étant pas 
citoyen anglais, il n'avait pas le droit de présenter au parlement une pétition en leur nom; et qu'il ne 
devait pas se mêler d'aucune transaction politique jusqu'au moment qu'étant définitivement 
consommé, elle aurait cessé d'être une affaire de controverse: que s'il s'adressait aux ministres, ils 
ne le reconnaîtraient pas comme agent de Parga, puisqu'elle n'était pas une ville indépendante; et 
quand même ils accepteraient des réclamations, ils les renvoyeraient à la décision du Général 
Maitland: que néanmoins l'on disait que Sir Charles Gordon, à qui les Pargiottes avaient donné la 
possession de leur forteresse, s'étant intéressé près d'un ministre, il avait reçu des assurances en 
faveur de leur ville; et qu'en même temps quelques membres de l'opposition alléguaient les délais 
de Sir Th. Maitland comme une preuve que malgré l'insistance du ministère, il refusait de la livrer à 
Ali: qu'en tout cas si la question allait au parlement, il y aurait à craindre la connivence des partis 
qui sacrifient souvent leurs principes à leurs intérêts, et quelquefois leur principes et leurs intérêts 
aux égards pour des individus.”</p>
            <p lang="fra">Les délais se prolongèrent pendant une autre année, et on les attribue aussi 
aux tergiversations d'Ali à ne point débourser 633,000 dollars (142,425 livres sterling) qui d'après 
la proclamation du Juin, 1819, de Sir Thomas Maitland, ont été le produit de l'évaluation définitive, 
et qui n'est pas même le tiers de la somme qui en était resulté d'après l'évaluation antérieure. 
— Peutêtre que nous nous sommes trop longuement occupé de ce sujet. Mais il ne fallait pas 
omettre les événements et les détails indispensables à faire ressortir une vérité de fait unique dans 
l'histoire du genre humain et c'est: Que une petite tribu a constamment repoussée les menaces, 
déjoué les ruses, et méprisé les promesses d'un voisin cruel et perfide, et ces menaces, les 
promesses, et les ruses ont tour à tour réussi avec les plus grandes puissances de manière qu'elles 
ont aveuglement conspiré avec Ali depuis le 1797 jusqu'au moment que le Congrès des Alliés a 
sanctionné le sacrifice, et les Ministres Anglais l'ont encore plus aveuglement et plus 
inhumainement exécuté.</p>
            <p lang="fra">Lorsqu'on leur intima de quitter leur patrie, chaque famille se plaça devant sa 
maison; et leurs pères leur recommandèrent de contenir les murmures et les larmes. Tous les 
hommes, précédés par leurs prêtres et suivi par le urenfans mâles, déterrèrent des sépultures les 
ossements des morts, et les ammassèrent sur du bois préparé devant une Eglise. Ensuite ils 
s'armèrent, et brûlaient les ossements, restant tous immobiles autour du rog. Les Turcs approchaient 
de la ville, et les Pargiotes déclarèrent à la garnison que si un seul Turc se présentait, avant que les 
reliques de leurs pères fussent délivrées de la profanation, et avant qu'ils se fussent tous embarqhés, 
ils s'étaient déjà déterminés a égorger leurs propres femmes et leurs enfans, et mourir les armes à la 
main en tirant quelque vengeance des acheteurs et des vendeurs de Parga. Le général Adam 
persuada aux Turcs de s'arrêter; et les Pargiotes demeurèrent jusqu'à ce que le feu des ossements 
fut consommé.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 lang="ita" n="Ricordi per que' di Parga">
            <head>RICORDI PER QUE' DI PARGA</head>
            <p>1. Importerà che i Primati eleggano due Deputati d'età provetta, di presenza prestante, e 
di aspetto civile.</p>
            <p>2. I Deputati portino seco in Londra una narrazione di quanto avvenne nella loro città 
dal mese di [giugno] 1817, allorchè fu loro intimato di emigrare o di restare sudditi 
d'Alì — sino al giorno del loro arrivo nell'isole.</p>
            <p>3. Sì fatta narrazione sia testificata dalle firme con giuramento di tutti i Primati.</p>
            <p>4. Notisi che tutto sia scrupolosamente <emph>vero</emph> ne' fatti, e nulla esagerato 
nello stile.</p>
            <p>5. Non sarà inutile che narrino inoltre in che modo furono e sono tuttavia trattati dal 
Lord Alto Commissario, o da' suoi ministri nelle sette isole.</p>
            <p>6. La narrazione servirà di fondamento al ricorso che si dovrà stendere in Londra.</p>
            <p>7. I due deputati abbiano una credenziale firmata da tutti i Primati, affinchè possano 
sottoscrivere il ricorso in nome della popolazione di Parga, e siano riconosciuti dal Governo 
Inglese.</p>
            <p>8. Avranno valido appoggio nella Opposizione, se porteranno al Duca di Bedford una 
lettera in greco volgare secondo l'esemplare qui annesso: — perchè un Comitato presieduto 
dal Duca di Bedford ha recentemente deliberato di sovvenire di danaro il popolo di Parga, ed ha 
promulgato la deliberazione seguente:

<quote rend="block">
                  <text>
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>Londra, Mercoledì 11 Agosto 1819.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>«Il Comitato della Contea di Devon fondato in Agosto 1816 per la 
PROPAGAZIONE de' PRINCIPII DELLA COSTITUZIONE BRITANNICA, e mantenimento 
Libertà civile e religiosa —</p>
                        <p rend="text-align:right">Presidente il Duca di BEDFORD</p>
                        <p rend="text-align:right">Vice–Presidente il Colonnello PELL</p>
                        <p rend="text-align:right"> (qui seguono i nomi d'altri Ufficiali d'esso Comitato)</p>
                        <p>in un'assemblea tenuta a di 5 Agosto 1819: —</p>
                        <p>«Risolve — Il Comitato essendo profondamente tocco dallo stato di quei 
che abitano Parga, ed ammirando il virile ed eroico animo ch'essi hanno sì altamente manifestato, 
raccomanda alla Nazione Inglese di aprire una soscrizione di danaro per sovvenire ad essa 
popolazione.</p>
                        <p>«Risolve — Il Comitato soscriverà per Lire 50 sterl., ed il Duca di 
Bedford sarà rispettosamente richiesto di trasmetterle a quei che abitavano Parga.</p>
                        <p>«Risolve — Che i Signori Floud, Cross, Wilcocks e Comp. Banchieri 
siano richiesti di ricevere le soscrizioni; e che le presenti risoluzioni siano inserite nel 
<title>Times</title>, nel <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, nell'<title>Alfred</title> etc.» 
(qui si designano alcune altre gazzette nelle quali infatti queste furono pubblicate).</p>
                     </body>
                  </text>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>9. Modello di lettera da presentarsi scritta in greco volgare al Duca di Bedford:

<quote rend="block">
                  <text>
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>ALLA GRANDEZZA DEL DUCA DI BEDFORD I PRIMATI DELLE FAMIGLIE CHE 
ABITAVANO LA CITTÀ DI PARGA SALUTE</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Avendo per le efemeridi inteso come alla Grandezza vostra e a' vostri parenti ed amici è 
piaciuto di sovvenirci di danaro, e d'esortare la Nazione Inglese a soccorrerci e riverirci come 
uomini che abbiamo sostenuto virilmente la avversità e l'ingiustizia, noi offeriamo alla vostra 
Grandezza, e a' vostri parenti ed amici, e alla vostra Nazione molte grazie ossequiose, ed 
esponiamo nel tempo stesso che il danaro venendoci da tali mani non potrebbe umiliarci, ma che se 
fosse distribuito a tutti quelli che sono più poveri fra di noi, il soccorso riescirebbe precario e 
dannoso, e quindi contrario all'intento de' nostri Benefattori. Perchè ogni poco danaro 
provocherebbe sempre più i nostri poveri a emigrare ed andare a procacciarsi la vita raminghi in 
paesi lontani, e la nazione di Parga si dileguerebbe eternamente dal mondo. Invece se il soccorso e 
il favore che la vostra Grandezza co' suoi parenti ed amici si degna di compartirci si impiegassero 
ad assistere i Deputati che noi manderemo in Londra per implorare da S. M. il Re della Gran 
Brettagna la pietà e la giustizia che disperiamo di ottenere da' suoi Ministri nelle Isole, il beneficio 
sarebbe grandissimo, e i benefattori sarebbero rimeritati e dagli uomini viventi e futuri, e da Dio. 
Onde commettiamo a N. N. (qui i nomi dei due Deputati) Deputati nostri di presentarsi alla vostra 
Grandezza con questa lettera, e di esporle a voce le preghiere e l'intento del nostro popolo; perchè 
nella nostra rovina speriamo ancora di impetrare nelle dipendenze della Repubblica delle Sette Isole 
un angolo di terra dove le profughe famiglie di Parga possano riunirsi, e vivere secondo gli usi de' 
nostri antenati.</p>
                        <p>(qui le sottoscrizioni de' Primati)</p>
                     </body>
                  </text>
               </quote>
            </p>
            <p>10. Quanto più presto arriveranno i Deputati Pargioti, tanto meglio sarà.</p>
            <p>11. Importa assai che arrivino ignoti, perchè i Ministri Inglesi hanno mezzi arbitrari a 
impedire che forestieri entrino nell'Isola, ma è difficilissimo a farli uscire, perchè ciò dipende dal 
Consiglio privato.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
