<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://backend.bibliotecaitaliana.it/DTD/bibit.dtd">
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Saggio sulla letteratura contemporanea in Italia</title>
            <author>Ugo Foscolo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>194540 Kb in UTF-8</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Biblioteca Italiana</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <idno>bibit001031</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso
      personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Collezione BibIt</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Saggio sulla letteratura contemporanea in Italia</title>
               <title type="part">v.</title>
               <author>Foscolo, Ugo</author>
               <editor id="ed">Foligno, Cesare</editor>
               <publisher>F. Le Monnier</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Firenze</pubPlace>
               <date>1958</date>
               
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Tutti i materiali paratestuali della fonte cartacea non riconducibili alla
    responsabilità dell'autore dell'opera sono stati soppressi nella versione
    digitale</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction method="silent" status="medium">
               <p>Livello medio: controllo a video con collazione con edizione di
      riferimento</p>
            </correction>
            <quotation form="data" marks="all">
               <p>I simboli di citazione e di discorso diretto presenti sulla fonte cartacea
      sono stati rappresentati sulla versione digitale</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>I trattini di sillabazione a fine riga sono stati soppressi e le parole
      ricomposte</p>
            </hyphenation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="CGB">
               <bibl>Classificazione generi BibIt</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date>800</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="CGB">
               <term>Trattati</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06-08T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Novadata systems</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Digitalizzazione - OCR</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-04-21T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Sara Loddo</name>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Correzione linguistica</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05-20T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Ilenia Sabelli</name>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Codifica XML - Codifica manuale</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06-17T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Carla Deiana</name>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Validazione</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 n="Essay on the present literature of Italy">
            <head>ESSAY ON THE PRESENT LITERATURE OF ITALY</head>
            <div2 n="Introduzione">
               <p>It is the boast of the Italians, that their literature has flourished with unequal, but 
uninterrupted brilliancy, from the thirteenth century to the present day.</p>
               <p>The progress of time alone would naturally have produced and obliterated many 
innovations, but the frequent domestic revolutions, the repeated irruptions, the arms and the arts of 
strangers, succeeding each other rapidly and imperceptibly, and bringing with them new laws, and 
manners, and opinions, have occasioned in Italy more vicissitudes than are to be found in the 
literature of any other country. Thus it is that their critics have been able to point out at least ten 
different epoques when it has assumed certain characteristics, or, to use a single word, a 
physiognomy, altogether distinct from that of any preceding or subsequent period. The average 
duration assigned to each of these epoques, has been laid down at about half a century. This is the 
utmost length that any individual taste and mode of writing can be discovered to have 
prevailed.</p>
               <p>The above remark is purposely premised to a short account which it is intended to give 
of the present state of Italian literature; that is to say, of the character, of the actual epoque, which 
embraces not only those writers at present in existence, but others who have powerfully contributed 
to form the taste and the tone which will continue to prevail until succeeded by another revolution 
in the republic of letters. The latter Italian authors may be expected to form a diversity more distinct 
than those of any other generation, when it is recollected, that whilst they wrote the most 
extraordinary change was prepared and consummated, that had ever affected the moral or political 
world. That the great convulsions which shook not only “mightiest monarchies”, but 
also the mind of man, in all the countries of Europe, should communicate itself to these authors, 
was inevitable, and will be discovered in the works, the principles, the character, and the estimation, 
of the most celebrated amongst them, whom it is proposed to examine and pourtray. These authors 
will be their poets: who are selected, first, because the verse of every country is the depository of 
the language, the taste, and the manners, of the times; secondly, because this is found more 
particularly the case in those nations whose imagination is their predominant faculty; and, in the 
third place, because the writers chosen on this occasion, are in part distinguished for their 
compositions in prose.</p>
               <p>This method of illustration might be liable to objections in any other country than Italy, 
where the few men of superior genius are separated from the crowd of writers by a barrier, which in 
other nations is rarely visible until posterity has pronounced the final decision. In Italy the judgment 
is in some sort formed and given by their cotemporaries; and thus, although the struggle to attain the 
eminence may be more serious and protracted, there is less danger of future degradation.</p>
               <p>An intimate acquaintance is, however, requisite, to perceive the difference between the 
esteemed and the popular author; for, otherwise, the above–mentioned singularity of Italian 
literature would be reduced to a shade only of distinction from that of other countries. A book may 
be in the hands of all readers, and, during some years, be the study and the talk of all. This was the 
case with the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Animali parlanti</foreign>
                  </title> of Casti: but the author 
had no pretence or right to renown. On the other hand, a work which few comparatively shall 
peruse, because every one cannot understand, having obtained the suffrages of those distinguished 
above the common class of readers, acquires for the author an established name, which the people 
themselves are soon taught to repeat with respect, although entirely ignorant or insensible of the 
specific merit which has obtained their applause. Such esteem may be compared to the blind 
honours conferred upon a successful general by the peaceful peasantry, who wish no other signal or 
reason for their shouts than the gazette, but it is not less devoted.</p>
               <p>If we endeavour to account for this characteristic in the literature of Italy, a partial, or 
perhaps sufficing, reason may be found, in the difference between countries like England and 
France, and one in which, as there is no single capital, there are, comparatively speaking, none of 
those court intrigues, none of those party passions, none of those fashionable cabals and tribunals, 
which are all called into play and employed in Paris and London, in deciding the fate of authors. It 
is not that there are no reviews composed by the personal enemies or friends of the respective 
writers; it is not that fashion has no voice; but the injustice of criticism, or the folly of a coterie, 
which may sway the public opinion for awhile in one of the great cities, is inevitably corrected 
before it has run through the mass of disinterested readers, and travelled the wide circle of Venice, 
Bologna, Parma, Verona, Milan, Turin, Florence, Naples, and Rome. The same instances of 
undeserved neglect and elevation may be found in each of those towns, as are the constant 
complaint throughout the vast extent of our own country. But even in any single capital the error is 
more speedily corrected by the justice of many rival, or, what is better, impartial neighbours: and as 
for the whole of Italy, there cannot be an instance of that rapid rise and thus as sudden precipitation, 
of which we have seen so many examples in our times, and which are to be attributed solely to what 
we call the fashion of the day. You do not even hear the expressions usual with us, applied to their 
national writers. The favourite of <emph>the town</emph> would be an absurd solecism in a 
country where there are twenty towns with distinct literary interest and pretensions, and where the 
attachment of one city secures the opposition of another; nor, as it has been before mentioned, can 
some of the most established authors be said to be most <emph>in vogue</emph>, for they are 
certainly not the most read.</p>
               <p>A reviewer may irritate the public curiosity, a lady of high rank may give a letter of 
recommendation, but neither the one nor the other can raise those phantoms of fashion, who, 
although they come and depart like shadows, walk the whole round of our united kingdoms, with all 
the honours and attributes of substantial existence.</p>
               <p>If, then, we find any living author enjoying very nearly the same character in all the 
provinces of Italy, we can safely prognosticate that he has received his final estimation — 
that the just appreciation of his merits alone having raised him, will prevent him from ever sinking 
into total neglect; that he has become one of the national writers, subject, indeed, to the fluctuations 
which, as it has been before remarked, affect more especially the literature of Italy, but always to be 
ranked amongst the <emph>classics</emph> of his country.</p>
               <p>The above circumstance furnishes the foreigner with a criterion not found in other 
countries: his survey is facilitated by being contracted to a narrower space; and he has collected the 
judgment pronounced upon a very few, he need not embarrass himself with the multitude of writers, 
but be assured that he has seized the traits that are at present, and will always be esteemed, 
characteristic of the literature of the age. — Of the writers, then, whose influence may be 
more or less discerned in the formation of the present taste and style, it may be sufficient to 
enumerate six: Melchior Cesarotti, Joseph Parini, Victor Alfieri, Hippolitus Pindemonte, Vincent 
Monti, and Hugo Foscolo. The three first are, it is true, no longer alive, but they clearly belong to 
the present day, and are no less to be taken into an actual survey than their surviving cotemporaries. 
There is nothing bold in pronouncing that these are decidedly the authors of the day; but it is an 
endeavour of great difficulty, and no little danger, to attempt to shew the specific reputation which 
each of them enjoys, and to describe their respective performances so as to give, on the whole, the 
acknowledged result of their effects upon the opinions of their countrymen. Such an effort has, 
however, been made in the following sketches of these distinguished Italians, and so much of their 
biography has been added as appeared service able in illustrating the motives that inspired, and the 
occasions that called forth, their various compositions.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 n="Cesarotti">
               <head>CESAROTTI</head>
               <p>Melchior Cesarotti was a Paduan, and died, in extreme old age, in the year 1808. Bold, 
fruitful, eloquent, and deeply versed in ancient and modern literature, this writer impressed his 
readers with the conviction of his genius: and yet, although he resembled no one of his predecessors 
or cotemporaries, there was something more of novelty than originality in all his compositions.</p>
               <p>He was brought up in the ecclesiastical seminary of Padua, which prides itself, and with 
some justice, on the constancy and success with which it has preserved the latinity of the purer ages. 
Indeed the Latin verses of Cesarotti are a proof no less of his talents than of the merit of this 
celebrated institution, which, had he continued to pursue the same studies, would have produced a 
new Vida or Fracastorius. But he no sooner entered into holy orders and quitted the seminary, than 
he declared war against the poets of antiquity, and, more especially, of Greece. An Englishman 
passing through Venice, made him acquainted with Ossian, at that time the delight, or at least the 
wonder, of the transalpine critics: and Cesarotti lost no time in translating it into blank verse, 
accompanying his version with notes, for the most part, against Homer. Ossian transported the 
Italians; who did not, generally speaking, embarrass themselves with the examination of the 
authenticity of the pretended epic. Palmieri of Placentia, and a few others, ventured to contest the 
antiquity of the poet, but the mass of readers, seduced by the authority of Blair, or by their 
inclination to be pleased with their Italian Ossian, were resolved to discover the genuine son of 
Fingal in the spurious offspring of Macpherson. Some there were who still defended the heroes of 
the old school, and exclaimed against a precedent fatal to the reputation of the ancient models, and 
to the purity of the modern language. But they read the work and they admired the translator. His 
verses, in truth, are harmonious, are soft, are imbued with a colouring, and breathe an ardent spirit, 
altogether new; and, with the same materials, he has created a poetry, that appears written in a metre 
and a language entirely different from all former specimens. His superiority was evinced by the 
want of success in those who endeavoured to imitate him, and whose exaggerations and caricatures 
were received with a ridicule that, by little and little, was attached to their model, and partially 
diminished his fame. The translation of Ossian will, however, be always considered as an 
incontrovertible proof of the genius of Cesarotti, and of the flexibility of the Italian tongue.</p>
               <p>The reputation into which he thus leapt, as it were, at once, encouraged him to still 
bolder innovations; and being raised to the Greek professorship in his own university of Padua, he 
translated Demosthenes and others of the Greek orators, subjoining criticisms full of learning and 
ingenuity, the chief aim of which was to convince the world that the veneration with which they 
read those orators was derived more from their antiquity than their intrinsic excellence.</p>
               <p>His next work was a translation of the <title>Iliad</title>. But the magic of his Ossian 
was not transfused into his Italian Homer.</p>
               <p>This work is in ten large octavo volumes: each book is translated literally into Italian 
prose, and almost every passage is illustrated by the compared opinions of the critics of every 
nation, from Aristarchus to those of our own days. He <emph>invariably</emph> cites the 
adversaries of Homer, and <emph>often</emph> opposes them with the partisans of the poet. 
When he subjoins his own decision, it very rarely inclines in favour of his original.</p>
               <p>To every book thus translated and commented upon, he adds his own poetical version, 
which, as it was intended to correct the errors discovered in the original, changes, omits, and 
transfers from one book to another, whole passages of the text. These alterations were so many and 
so material, that, in the end, he resolved to change the title of the poem, and his <title>Iliad</title> 
reappeared as the “<title>Death of Hector</title>”.</p>
               <p>The bold style, and the harmonious numbers of his version, procured for it many 
readers, and the work was applauded by a public accustomed to admire the author. The journalists, 
who in Italy are frequently without learning, and almost always without genius, exalted the 
translation as an extraordinary and successful effort, and the harmony of the blank verse of the 
Death Hector, became in a short time proverbial. But some few literary men of real merit and 
discernment, whose voice it is much more difficult to suppress in Italy than in any other country, 
prognosticated that the work, at some future day, would be more frequently cited than read. Their 
prophecy is now fully verified.</p>
               <p>In his treatise on the Italian language, Cesarotti stepped forward to defend the privilege 
assumed by certain authors, of enriching, by new words and combinations, their native language. 
His positions are undeniable, his observations profound, and his deductions exceedingly just. The 
didactic form of his treatise has not deprived it of the elegance necessary for the attraction of his 
readers. The style is precise, yet ornamented: and very few authors have so happily combined the 
language of evidence and of metaphysical disquisition; very few have made a grammatical 
discussion so alluring, or have arrayed materials so abstruse in eloquence so engaging. This is the 
only work of Cesarotti's that has preserved its original reputation up to this day. The author himself 
abused, however, the privilege which he claimed for all writers, and in one the reviews then most 
esteemed in Italy, it was asserted that the preacher of liberty had awakened a spirit of licentiousness, 
and yet might easily raise himself to the dictatorship.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <quote>«<foreign lang="ita">predicando la libertà letteraria aveva suscitato la licenza e 
però gli fu facile ad erigersi in dittatore</foreign>»</quote>. See <foreign lang="ita">
                           <title>Annali di scienze e lettere</title>, anno 1811, num. 111</foreign>, article on the 
<title>Odyssey</title>.</p>
                  </note>

The truth was, that Cesarotti was, by his partisans, regarded as infallible, and was the terror of his 
opponents, whose censure was confined to the adoption of a practice contrary to his powerful 
example.</p>
               <p>His prose is endowed with all the qualities that constitute a superior writer. The depth is 
no obstacle to the clearness of his ideas; his manner is free, his phraseology abundant, his periods 
are harmonious. He is lively, yet graceful; he is not so copious as to be tedious, nor so brief as to be 
obscure; he is full of pleasantry, which never degenerates into affectation, or is applied to the 
purposes of malicious controversy. But those who were obliged, had they not been willing, to 
discover these excellencies in Cesarotti, were relieved from unqualified admiration, by finding that 
all of them were spoilt and rendered inefficient; in the first place, by the intemperate and systematic 
use of <emph>gallicims</emph>; and, secondly, by their being lost upon discourses either critical 
or metaphysical, and such as could not interest the general reader. It was in his power to have 
furnished a model of the oratorical style in his translation of Demosthenes; but his deliberate 
purpose and all his efforts in this work were directed to fritter down his original, and, with this 
unaccountable design, he has affected a style scrupulously <emph>Cruscan</emph> and 
pedantic.</p>
               <p>His <title>Familiar Letters</title>, published after his death, have discovered to us an 
excellence and a defect that might not be collected from his other writings; for the shew him to have 
been an indulgent encourager of the talents of others, as well as very liberal of his own information; 
but at the same time he appears so over prodigal of his praises as to incur the suspicion of 
premeditated flattery.</p>
               <p>His conversation was distinguished by its eloquence and its amenity; his ideas were 
rapid and clear, and he gave a certain grace and embellishment to the most abstruse arguments. He 
took delight in the education of those who attached themselves to his opinions, and were loyal to 
their literary faith, more especially when he discovered in them any signs of future excellence; and 
although he was far from rich, it was not unusual with him to receive his pupils as his domestic 
guests. His confidence went so far as to entrust them with his secrets. Nevertheless, notwithstanding 
his kind patronage, and their devoted attachement, his most constant disciples attained to no 
reputation: either because imitation is, in itself, incapable of rising above mediocrity, or because 
there was in the system of this great writer something rather pernicious than conducive to success. 
This circumstance, so painful for the head of a sect, did not, however, sour his temper, or diminish 
his regard. He was the same affectionate nobleminded man to the last, and his friends had just 
reason to praise him and to lament his loss.</p>
               <p>His political conduct was not distinguished for its constancy. The revolution found him 
more than a sexagenary devoted to literary pursuits — a priest — and one who had 
never wandered beyond the narrow confines of his native country, which for more than a century 
had enjoyed the most profound calm.</p>
               <p>Bonaparte had read and re–read the Italian Ossian, and at his first occupation of 
Padua he eagerly sent for Cesarotti, and named him one of the chiefs of the new government. Our 
author took that opportunity of publishing a small treatise on the rights and freedom of mankind, on 
the duties of the magistrate, and the character of the people. Three or four years afterwards the 
chances of war brought him into the hands of the Russian and the Austrians, and he was 
<emph>forced</emph>, if such an expression may be applied to such an exertion, to compose a 
short poem in praise of the victorious potentates.</p>
               <p>Finally, when Bonaparte had become Emperor, and was again master of the Venetian 
states, he created Cesarotti a knight commander of one of his orders, assigning to him, at the same 
time, a pension, which was meant to insure his gratitude and his praise. Napoleon was not mistaken; 
his pensioner published his poem, called <title>Pronéa</title>, or Providence, a most extravagant 
performance, where the style of Lucan, of Ossian, and of Claudian bewilders the reader, already lost 
amidst the mazes of metaphysics and of theological allegory. The work, from the first to the last 
page, was such as might be expected from a systematic innovator, from a devotee trembling on the 
brink of the grave, and from a poet who wrote by commission.</p>
               <p>He survived this efforts too short a time to enjoy his pension, but not before his poem 
had been consigned to oblivion.</p>
               <p>Had this writer been born in other times; had he expanded his ideas, and escaped from 
the circle of his own metaphysical speculations, by visiting other countries and mixing with other 
minds; had he encountered greater obstacles in his ascent to fame; but, above all, had he devoted 
himself to original composition, and made a more judicious use of his acquaintance with foreign 
literature, it is probable that Cesarotti would have taken a prominent place amongst the classical 
authors of his country. As it is, the Italians accuse his system, and accuse his example; but whilst 
they pronounce both the one and the other to have been highly prejudicial to his native literature, 
they are all willing to allow that he was possessed of great natural ability.</p>
               <p>Angelo Mazza, the school–fellow and the friend of Cesarotti, may be fairly 
subjoined to a mention of that poet. He is still alive, and enjoys a green old age at Parma. His first 
essay was made in the year 1764, when he translated the <title>Pleasures of the Imagination</title>, 
and convinced the Italian that the compressed style of Dante was capable of being applied to their 
blank verse, which as yet was little more than a string of sonorous syllables.</p>
               <p>The poetry published by him in a maturer age consists in great part of lyrical pieces on 
<title>Harmony</title>. They are to be found in two small volumes; and Saint Cecilia is the inspirer 
and patroness of two of his best odes. It was not likely that he sould equal the invention of Dryden; 
he wisely, therefore, was contented with trying a version of that poet, and his translation of that 
lyrical masterpiece has the merit of having extended the fame of our laureate to every corner of 
Italy.</p>
               <p>The imitations, and even the translation of Mazza, have a certain air of originality 
impressed not only on their style, which is extremely energetic, but even on the ideas which appear 
generally drawn from a metaphysical turn of mind. He excels much in the poetical array of abstract 
images, and what the <title>Theodicea</title> of Leibnitz is in prose, he sometimes contrives to 
execute in verse. In spite, however, of the inspired tone of some of his verses on the Universe, and 
the wisdom of the Creator, displayed, according to Mazza, in the harmony of all things, and 
notwithstanding he has represented this same harmony under aspects entirely new and beautiful, the 
poet has failed no less than all others who have attempted to embellish these sacred subjects, in 
keeping alive the interest of his reader, and has succeeded only in attracting the admiration of those 
who are delighted to see objections encountered and difficulties overcome. His odes are composed 
of stanzas, the melody of which is often sacrificed to what the musicians call <foreign lang="ita">contrapunto</foreign>, which is calculated to surprise more than please, and he has 
even adopted those difficult rhymes which the Italians call <foreign lang="ita">sdrucciole</foreign>, or slippery, and which not only lengthen the eleven syllabled 
verse into twelve syllables, but change the position of the accent, as appears from the following 
specimen extracted from the same Mazza:

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>A me le voci di concento gravide</l>
                        <l>A me le forme dello stil Pindarico,</l>
                        <l>Date a me l'inspirata arpa di Davide.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>The only work of Mazza which has been often printed, and has hit the taste of the 
Italians, is a poem in thirty pages, addressed to Cesarotti, in which he gives a masterly sketch of the 
great poets of every nation, and has placed the English on a distinguished eminence amongst the 
immortal brotherhood. It is only the women, who affect our endemic melancholy, and the younger 
readers, who occasion the immense demand for Young's <title>Night Thoughts</title>, translated 
as they are into poor verse, a or ampullated prose; for the more enlightened Italians study Milton 
and Shakespeare.</p>
               <p>Mazza is remarkable for the candour with which he has treated his cotemporaries, even 
those attached to a system totally different from his own. This discretion, however, has not silenced 
the voice of criticism, and in spite of his own reserve, his partisans and his opponents have carried 
on a war of words, which is seldom to be equalled by English polemics, and is outrageous even in a 
country distinguished by the pedantry, the fury, and the illiberality of its literary quarrels. The 
foreigners who have by turns usurped the Italian provinces, have extended their claims to all the 
productions of that fruitful soil: not only the corn, and the wine, and the oil are put in requisition, 
but the tithe of the poetry is claimed by the conquerors. Mazza, in his quality of perpetual secretary 
of the academy of Parma, has composed the usual complimentary sonnets of the successive 
governments of his country, but he has cautiously avoided all political topics, and left his opinion 
still uncompromised and unknown.</p>
               <p>It is generally reported that he has long finished, although he has never ventured to 
publish, a translation of Pindar. The Italians are impatient, but they are also fearful, for the result. 
The Greek poet has had many happy imitators in this country, and especially in the days of 
Chiabrera, of Filicaia, of Menzini, and of Guidi; but his translators have failed here no less than in 
all other countries. Mazza, besides his poetical reputation, has the character of a scholar profoundly 
versed in ancient and modern languages, and the acquisition of the latter is the more singular, as he 
has never been out of Italy, and indeed has seldom quitted his native town.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 n="Joseph Parini">
               <head>JOSEPH PARINI</head>
               <p>Parini was almost the only Italian poet of last century who dared to conceive, and 
certainly he was the only one capable of completing the project of directing the efforts of his art 
towards the improvement of his fellow citizens. If by <emph>moralizing his song</emph> he has 
failed to correct his cotemporaries, he has, however, acquired a reputation much more valuable than 
can be the share of those whose talents are devoted solely to the amusement of the public.</p>
               <p>His parents were peasants on the borders of the lake Pusiano, the Eupilis of Pliny, about 
twenty miles north of Milan. It is usual in Italy to choose from the poorest classes those destined to 
supply the humblest and most laborious duties in the church, whilst the valuable benefices are 
reserved for the younger sons of noble families. When one of these children * of poverty shews 
signs of superior talents, the monks endeavour to attach him to their community, and the charity of 
the bishop provides him a gratuitous education. In this way Parini was sent to study in the capital of 
Austrian Lombardy. He applied to his scholastic pursuits until nearly his twentieth year, when his 
constitution, feeble from the beginning, almost sunk under an attack which took away the use of his 
lower limbs, and occasioned his retreat from the seminary in a condition that seemed to deprive him 
of all hopes of aspiring even to a country curacy. All that medical care, all that time could do for the 
improvement of his health, from his youth to the day of his death, barely enabled him to crawl along 
by the help of a stick, or by leaning on the arm of a friend.</p>
               <p>Some of the verses published in his posthumous works, are painfully affecting, from the 
picture which they afford of the extreme indigence in which he languished even after he had arrived 
ad years of maturity. His whole livelihood, and that of an angel mother, were derived from 
composing articles for a newspaper. He speaks thus in requesting an intimate friend to send him 
relief:

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>La mia povera madre non ha pane</l>
                        <l>Se non da me, ed io non ho danaro</l>
                        <l>Da mantenerla almeno per domane.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <note place="foot">
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <foreign lang="ita">Parini, <title>Opere</title>, vol. III</foreign>
                           </bibl>.</p>
                     </note>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>He had already published some poetry which had dropt after the partial applauses that 
usually succeed the first essays of every author, that are not bad enough for ridicule, nor good 
enough for envy. Parini would never allow these specimens to be reprinted. It was not until his 
thirty–fifth year that he published the first canto of that poem, which rendered him 
formidable to the most powerful families around him in the eyes of the Eterary world as the founder 
of a new school in poetry. This poem is called the Day (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Il 
Giorno</foreign>
                  </title>), and is divided into four cantos — Morning (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Mattino</foreign>
                  </title>); Noon (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Meriggio</foreign>
                  </title>); Evening (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Vespro</foreign>
                  </title>); and Night (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Notte</foreign>
                  </title>) — and it contains a satirical description of the manner in 
which the Italian nobles contrive to waste away the four and twenty hours of an existence for the 
most part truly despicable. Before we enter into an examination of this poem, a word or two may be 
requisite on the author. The literary history of every nation abounds with instances of the distresses 
and ill success of those endowed with the finest abilities; and it is a painful truth, that the union of 
the severest virtue with those abilities is no shield against the arrows of Fortune.</p>
               <p>The case of Parini, however, is not to be confounded with these examples. Infirm, 
indigent, without the advantages of a regular education, struggling against the obscurity of his birth, 
and the disgrace of poverty, he lived in a city where the nobles are not only more rich, but are 
perhaps more haughty and more ignorant than in any other town in Italy. At that time they were 
more important from their influence, direct and indirect, and formidable from the impunity with 
which they could give a loose to their revenge.</p>
               <p>It is universally known, that before the revolution the Italian nobles enjoyed a kind of 
prescriptive right of employing assassins; but it is more wonderful still, that at this day, and in the 
face of the new <emph>noblesse</emph>, created by Bonaparte, there is not a single instance of 
the daughter or wife of any but those in possession of ancient titles being admitted to the 
ball–room or drawing–room of a Milanese Patrician. The same absurd distinction 
prevails at Turin. At Venice, at Bologna, at Florence, at Rome, the exclusion is not so strictly 
observed, and a few young females of the middling rakns are allowed to stand in the same dance 
with the daughters of barons and of counts.</p>
               <p>Such was the state of society that Parini undertook to correct. And this difficult, this 
dangerous task he adventured upon, by boldly reproaching the nobles with their vices and their 
crimes. He raised his own reputation by the depression of a whole order, which, in spite of their 
being essentially more despicable than in any other country of Europe, were, owing to the ignorance 
and extreme poverty of the lower classes, in fact more respectable. The care taken by Parini to 
conceal his personal allusions, could not prevent the discovery that his portraits were all drawn from 
living characters; and if his originals recognised their likeness only now and then, the public were 
never mistaken. There was not a single Milanese who did not see, in the chief personage of the 
poem, the Prince Belgiojoso, of the reigning family of Este, the eldest brother of the Field Marshal 
of the same name, who was Austrian Ambassador at our court, and Governor of the Low 
Countries.</p>
               <p>It should be here observed, to the honour of Parini, and indeed of the Italian authors in 
general, that, let a work be ever so much admired, it never brings the writer money enough to defray 
the expense of the first edition. There is but a very limited number of readers in Italy; and though a 
work may receive from their applause a character which secures the esteem of the whole nation, a 
multitude of purchasers, such as we are accustomed to, is not to be procured by any merit, or any 
accident. Twelve hundred names to a subscription are reckoned an extraordinary instance of public 
patronage, and it is hazardous to demand more than three francs (half a crown) for any new 
production in a single volume under the quarto size. The copyright law can hardly exist in a country 
divided into so many small governments, and the booksellers find it no difficult matter to elude the 
prosecutions, which must be transferred from one state to another before they can be brought before 
any competent tribunal. After the revolution, an effort was made to correct this abuse; but it was 
found almost impossible to change the practice of a whole class of tradesmen, long habituated to 
consider all literary profits their own, and to esteem every mercenary art a fair branch of 
speculation.</p>
               <p>Those accustomed to the liberality of English publishers, which affords a decent 
subsistence to those whose talents and whose fame do not rise above mediocrity, will hardly believe 
that the best authors in Italy think themselves fortunate if they find a publisher to take the expense 
of printing off their hands. In that country the booksellers are also printers, and have it in their 
power to multiply indefinitely the copies of any edition, without accounting for the accruing profits. 
The swearing of the printer, and our other protections of literary property, are unpractised and 
unknown.</p>
               <p>Alfieri, in a sort of preface, in verse, prefixed to the second edition of his tragedies, 
complains that his eagerness for renown has cost him a portion of his health, of his intellect, of his 
peace of mind, and, above all, of his fortune; the latter having been sacrificed to the rapacity of the 
bookseller.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>Profonder tutto in linde stampe il mio,</l>
                        <l>E perchè altri mi compri, accattar io:</l>
                        <l>Soffrire il revisor che l'uomo strazia;</l>
                        <l>Appiccicarmi i masnadier librai</l>
                        <l>Che a credenza ricevon e fan grazia</l>
                        <l>Nè metallo per foglio rendon mai.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>There were, however, certain coincidences favourable to the bold project of Parini. A 
sort of colony of French Encyclopedists had settled at Milan, and four or five Patricians having 
taken to reading, dared also to disseminate in writing the principles of the approaching revolution. 
The Marquis Beccaria had recently published his work on Crimes and Punishments, which effected 
an important change in the criminal jurisprudence of his own country, and extended its beneficial 
influence to many other nations, where torture prevailed, and was consequently abolished. Joseph II 
had himself began those innovations, which ended by diminishing the preponderating influence of 
the Lombard nobles. Count Firmian, the governor of those provinces, when questioned as to the 
publication of the poem of Parini, exclaimed, “Let him make haste; we want it 
mightily!” — <foreign lang="fra">Qu'il se hâte, nous en avons une necessité 
extrème</foreign>.</p>
               <p>In addition to such a powerful ally, Parini was backed by all the middling classes of 
society, which generally speaking, are certainly the most moral and the most enlightened portion of 
civilized mankind. Some individuals amongst them having quarrelled with the 
church–rectors of certain collegiate establishments, found in Parini a champion who 
overwhelmed their adversaries with a few strokes of the pen. Parini published a pamphlet on that 
occasion, which, in the cooler hours of revision, appeared to him too violent and he would not 
suffer it to proceed to a second edition: but this work introduced him to notice before the 
publication of his poem, and those whose cause he had advocated, continued his friends to the last 
moments of his melancholy existence.</p>
               <p>The <title>Day</title> is in one continued strain of irony from the first line to the last. 
The author asumes the character of preceptor to a nobleman, and teaches him how to devote his 
morning to the toilette, his noon to the serious occupations of the table, his afternoon to the public 
walks and his night to the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Conversazioni</foreign>
                  </title>. The most 
frivolous actions, the most contemptible vices, the most ridiculous follies, and sometimes the most 
atrocious crimes, are detailed with minuteness, and always with the pretext of recommendation. The 
“Advice to Servants” is carried into the highes departments of society, and a 
magnificence of diction and of images is tastefully employed, instead of the familiar tone of Swift, 
to pourtray the luxury and the pride which the Italian nobility carefully wrap round the naked 
wretchedness of their hearts.</p>
               <p>The variety of the objects, and the numerous portraits of individuals, all in the higher 
classes, of every age and sex, engage the attention, whilst the faithful and fine–spun 
description of manners keeps alive the curiosity of the reader. The poet has shewn no little address 
in contrasting the effiminacy of the actual race of nobles, and the industry and the courage of their 
ancestors, who, in the middle ages, restored the civilization of the South, and, with unshaken 
constancy, defended the liberties of the Italian republics. This contrast naturally transported Parini 
to the days of Romance; and the wild life of the military patricians, the old castles, and the glittering 
arms of the half barbarous ages, were a happy relief for the silken barons, the palaces, and the 
embroidered suits of his contemporaries, whom it was necessary to amuse in oder to instruct. The 
ruins of dungeons and towers neglected by the heirs of those who raised them, enabled the poet to 
employ his fancy in restoring them to their ancient splendour, and he thus threw in those sombre 
shades and colourings which the Germans afterwards appropriated to themselves, and were believed 
to have formed a new and national school of poetic fiction.</p>
               <p>With this mixture of romance Parini also recurred to the characters and allegories of the 
old mythology, the favourite resource of the Italians, who still think it the only fabulous system 
whose images combine the truth of real nature with the charms of ideal grace. But even in this 
department of his art, which an Eglishman would abandon as hopeless, our author contrived to give 
an air of reality to his classical fables, by applying them to the practices and principles of his own 
times. Thus it is that his Cupid and Hymen are introduced. They are engaged in a war to all 
appearance interminable, but they agree to treat, and peace is made on condition that Cupid shall 
reign all day, and Hymen all night. An English reader would not be much struck with this invention; 
but whoever meets a handsome Italian matron, decently pacing between her husband and her 
Cavalier Servente, will instantly remember the Love and Hymen of Parini, and the graceful solemn 
air with which his verses march majestically along.</p>
               <p>Our own nation can hardly have a just idea of this species of poetry. The Italian who 
admire it the most compare it to the <title>Georgics</title>; and the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Giorno</foreign>
                  </title> has certainly more than one property in common with the 
poem of Virgil. Both one and the other are employed in dignifying topics essentially common and 
familiar. Both one and the other display their poetical vigour in frequent episodes; and the Italian 
perhaps has gone less out of his way for those embellishments than the Latin poet. It was the 
misfortune, not the fault, of Parini, that he could not employ the hexametral structure; and owing, 
partly to the same defect of language, and partly, perhaps, to real inferiority, he was not able to 
adorn every picture with those images, nor lend to every word that harmony, which are the 
constituent excellence of Virgil. If Parini's style does not rival that of Virgil, it is some comfort for 
the Italians to think, that their poet has approached that great master nearer than any other follower.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg>
                        <l>.... <foreign lang="lat">longo sed proximus intervallo</foreign>.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>

His countrymen are, besides, hardy enough to suppose, that in the grouping, in the invention, in the 
connexion of all the parts with the whole, the pictures of the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Giorno</foreign>
                  </title> are superior to those of the <title>Georgics</title>. It is not, 
certainly, too hazardous to assert, that no one can learn farming from the verses of Virgil, but that 
much instruction may be gained by avoiding the follies which characterise the hero of Parini. If the 
<title>Sopha</title> of Cowper were a little more varied, and tinctured with satire, it would, in the 
domestic details, and the easy flowing versification, be a tolerable counterpart of the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Giorno</foreign>
                  </title> — at least we cannot furnish a stronger 
resemblance.</p>
               <p>The versification of Parini is not altogether unlike the Latin, and is entirely different 
from that of the other authors who in this age particularly distinguished themselves by trying every 
variety with which they could rival each other, and improve the structure of Italian verse. This has 
been already remarked in the articles on Cesarotti and Mazza, and the same truth will be deduced 
from the subsequent notices of this essay. The imagery, the expressions, the numbers, the very 
words of Parini, have a certain solemnity which they never altogether lay aside; and the melody and 
change of tone so conspicuous in the soft and varied descriptions of the Greek and Latin epics, are, 
in the verses of the Italian poet, not so much recognized at once, as they are imperceptibly felt by 
the reader.</p>
               <p>It may be sufficient to give a short example of the distinction here alluded to. The poet 
conducts his hero to the public walks: the time chosen is the night–fall: he leaves his 
mistress alone in her carriage, and slipping through the crowd, steals quietly into the carriage of 
another lady, who has also been abandoned by her Cavalier. Such a scene required some delicacy to 
pourtray. A loose or a careless poet would hardly steer clear of indecent images: but Parini is not 
less adroit with his carriage and his night, than is Virgil with the cave and the storm, that were so 
fatal to the happiness of Dido. He invokes the goddess of Darkness with his usual irony, and prays 
her to arrest her progress, that he may contemplate at leisure the exploits of his chosen hero.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg>
                        <l part="F">
                           <foreign lang="ita">.... Ma la Notte segue</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Sue leggi inviolabili, e declina</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Con tacit'ombra sopra l'emispero;</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">E il rugiadoso piè lenta movendo,</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Rimescola i color varj, infiniti,</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">E via gli sgombra con l'immenso lembo</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Di cosa in cosa: e suora de la morte</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Un aspetto indistinto, un solo volto,</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Al suolo a i vegetanti a gli animali</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">A i grandi ed a la plebe equa permette;</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">E i nudi insieme e li dipinti visi</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Delle belle confonde, e i cenci, e l'oro:</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Nè veder mi concede all'aer cieco</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Qual de' cocchj si parta o qual rimanga</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Solo all'ombre segrete: e a me di mano</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Tolto il pennello, il mio Signore avvolge</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Per entro al tenebroso umido velo.</foreign>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheless it is evident that this kind of poetry, beautiful as it is, and recalling to us 
some of the most delicate passages of the <title>Rape of the Lock</title>, is addressed rather to the 
imagination than to the heart. Yet Parini has occasionally proved himself a master of the pathetic, 
and he calls forth tears of regret when he shews us a servant, after twenty years of faithful 
attachment, dismissed, persecuted, and reduced to beggary, for no other offence than slightly 
beating a favourite dog that had bit him. We may be here reminded of some of the efforts of Mr. 
Crabbe, when he is most harmonious and most tender: but the Italian awakes, by the same picture, 
feelings more allied to indignation than to pity, and his sleepless irony somewhat fatigues the 
attention, and helps to counteract the general effect. The perpetual aggrandisement and decoration 
of objects, in themselves little and mean, display a curious felicity, and succeed in exciting the 
proposed ridicule; but the effect diminishes as the effort is continued and concludes in being 
mistaken for affectation. A single pebble set tastefully in diamonds may amuse the spectator, but a 
whole cabinet of such curiosities would hardly be worth attention or examination.</p>
               <p>Another deficiency will be apparent to the foreign reader of Parini. The poet never saw 
any other city than Milan. His infirmities and his poverty confined him entirely at home. It was thus 
impossible that he should not give too much importance to objects which those accustomed to a 
wider sphere of action would consider unworthy of regard. It was natural, also, for the same reason, 
that his style, formed altogether on the classical writers, should occasionally degenerate into 
pedantry. What could be performed by an exquisite and cultivated taste has been done by Parini, but 
he is not to be classed with the inspired poets. The great defect of the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Giorno</foreign>
                  </title> is the little interest excited by the hero of the poem, who is 
contemptible from his entrance to his exit. Yet even this capital objection seldom occurs to those 
absorbed in admiration at the effect produced by the address and execution of the author.</p>
               <p>The great merit of Parini lies in the dignity, not only of his style, but of his conduct in 
wielding the weapons of satire. His poem has nothing of that impotent rage against the powerful, of 
that invidious detraction of the wealthy, of that plaintive accusation against patronage and 
ingratitude, which have been the favo[u]rite topics of all satirists, from Horace to the 
English Imitator of Juvenal. The vices of the great he contemplates with a pity worthy 
[of] the noblest of their own order; he does not indulge himself with epigrams; he never 
degenerates into obscenity; he will not condescend to be the buffoon, nor to administer to the bad 
passions of the multitude.</p>
               <p>There is a grandeur in the expression of his censures which casts, as it were, a shield 
between those whom he condemns, and the anger and hatred of the people. He respects human 
nature; he is not misanthropic; and he takes care to attribute the depravity of the nobles to their total 
idleness. Throughout his whole satire he shows himself bent upon the generous project of repairing 
the disgrace of his country, and never incurs the suspicion that he would only satisfy his private 
animosities.</p>
               <p>Soon after the appearance of this poem, all those of easy circumstances in the middle 
classes, and the few patricians who, being addicted to literary pursuits, were the natural opponents 
of the great body of the nobles, interested themselves with the Austrian government in providing for 
Parini. They persuaded that government to found a professorship of eloquence expressly for their 
favourite, who justified the high expectations entertained of him; and, by his efforts in his new 
capacity, gave a stability to his rising reputation. He was indeed by nature qualified more than any 
one, perhaps, of his cotemporaries, to give lessons on the <foreign lang="fra">belles 
lettres</foreign>, and to perform that task in a way totally different from that usually employed in 
the Italian schools. There was a gravity, and at the same time an ease, in his eloquence, which 
enabled him to cite the examples of the former great writers with a powerful effect, and to illustrate 
them with new and brilliant observations. He applied the various theories of the sublime and 
beautiful not only to the productions of the pen, but to all the creations of nature; and many of his 
cotemporaries, already in possession of literary renown, were not ashamed to put themselves to the 
school of Parini. Those persons, and readers in general, were perhaps surprised to find, when they 
came to peruse his dissertations in print, that the ideas, although just, were seldom very profound: 
that a clear method, a chaste style, and an ingenious view of the subject, were their chief merit; but 
that the flow of words, the soul, the fire of expression and sentiment, had vanished with the 
delivery, and that the genius, and even the polished correctness of the poet, were not to be 
recognised in the discourses of the rhetorician.</p>
               <p>Parini was so painfully scrupulous, and at the same time so idle a writer, that he never 
published more than the two first cantos of his poem, the whole of which does not amount to four 
thousand lines. The two last cantos were published after his death, and they contain several 
half–finished verses, a great many variations, and two large chasms, which a long life was, it 
seems, too short to enable him to fill up to his satisfaction. This severity of taste he applied to others 
as well as to himself; and it was his favourite expression, when speaking even of Virgil and Horace, 
<quote>“<hi rend="italic">We should study them in those passages were they are not mortal 
men like ourselves</hi>”</quote>. From such a master the youth of Milan imbibed a 
delicacy of taste bordering upon affectation, and these scruples were easily cherished in a people 
less given to poetry than any other of the inhabitants of Italy. Indeed Parini himself is the only 
distinguished poet that this city has produced from the revival of letters to the present day.</p>
               <p>In addition to this individual propensity, it may be remarked that a severity of judgment 
prevails more or less with all the Italians, who are, as it were, saturated with poetry, and are besides 
accustomed to disregard the matter in comparison with the manner of metrical expression — 
a feeling deducible from the surpassing variety and beauty and strength of their language. Add to 
this that they judge all modern compositions with a reference to their most ancient poets, whom 
they worship with a veneration almost superstitious.</p>
               <p>Parini was not remarkable for his erudition, and knew but very little Greek. He could not 
write Latin, but he felt all the beauties of the Roman writers, and made them perceptible to his 
audience. His favourite Italian studies were Dante, Ariosto, and the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Aminta</foreign>
                  </title> of Tasso; yet he imitated none of these great writers; and it 
may be said of him as of our own Swift, that it would be difficult to point out a single idea that he 
has borrowed from his predecessors. He may be called an imitator, inasmuch as he sedulously 
traced back to their great constituent causes the effects produced by the old writers, and then made 
use of his discovery; but his manner is altogether his own; is inspired by his own genius, and 
attempered by his own inexorable taste. He followed the rule of Horace which inculcates the 
sacrifice of every thought, however noble, which is found incapable of embellishment: and he 
renounced the adoption of those beauties, which vulgar readers are apt to call natural, but which in 
fact are obvious and commonplace.</p>
               <p>Treatises upon the fine arts, and more particularly the lives of celebrated artists, were his 
favourite and constant study. Amongst the few books which he possessed at the time of his death, 
his executors found two copies of <title>Vasari's Biography</title> (<foreign lang="lat">sic</foreign>), both of them worn away by repeated perusal. He never applied either to 
drawing or to music, but he was perfectly well acquainted with the theory, and sensible to the 
charms, of both, and the most celebrated professors had frequent recourse to his advice. His 
posthumous works furnish us with the ideas, the composition, and even the details of several 
pictures which he had communicated to distinguished artists, and which are now to be seen, 
faithfully executed according to his directions, in many of the palaces at Milan. Parini employed, 
indeed, his whole life in carrying into practice the maxim that <emph>poetry should be 
painting</emph>; for, with the exception of Dante, the other Italian poets have only occasional 
pictures: all the rest is but description. Parini effected by dint of meditation that which was the 
natural production of the wonderful genius of Dante, and it would be difficult to point out ten 
consecutive lines in the poem of the Milanese from which a painter might not extract a complete 
picture, with all the requisite varieties of attitude and expression.</p>
               <p>Parini also published in his lifetime about twenty odes, of which the Italians consider 
<emph>four</emph> as inimitable, six or seven of the others tolerable, and the remainder 
absolutely bad. The whole of them bear a nearer resemblance to those of Horace than of Pindar, but 
neither of them has a shadow of likeness to the lyric poetry of Petrarch, or of Chiabrera, or of Guidi. 
Not only the style, but even the language appears quite diferent. It is his constant practice here, as in 
the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Giorno</foreign>
                  </title>, to avoid detailed descriptions, and to 
throw out his images in mass and at one stroke of his pencil. He has also the same object in view; 
namely, the correction of national manners.</p>
               <p>The ode addressed to a young woman of eighteen, who had adopted the Parisian fashion, 
then called “<foreign lang="fra">robe à la guillotine</foreign>”, is written in a style 
more than usually intelligible for a foreign reader. The beauty and the innocence of the maiden are 
presented under colours that contrast admirably with the depravity of mind and manners which the 
poet foresees must be the consequence of imitating so vile an example.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">Da scellerata scure</foreign>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">Tolto è quel nome; infamia</foreign>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">Del secolo spietato</foreign>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">E diè funesti augurii</foreign>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">Al femminile ornato</foreign>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">E con le truci Eumenidi</foreign>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">Le care Grazie avvinse</foreign>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">E di crudele immagine</foreign>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <foreign lang="ita">La tua bellezza tinse.</foreign>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>


He digresses to the history of the ancient Roman females, from the earliest times to those days of 
cruelty and corruption when they thronged the gladiatorial shows, and a Vestal gave the signal for 
the slaughter.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>Potè all'alte patrizie</l>
                           <l>Come alla plebe oscura</l>
                           <l>Giocoso dar solletico</l>
                           <l>La soffrente natura.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Che più? Baccanti e cupide</l>
                           <l>D'abbominando aspetto</l>
                           <l>Sol dall'uman pericolo</l>
                           <l>Acuto ebber diletto,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>E da i gradi e da i circoli</l>
                           <l>Co' moti e con le voci</l>
                           <l>Di già maschili, applausero</l>
                           <l>A i duellanti atroci:</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Creando a sè delizia</l>
                           <l>E de le membra sparte,</l>
                           <l>E de gli estremi aneliti,</l>
                           <l>E del morir con arte.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>The poet has contrived that the progress of his ideas shall correspond with the gradual 
corruption with which the imprudent imitation of novelty seduces by little and little the incautious 
female into the worst practices of debauchery.</p>
               <p>The biographer of Parini, who has furnished the greater portion of the preceding 
account, has been accused of swelling out the works of his author into six volumes, although those 
published during his lifetime scarcely occupy two hundred pages.</p>
               <p>It may be added, that of all the posthumous works, the two last cantos of his 
<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Giorno</foreign>
                  </title> is the only one which deserved to be rescued 
from that obscurity to which they had been consigned by their scrupulous author.</p>
               <p>Not that they are deficient in affording instruction to those who delight in the study of 
human nature, and love to watch the development of the mind. The odes which are reckoned 
Parini's best were composed in his old age; and such of the verses as appear in their first form, and 
as were not intended for publication, are remarkable chiefly for their good sense, and for their 
unaffected taste. But their imagery is not abundant; their style has little warmth, and the turns are 
common–place and trite. They enable us then to form some conception of the time and 
thought employed in the elevation and constant support of a style which frequently borders upon 
sublimity. His commerce with mankind laid open to him the most secret recesses of the heart, and 
furnished him with that acquaintance with our natural foibles of which he discovers so intimate a 
knowledge in his principal poem, and in his odes. In the same manner his continued and minute 
contemplation of nature in all her varieties furnished him with the beauties necessary for his 
poetical purposes, and enabled him to recognise their recurrence in the old classical writers, and to 
demonstrate their existence to others.</p>
               <p>The result of study and cultivation was never more conspicuous than in the example of 
Parini. It had all the appearance, and produced all the effect of genius: and yet his was, doubtless, 
one of those minds rather capable of culture, than naturally fruitful. The soil might have brought 
forth none but barren plants, had not care, and labour, and patience, qualified it to receive the seed, 
and supply the nourishment of they richest productions.</p>
               <p>The Milanese nobles did not dare to revenge themselves openly for the boldness of 
Parini. There is a story current of an attempt to assassinate him, but this, perhaps, is an invention 
suggested by the ancient manners of Italy. His enemies took another course. The emoluments of his 
professorship amounted only to 3000 francs, a little more than one hundred pounds a year.</p>
               <p>Leopold II, on a visit to Milan, was struck with the physiognomy of an old man, lame, 
and moving slowly along, but with an air of dignity. He asked his name, and being told that it was 
Parini, ordered the municipal council to increase his pension sufficiently to enable him to keep a 
small carriage. But the verbal command of a foreign monarch is seldom strictly obeyed in distant 
provinces, where the nobles have an interest or a will distinct from their duty. Parini continued 
without any other prop than his stick. The poet whom the Milanese pointed out to strangers as the 
pride and glory of their city, was often pushed into the dirt, and was repeatedly near being run over 
by the carriages, in the streets where there is no pavement for foot passengers.</p>
               <p>In an ode, which he calls the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Caduta</foreign>
                  </title>, the 
<title>Fall</title>, he describes the accidents which happened to him in rainy and foggy days; and 
although this production is not in the first rank of his poetry, it can never be perused without 
delight, nor be quoted without exciting our admiration at the profound pathos, the honest pride, and 
the philosophy with which it abounds.</p>
               <p>The French, on their arrival in Italy, soon understood the active part which the literary 
class had played in the revolution. They employed many of these individuals, and amongst others 
Parini, who found himself all at once amongst the chiefs of the republican government, with no 
other qualification or capital for such an elevation, than what was derived from a love of liberty, a 
habit of speaking the truth, an unbending character, and a total disregard of all selfish interests. He 
felt the embarrassment of his situation, and having often spoken harshly to the French generals, it 
was not difficult for him to obtain permission to retire, after a few weeks of thankless employment. 
His name and his integrity commanded respect, and the opposition of a whole life against the 
nobles, made him regarded by all the lower classes as the great partisan of the democracy. This 
influence was not lost even when he opposed the follies of the populace. They still shew a square at 
Milan, opposite to the great theatre, which was one day filled by a large mob of idle fellows, who 
ran about crying, “<hi rend="italic">Long life to the Republic — death to the 
Aristocrats!</hi>” Parini issued from a coffee–house and exclaimed, 
«<foreign lang="ita">Viva la Repubblica — e morte a nessuno; Canaglia 
stolta!</foreign>» The crowd instantly dispersed. Whatever may be the honours acquired by 
poetry in England, we cannot form an idea of the influence enjoyed by a man who has obtained a 
great literary reputation in a country where the largest portion of the people cannot read. He is 
listened to with a sort of religious obedience.</p>
               <p>The circles at Milan were afraid of every word that might drop from Parini, and he now 
and then abused his acknowledged ascendancy. But his intolerance never extended to his friends: 
with them he was indulgent to the last degree, and his severity was laid aside for a sort of infantine 
joviality. He was pleased with the company of those young people who were distinguished by the 
fire, the frankness, and the <foreign lang="fra">etourderie</foreign> of their age: but he was 
incensed somewhat extravagantly against those who either affected, or were naturally inclined, to 
gravity. He was complaisant and affable to strangers who came, even without introduction, to visit 
him; but if they unfortunately ventured to praise him, they did not escape without a reprimand, and 
found his door shut against them afterwards.</p>
               <p>His philosophy, strengthened as it was by the useful alliance of disease and age, did not, 
however, defend him against the attacks of love; and the odes written towards the end of his life, are 
sufficient proof that he never looked upon female charms with impunity. He confesses this truth, 
and perhaps has adopted the safest course to avoid ridicule, by declaring openly, that his good 
genius, which had preserved him from the tortures of ambition and avarice, had still left him 
accessible to the soft torment of the most tender and most disinterested of all the passions.</p>
               <p>Those high–born dames who were often the objects of his affection and of his 
poetry, were much flattered by his preference, and forgave him all that he had said of their husbands 
and of their <foreign lang="ita">Cavalieri Serventi</foreign>. With these he never made peace. 
And although he was an inmate in many great houses, he staid not a moment after he saw that he 
was required to submit to condescensions incompatible with his principles, and unbecoming his 
character. After all that has been said of the liberality of the great, it is clear that the precedence 
granted to genius does not commence during the lifetime even of the most fortunate writer. It was 
by a noble perseverance that Parini, indigent, unknown, imperfect, and perpetually boasting of his 
paternal plough, succeeded so far as to make himself respected by those powerful classes whose 
vices he derived; and maintained the dignity of his character and calling in a country where flattery, 
common as it is elsewhere, is found more base and abject amongst the men of letters than in the 
other orders, where the poets are very often the buffoons of their society, and where the tutors of 
boys of rank are confounded with the domestics of the family. At the time that almost all the Italian 
<emph>rhymesters</emph>, an innumerable class, were dedicating their canzoni and their sonnets 
to their respective patrons, Parini refused to recite a single verse at the table of any great man.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See the ode entitled <title>
                           <foreign lang="ita">La Recita de' 
Versi</foreign>
                        </title>.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He is to be exactly recognised in the portrait which he has given of himself.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>Me, non nato a percotere</l>
                        <l>Le dure illustri porte,</l>
                        <l>Nudo accorrà, ma libero,</l>
                        <l>Il Regno della morte.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <note place="foot">
                        <p>See his ode <title>
                              <foreign lang="ita">La Vita Rustica</foreign>
                           </title>.</p>
                     </note>
                  </quote>


He preserved his dignity and his poverty, the strength of his mind and the powers of his genius, to 
his seventieth year. He had been employed a few days in projecting some verses,

<note place="foot">
                     <p>It is the last copy of verses at page 44 of the second volume of Parini's works.</p>
                  </note>

 and one morning he dictated them to a friend. Having read them over, he said that he was satisfied 
with them, and begged his friend to get them printed. He then retired into his bedchamber, and, in 
half an hour afterwards, expired.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 n="Victor Alfieri">
               <head>VICTOR ALFIERI</head>
               <p>The life of this author has been written by himself. His tragedies have been criticised in 
every European language. There still remain some notices on his death, and some opinions on his 
other works, which may be new to the English reader.</p>
               <p>His connexion with the Countess of Albany is known to all the world, but no one is 
acquainted with the secret of that long intercourse. If they were married, Alfieri and the Countess 
took as much pains to conceal that fact, as is usually bestowed upon its publicity. Truth might have 
been spoken on the tomb of the poet, but even there we only find that Louisa, Countess of Albany, 
was his <emph>only love</emph> — «<foreign lang="lat">quam unice 
dilexit</foreign>». — A church, perhaps, was not the place to boast of such a passion; 
but after every consideration we may conclude, that the Abate Caluso, who wrote the epitaph, and 
received the last sighs of Alfieri, knew, and did not choose to tell, that his friend was never married 
to the widow of Charles Edward Stewart — «<foreign lang="lat">Tacendo 
clamat</foreign>» — his silence is eloquent.</p>
               <p>Alfieri, in the languor of a protracted agony, which the presence of Caluso assisted him 
to support, received the last visit of a priest, who came to confess him, with an affability for which 
he was not distinguished in the days of his health: but he said to him. “Have the kindness to 
look in to–morrow; I trust that death will wait for twenty–four hours”. The 
ecclesiastic returned the next day. Alfieri was sitting in his armchair, and said, “At present, I 
fancy, I have but a few minutes to spare”: and turning towards the Abbé, entreated him to 
bring the Countess to him. No sooner did he see her than he stretched forth his hand, saying, 
“clasp my hand, my dear friend, I die”.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <foreign lang="ita">Stringetemi, cara amica! la mano, io muoio</foreign>.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The religious opinions of Alfieri cannot be collected from his writings. His tragedies 
contain here and there a sarcasm against the Popes, and in his fugitive pieces may be found some 
epigrams against the monastic orders, but more particularly against the cardinals. Not a word, 
however, has ever escaped him against the Christian doctrines. It is only upon close inspection that 
we find, in a treatise on tyranny, that auricular confession, and the indissolubility of marriage, have 
contributed to the enslavement of Italy. His latter years were divided between a haughty irascibility 
and a deep melancholy, which afflicted him by turns, to a degree which rendered him scarcely 
accountable for his actions. Alfieri was then not unfrequently seen in the churches from vespers to 
sunset, sitting motionless, and apparently wrapt up in listening to the psalms of the monks, as they 
chanted them from behind the skreen of the choir. The way in which he died would, however, lead 
us to conjecture, that his meditations were not those of religion, and that he chose such a retreat in 
search of that solemn tranquillity which alone promised him a temporary repose from the relentless 
furies that preyed upon his heart:

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>Due fere Donne, anzi due Furie atroci</l>
                        <l>Tor' non mi posso — ahi misero! — dal fianco:</l>
                        <l>Ira e Malinconia.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>The complaint is from one of his own sonnets. He printed, during his own life, but he 
could never be persuaded to publish, some prose works, and amongst them the treatise before 
mentioned, <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Della Tirannide</foreign>
                  </title>, and another entitled, 
<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Il Principe e le Lettere</foreign>
                  </title>. They are in two small 
volumes. The first is a series of close arguments and severe remarks against monarchy. The second 
is written to prove, that poets, historians, and orators, can flourish only amongst a free people, and 
that tyranny is interested in the advancement only of the sciences, and more especially of medicine 
and jurisprudence. In both these works he has shewn that his address lay chiefly in the vigor of his 
attack; his preparations for defence were less skilfully disposed. Indeed, he seems to forget that he 
was liable to a retort. Thus it is that he may confirm the partisans of freedom, but he cannot hope to 
make a convert from the opposite opinion.</p>
               <p>The Italians look upon the prose of Alfieri as a model of style, particularly on political 
subjects. It is simple and energetic; his ideas are not abundant, but they are clear and precise, and 
connected according to the exactest rules of reasoning. It corresponds well with a metaphor 
employed for its description by one of his own countrymen — «<foreign lang="ita">I 
suoi pensieri in prosa sono non tanto vagamente dipinti quanto profondamente 
scolpiti</foreign>». His language is pure, and founded upon that of the oldest writers, but is 
free from the pedantry and the rust of antiquity. No man, therefore, was more qualified than Alfieri 
for the translation of Sallust. In fact, his version of that historian is reckoned a masterpiece.</p>
               <p>He tells us, in his preface, that this translation cost him many years of painful 
application. The whole of his works, indeed, bear the mark not only of laborious effort, but of 
retouching, repeated, and indefatigable. In the latter half of his own memoir, he had not time to be 
equally scrupulous, and that part is written in a style occasionally careless, and in a language not 
always remarkably correct.</p>
               <p>Alfieri, however, was not born to be the translator of Virgil. Could perseverance have 
obtained his object, his success was certain; for he sat down to his task with the same constancy 
with which he commenced pupil in the Greek language, after he had passed his fortieth year. He 
translated the whole of the <title>Aeneid</title> three times over; and yet the version published 
after his death, generally speaking, gives us but the contents of Virgil. The harmony, the glowing 
style, have no representative in the Italian epic. Alfieri was a perfect master of his language; his 
words were admirably adapted to the expression of sentiments which flowed warm from his heart; 
but which, being invariably animated by the same ardent temperature, absorbed his imagination, 
and left no room for those finer and varied graces which constitute the charm of poetry. Above all, 
he was extremely deficient in that branch of his art, in which his original is so consummate a master 
the elevation of a mean subject by the happy use of metaphor. He could not:

<quote rend="block">
                     <p>Throw about his manure with dignity.</p>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>This must appear the more surprising, since the Italian language is essentially 
metaphorical, and is by that very quality capable of being adapted to such an astonishing variety of 
styles, according to the invention, the taste and the imagination of each succeeding writer.</p>
               <p>Alfieri was not quite so unfortunate in his translation of Terence; but even there his 
simplicity is studied, not natural; and even in his happiest effort he betrays the secret that he had no 
genius for comic writing.</p>
               <p>The six comedies found amongst his posthumous works are compositions extravagant in 
the extreme. It is possible that some may admire them for their originality; but the sober reader is 
much more astonished at the perseverance with which the poet pursued such unprofitable labour. 
One only, entitled <title>The Divorce</title>, is a satire on Italian marriages. The others cannot 
possibly be adapted to the theatre. They are in the manner of Aristophanes, and all turn on political 
subjects. <title>The One</title> (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">L'Uno</foreign>
                  </title>) is a satire 
against monarchy; <title>The Few</title> (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">I Pochi</foreign>
                  </title>), 
and <title>The Too Many</title> (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">I Troppi</foreign>
                  </title>), attack 
the aristocratic and the popular government. A fourth is meant to teach that the One, the Few, and 
the Too Many, should be mixed together, and may then compose a system somewhat tolerable.</p>
               <p>The other comedy, called <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Il Finestrino</foreign>
                  </title>, is a 
satire partly against religious impostors; but more against the philosophers who invent no good 
religion, but yet would destroy all the old creeds, although (so thinks Alfieri) a bad one is better 
than none at all. One of the principal persons of the drama is Mahomet.</p>
               <p>The verse and the language of these comedies are still more extravagant than their 
original conception. In short, they are seldom read, and are regarded, except by a very few, as 
unworthy of the genius of Alfieri.</p>
               <p>His posthumous works contain also some translations from the ancient dramatic writers; 
the <title>Frogs</title>, the <title>Persians</title>, the <title>Philoctetes</title>, and the 
<title>Alceste</title>. To the latter he added another play of his own composition on the same 
subject, and formed exactly on the Greek model. He pleased himself with the innocent assertion that 
the new Alceste was a translation from a recovered manuscript, which might fairly be attributed to 
Euripides. It is the happiest of his latter efforts, and is only not fit for the modern stage. In the closet 
it affects us by the pathetic tenderness with which Alfieri either could not or would not embellish 
his other tragedies, constructed as they were expressly for the purpose of bracing the relaxed vigour 
of his effeminate fellow–countrymen.</p>
               <p>With this noble design he composed a sort of drama, altogether new, which he called a 
<emph>melo–tragedy</emph>. His object here was to unite the music which the Italians 
look upon as a constituent part of the theatre, with the grandeur and the pathos of tragedy. He chose 
the <title>Death of Abel</title> for his subject, and he adopted that repeated change of scene which 
his countrymen would have regarded as a monstruous innovation, although it is one of the 
characteristics of their opera.</p>
               <p>Angels and demons are part of the persons of the drama, and are the singers of the play. 
The poetry of their songs is composed in different metres. Adam, Eve, and their two sons also 
discourse in verse, but in blank verse, and without music. This composition has some brilliant 
passages; but is, on the whole, devoid of interest. As an experiment it would perhaps be 
unproducible on the Italian stage, where the opera has formally excluded all display of ideas or 
sentiments, and almost of words, and is solely devoted to the musician and the ballet master.</p>
               <p>The satires of Alfieri will cherish the melancholy of every unwilling member of human 
society. They are directed against every condition. Kings and nobles, rich and poor, priests and 
philosophers, physicians, lawyers, merchants, none are exempt; all of them, in fact, are made the 
subject, and furnish the title of a separate censure. The satirist is free from personality, and even all 
individual allusion; he strives no farther than to convince his reader, that whatever may be his place 
or pursuit, he runs a great risk of being unhappy, and wicked, and contemptible. Of the women 
alone he says nothing good, nothing bad. His satire on them is contained in a very few verses, and 
resolves itself into the maxim, that the stronger is responsible for all the vices of the weaker 
sex.</p>
               <p>There are, however, certain of his satires which are recommendable from their wit, and 
from their acquaintance with human nature. We may select the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Cavaliere Servente Veterano</foreign>
                  </title> — <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">I 
Pedanti</foreign>
                  </title>, — <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">L'Educazione</foreign>
                  </title> 
— and <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Il Duello</foreign>
                  </title>. In the latter he steps forward, 
like another Johnson, in defence of a practice necessary for the protection of the man of honour, 
from the intrigues, and calumnies, and assaults of the coward and the bully. Another of the same 
class, <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">I Viaggi</foreign>
                  </title>, is devoted to the censure of 
<emph>himself</emph>, and of the nobility, and of those who travel for want of occupation.</p>
               <p>This satire is in <foreign lang="ita">terza rima</foreign>, and is the best specimen of 
that harshness of versification which the warmest admirers of Alfieri allow to be indefensible. He 
was seduced into this error by a wish to shun the opposite defect which characterised the poets of 
the preceding generation. The plant had been so warped and drawn to the earth on one side by 
Metastasio, that Alfieri thought he could never recover its position without bending it backwards as 
much on the other. The tree is not yet upright. Yet his strange words, and his capricious innovations 
in phraseology, profusely as they are spread over his satires and his comedies, will be forgotten or 
forgiven, and the force and purity of his diction will ever recommend the prose of Alfieri to the 
study of his countrymen. It is worthy of remark, that the Paris edition of his tragedies, which he 
printed at the press of Didot, is <emph>partially</emph> exempt from that harshness of 
versification observable in all his former editions.</p>
               <p>The errors of a man of genius are not unfrequently of service to the cause of literature. 
Mr. Bellotto, in his translation of Sophocles, chose Alfieri for his model, as far as regarded his 
method and general style; but he softened the diction, he harmonised the numbers of his prototype, 
and thus succeeded in producing a work which had been long expected, and often essayed in 
vain.</p>
               <p>Alfieri, a little after the year 1790, and before his return to Italy, printed at Kell some 
specimens of lyrical poetry in two volumes. The first contains an ode on the taking of the Bastille, 
ad a poem, comprising five odes on the emancipation of America. The one addressed to 
Washington is the best; but bespeaks, after all, only the originality of the poet. It no less shews that 
he had misdirected his genius; for his ode is in the same harsh, dry style which spoils his translation 
of Virgil. The eulogist of America could not be expected to spare the English; but his dislike was 
confined to the minister of the day — the nation which he has praised so often in his memoirs 
he did not degrade in his poetry. Indeed his ode on the Bastille contains an appendix with which we 
cannot but be content. This is a short apologue, in which the English are the <emph>bees</emph>, 
the French the <emph>flies</emph>, of the fable.</p>
               <p>The other volume of his lyrics consists in great part of amatory sonnets, almost all 
addressed to the same person. The delicacy of his sentiments, the fire of his passion, and the novelty 
of his turn of thought, redeem the want of elegance and harmony, which must be regretted in the 
whole perfor mance, and may, perhaps, be discovered in the following specimens.</p>
               <p>The first was written in the Album, at Petrarch's house, at Arquà.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>O Cameretta, che già in te chiudesti</l>
                           <l>Quel Grande alla cui fama è angusto il mondo,</l>
                           <l>Quel gentile d'amor mastro profondo</l>
                           <l>Per cui Laura ebbe in terra onor celesti!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>O di pensier soavemente mesti</l>
                           <l>Solitario ricovero giocondo!</l>
                           <l>Di che lagrime amare il petto inondo</l>
                           <l>In veder che ora innonorato resti!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Prezioso diaspro, agata, ed oro</l>
                           <l>Foran debito fregio e appena degno</l>
                           <l>Di rivestir sì nobile tesoro.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Ma no; tomba fregiar d'uom ch'ebbe regno</l>
                           <l>Vuolsi, e por gemme ove disdice alloro:</l>
                           <l>Qui basta il nome di quel Divo Ingegno.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>The other is on the tomb of Dante.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>O gran padre Allighier, se dal ciel miri</l>
                           <l>Me non indegno tuo discepol starmi,</l>
                           <l>Dal cor traendo profondi sospiri,</l>
                           <l>Prostrato innanzi a tuoi funerei marmi;</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Piacciati, deh! propizio a' bei desiri,</l>
                           <l>D'un raggio di tua mente illuminarmi:</l>
                           <l>Uom che a perenne e prima gloria aspiri</l>
                           <l>Contro invidia e viltà dee stringer l'armi?</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Figlio, i' le strinsi, e ben men duol, che diedi</l>
                           <l>Nome in tal guisa a gente tanto bassa</l>
                           <l>Da non pur calpestarsi co' miei piedi</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Se in me fidi, tuo sguardo non abbassa;</l>
                           <l>Va, tuona, vinci, e niun di costor vedi,</l>
                           <l>Non che parlarne; ma sovr'essi passa.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>His work, called the <title>Misogallo</title>, of which he speaks with so much 
complacency in his own memoirs, was not printed until the year 1814, ten years after his death, and 
just as the French evacuated Italy. One might have thought the period well chosen; and yet the 
editors were obliged to leave gaps in certain passages, particularly where he told truth of the Popes. 
The <title>Misogallo</title> is a mixture of prose and of epigrams. These latter would be a 
wretched effort, even in a middling author — they betray the rage of impotent sarcasm. As 
for the book itself, it is also seasoned more with spite than wit a remark that holds good of some 
other epigrams published during the life–time of the author. Mr. Forsyth has cited two that 
are just in point.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <title>Remarks, etc., on Italy</title>, p. 62, edit. 2d.</bibl>
                     </p>
                  </note>

 — The prose of the <title>Misogallo</title> contains two pieces worthy of perusal: one is 
the defence which Alfieri would have put into the mouth of Louis XVI in presence of the 
Convention. The other is the apology of the author himself, for his detestation of the French 
revolution, as having ruined the cause of liberty; that cause to which Alfieri had dedicated all his 
talents, and the better portion of his fortune and his life.</p>
               <p>Amongst the ancient and modern poets of Italy, no one has furnished so many pictures 
and busts as Alfleri. Fabre, who excels in portraits, and was his friend, has taken four likenesses in 
oil; all of them much esteemed, and, it should seem, justly. There is also a profile, having for 
inscription the sonnet in which he describes both his person and his character.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>Sublime specchio di veraci detti</l>
                           <l>Mostrami in corpo e in anima qual sono.</l>
                           <l>Capelli or radi in fronte, e rossi pretti;</l>
                           <l>Lunga statura e capo a terra prono.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Sottil persona su due stinchi schietti;</l>
                           <l>Bianca pelle, occhio azzurro, aspetto buono,</l>
                           <l>Giusto naso, bel labbro, e denti eletti,</l>
                           <l>Pallido in viso più che un Re sul trono. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Or duro acerbo, ora pieghevol mite,</l>
                           <l>Irato sempre e non maligno mai,</l>
                           <l>La mente e il cor meco in perpetua lite;</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Per lo più mesto, e talor lieto assai,</l>
                           <l>Or stimandomi Achille, ed or Tersite.</l>
                           <l>Uom, sei tu grande, o vil? Mori e il saprai.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Compare the <title>Orestes</title>, the <title>Virginia</title>, the 
<title>Myrrha</title>, the <title>Saul</title>, and some other of his tragic masterpieces, with his 
comedies and his <title>Misogallo</title>, and we shall almost think it was the voice of conscience 
that told him he was sometimes the Achilles, sometimes the Thersites of authors.</p>
               <p>His example has confirmed the opinion, that genius is the distinctive merit of poets. 
Alfieri, whose education was very much neglected, and whose youth was sunk in the loosest 
dissipation (<foreign lang="ita">dissipatissima</foreign>),

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See his letter to Mr. Calsabigi, printed in the preface to his tragedies.</p>
                  </note>

 rose, in a few years, to the highest literary distinction, and was ranked amongst the great writers of 
his country. His perseverance and his ardour were, it is true, such as are rarely seen. Yet the same 
perseverance, the same ardour, were employed in the production of his latter writings: his learning 
was greater, his knowledge of the world more extensive, and his understanding more enlightened by 
the progress of years, and by that revolution of which he was an eye–witness, and which 
sharpened even very inferior intellects. Neither was he, at any period of his life, too advanced in age 
for mental exertion, for he was not fifty–three when he died. It is incontestable, however, 
that the suppression of the greater part of his posthumous publications would have been of infinite 
service to his fame. Perhaps he was born to shine in tragedy, and in tragedy alone; and perhaps the 
prodigious exertions of his first efforts exhausted his vigour and depressed his spirit, and 
condemned his latter years to languor and to regret. He might exclaim, with the ancient,

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="lat">
                        <l>Non sum qualis eram: periit pars maxima nostri</l>
                        <l>Hoc quoque, quod superest languor et horror habent.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>

It is affirmed by those who knew him, that between his fits of melancholy, Alfieri conversed with 
warmth, but always with a certain tincture of bitterness; and it is distressing to be told that he 
studiously avoided all those whom he had not known for several years. He carried his aversion to 
new intimacies to such a length, that a letter addressed by any other than a well–known 
hand, and under any but the seal of a friend, was thrown into the fire unopened. It need hardly be 
added, that he had but two or three correspondents. The public journals and periodical papers he 
never once looked into for many of his latter years. Thus he had no means of becoming acquainted 
with his own share of that glory which had been the principal object of his life. Nor did he believe 
himself arrived at the station which he actually occupied in the eyes of his countrymen, and of all 
Europe. His melancholy divested the vanities of life of all their charms, and he refused to cherish 
the only illusion that could console his existence.</p>
               <p>Count Alexander Pepoli, who inherited the wealth and the name of that powerful family, 
which, during the middle ages, made themselves masters of Bologna, and alarmed the princes of 
Italy, was the cotemporary, and, it may be said, the rival of Alfieri. He wrote tragedies, he wrote 
comedies: both the one and the other were applauded on the stage; both the one and the other now 
slumber in the libraries. He aspired to the invention of a new drama, which he thought 
Shakesperian, and which he called <title>Fisedia</title> — a compliment to our poet, and a 
tacit reproof to all the other writers for the stage, from Aeschilus downwards. His 
<title>Representation of Nature</title> pleased both the people and the actors, but never came to a 
second edition. Like Alfieri, he also was passionately fond of horses, and he was bolder than our 
poet, for he drove a Roman car, a <emph>quadriga</emph>, at full gallop over the ascents and 
descents of the Apennines. He built a theatre for the representation of his own tragedies; he founded 
the magnificent printing press at Venice, from which, under the name of the <hi rend="italic">Tipografia Pepoliana</hi>, have issued many works, and particularly several editions 
of the Italian historians. His daily occupations were divided, with a scrupulosity which they hardly 
merited, between his studies, his horses, and his table. His guests consisted of men of letters, of 
buffoons, of people of fashion, and of parasites. His nights were devoted to the pursuits of gallantry, 
in which he was sufficiently successful; for he was handsome and he was rich. His amours were 
occasionally postponed for his billiards, at which he lost large sums of money, in the pursuit of an 
excellence which he would fain have attained at all games of skill. His great ambition was to be the 
first <emph>runner</emph> in Italy, and he died in 1796, before he was forty, of a pulmonary 
complaint, which he had caught in a foot–race with a lacquey. He merits a place in this 
memoir, not for the brilliancy of his compositions, but for the shade of relief which they furnish to 
the similar and successful efforts of Alfieri.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 n="Hippolitus Pindemonte">
               <head>HIPPOLITUS PINDEMONTE</head>
               <p>The Marquis John Pindemonte, eldest brother of him who will be here treated of, is a 
proof of the preliminary observation, that a man of literature may be very popular in Italy, and yet 
be without that settled reputation which owes its origin to the suffrages of the learned class of 
readers. This nobleman, in conjunction with Pepoli, kept for some time possession of the stage. The 
tragedies of John Pindemonte, which are now almost forgotten, brought crowds to the theatre at the 
time that Alfieri was listened to with* impatience. Hippolitus Pindemonte has perhaps less 
imagination than his brother, but he was naturally andowed with a certain delicacy of taste, the 
development of which, by an education truly classical, has secured for him the highest distinctions 
of literature. It is, however, a fact which any one will verify by a careful enquiry, that the poetry of 
Hippolitus Pindemonte is not relished by the generality of readers, who are nevertheless obliged to 
repeat his praises, having been taught that lesson by the learned distributors of literary fame, and by 
those who are by tacit consent allowed to possess the most cultivated taste. The same obedient 
crowd throng the play–houses, to see the tragedies of his elder brother, but the fear of the 
same censors prevents them from praising the composition of their favourite dramas.</p>
               <p>Hippolitus has also written a tragedy on the death of Arminius, the German hero, whose 
conspiracy against the liberties of his country was punished with death, from the hand of his own 
relations. The style of this piece is much applauded; the plan of it is on the model of Shakespeare, 
without, however, a total abandonment of those ancient rules which the Italians will allow no writer 
to violate with impunity. He has introduced chorusses sung by young warriors and maidens, and has 
thus combined, with some success, the English, the Greek, and the Italian drama — as to the 
French plan, the example and the system of Alfieri have created a persuasion that it is irreconcilable 
with the Italian theatre. Whether the <hi rend="italic">Arminius</hi> has stood the great test, does 
not appear in the published play. Perhaps it has been never acted, and perhaps it may be as little 
qualified for any stage as the <title>Caractacus</title> and the <title>Elfrida</title> would be for 
our own. The works of Pindemonte which are most esteemed, are some lyrical poems, and 
particularly his epistles in verse. These last contain a happy assemblage of qualities not easily 
combined. The Italians behold in them the amenity of Horace, the tenderness of Petrarch, and a 
certain gravity of ideas and sentiments, for which, perhaps, he is indebted to his acquaintance with 
English poetry. A similar transfusion of our style was before attempted by Mazza. The epistles are 
in blank verse, the favourite metre of the present day.</p>
               <p>This writer has not only borrowed the English style, but many individual passages of our 
poets, more particularly of Milton and of Gray. The plagiaries, if they may be so called, are inserted 
with considerable taste and effect. A great part of his youth was spent in travelling, and he lived 
long enough in England to become familiar with our literature. His <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Campestri</foreign>
                  </title> contain some copies of verses addressed to Englishmen. He 
speaks with enthusiastic admiration of their country; and it may be pleasing to see a fine description 
which he gives of a park, one of the characteristic beauties of England.</p>
               <p>Speaking of the practice of raising tombs in gardens, he continues,

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>Così eletta dimora e sì pietosa</l>
                        <l>L'Anglo talvolta, che profondi e forti</l>
                        <l>Non meno che i pensier, vanta gli affetti,</l>
                        <l>Alle più amate ceneri destina</l>
                        <l>Nelle sue tanto celebrate ville,</l>
                        <l>Ove per gli occhi in seno, e per gli orecchi</l>
                        <l>Tanta m'entrava, e sì innocente ebbrezza.</l>
                        <l>Oh chi mi leva in alto, e chi mi porta</l>
                        <l>Tra quegli ameni, dilettosi, immensi</l>
                        <l>Boscherecci teatri! Oh chi mi posa</l>
                        <l>Su que' verdi tappeti, entro que' foschi</l>
                        <l>Solitari ricoveri, nel grembo</l>
                        <l>Di quelle valli, ed a que' colli in vetta!</l>
                        <l>Non recise colà bellica scure</l>
                        <l>Le gioconde ombre; i consueti asili</l>
                        <l>Là non cercaro invan gli ospiti augelli:</l>
                        <l>Nè Primavera s'ingannò, veggendo</l>
                        <l>Sparito dalla terra il noto bosco,</l>
                        <l>Che a rivestir venia delle sue frondi.</l>
                        <l>Sol nella man del giardinier solerte</l>
                        <l>Mandò lampi colà l'acuto ferro,</l>
                        <l>Che rase il prato ed agguagliollo; e i rami</l>
                        <l>Che tra lo sguardo, e le lontane scene</l>
                        <l>Si ardivano frappor, dotto corresse.</l>
                        <l>Prospetti vaghi, inaspettati incontri,</l>
                        <l>Bei sentieri, antri freschi, opachi seggi,</l>
                        <l>Lente acque e mute all'erba e ai fiori in mezzo,</l>
                        <l>Precipitanti d'alto acque tonanti,</l>
                        <l>Dirupi di sublime orror dipinti,</l>
                        <l>Campo e giardin, lusso erudito e agreste</l>
                        <l>Semplicità — Quinci ondeggiar la messe,</l>
                        <l>Pender le capre da un'aerea balza,</l>
                        <l>La valle mugolar, belare il colle:</l>
                        <l>Quinci marmoreo sovra l'onde un ponte</l>
                        <l>Curvarsi, e un tempio biancheggiar tra il verde;</l>
                        <l>Straniere piante frondeggiar, che d'ombre</l>
                        <l>Spargono Americane il suol Brittanno,</l>
                        <l>E su ramo, che avea per altri augelli</l>
                        <l>Natura ordito, augei cantar d'Europa.</l>
                        <l>Mentre superbo delle arboree corna</l>
                        <l>Va per la selva il cervo, e spesso il capo</l>
                        <l>Volge, e ti guarda; e in mezzo all'onda il cigno</l>
                        <l>Del piè fa remo, il collo inarca, e fende</l>
                        <l>L'argenteo lago. Così bel soggiorno</l>
                        <l>Sentono i bruti stessi, e delle selve</l>
                        <l>Scuoton con istupor la cima i venti.</l>
                        <l>Deh perchè non poss'io tranquilli passi</l>
                        <l>Muovere ancor per quelle vie, celarmi</l>
                        <l>Sotto l'intreccio ancor di que' frondosi</l>
                        <l>Rami ospitali, e udir da lunge appena</l>
                        <l>Mugghiar del Mondo la tempesta, urtarsi</l>
                        <l>L'un contro l'altro popolo, corone</l>
                        <l>Spezzarsi, e scettri? oh quanta strage! oh quanto</l>
                        <l>Scavar di fosse, e traboccar di corpi</l>
                        <l>E ai condottier trafitti alzar di tombe!</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>It was, however, neither our parks nor our learned leisure that awakened such lively 
feelings, and called forth such ardent vows for his return to England. Our women must share the 
merit of the inspiration; for Pindemonte has given the initial of some nymph who had the good 
fortune to be the object of his first real, as well as his first poetic, passion. It may, perhaps be 
flattering to this person, if she is still in existence, to know that the poet's verses to Miss H.** are 
esteemed by the Italians as some of his best, and not unworthy of comparison with those which 
have immortalized the charms of Laura. They are in the form of a canzone, in the manner of 
Petrarch, and the two first stanzas are as follows:

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>O Giovenetta, che la dubbia via</l>
                           <l>Di nostra vita, pellegrina allegra,</l>
                           <l>Con piè non sospettoso imprimi ed orni;</l>
                           <l>Sempre così propizio il ciel ti sia!</l>
                           <l>Nè adombri mai*nube improvvisa e negra</l>
                           <l>L'innocente seren de' tuoi bei giorni.</l>
                           <l>Non che il Mondo ritorni</l>
                           <l>A te quanto gli dai tu di dolcezza,</l>
                           <l>Ch'egli stesso ben sa non poter tanto.</l>
                           <l>Valle è questa di pianto</l>
                           <l>E gran danno qui spesso è gran bellezza,</l>
                           <l>Qui dove perde agevolmente fama</l>
                           <l>Qual più vaga si chiama:</l>
                           <l>Come andrà l'alma mia gioiosa e paga</l>
                           <l>Se impunemente esser potrai sì vaga!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Il men di che può donna esser cortese</l>
                           <l>Ver chi l'ha di sè stesso assai più cara</l>
                           <l>Da te, vergine pura, io non vorrei:</l>
                           <l>Veder in te quella che pria m'accese</l>
                           <l>Bramo, e sol temo che men grande e cara</l>
                           <l>Ciò ti faccia parere agli occhi miei.</l>
                           <l>Nè volontier torrei</l>
                           <l>Di spargerti nel sen foco amoroso,</l>
                           <l>Chè quanto è a me più noto il fiero ardore</l>
                           <l>Delitto far maggiore</l>
                           <l>Mi parrìa se turbassi il tuo riposo.</l>
                           <l>Maestro io primo ti sarò d'affanno?</l>
                           <l>O per me impareranno</l>
                           <l>Nuovi affanni i tuoi giorni, ed interrotti</l>
                           <l>Sonni per me le tue tranquille notti?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>The whole of the remainder of this canzone gives a flattering picture of the beauty, of 
the modesty, and of the unaffected graces, of the English young women of that day; and the 
delicacy of such a passion redounds not less to the credit of the poet than of the lady, who must 
either have been naturally exempt from the ambition of coquetry, or must have taken great pains to 
conceal it.</p>
               <p>The same author has published a romance in prose, which, as far as regards the apparent 
purpose of the work, reminds us of <title>Rasselas</title>. But Pindemonte's Abarite has failed to 
procure him the reputation of a distinguished prose writer. For purity, for erudition, for polish, it is 
not inferior to his verses, but it wants the charm of those pleasing compositions. His prefaces, his 
literary correspondence, and his little biographies, have never been seriously criticised, and are 
perhaps not worth it.</p>
               <p>He has been assailed, like all other writers, by repeated criticism; but those criticisms 
have made little noise, and, however they may have really affected him, have not disturbed his 
apparent tranquillity. The baseness of flattery, the bitterness of censure, will not be found in the 
personal allusions of Pindemonte. His writings, like his conversation, are those of an accomplished 
gentleman.</p>
               <p>He has always in theory been devoted to the cause of liberty; but at the coming of the 
French he laid down for his conduct one inviolable maxim — <hi rend="italic">Hide thy 
life; notwithstanding that his eldest brother and many of his friends have been actively engaged 
with different political parties</hi>.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See his own declaration in the preface to his <title>Epistles</title>, published at Verona, in the 
year 1805.</p>
                  </note>

 He has confined himself to some poetical complaints of the ravages and degradation which the 
sword of the stranger has for so many ages inflicted on his unhappy country.</p>
               <p>From the beginning of the Revolution he has passed his time between Venice and 
Verona, his native town, and chiefly employed upon a translation of the <title>Odyssey</title>. 
There are many Italian translations of Homer, but not one has yet obtained that complete success 
which the voice of the nation, and the sanction of the learned world, alone can bestow. Pindemonte 
has, it is probable, judiciously selected this poem in preference to the <title>Iliad</title>, which 
would have required more imagination and more energy than are the characteristics of his style. The 
two first books were published some time ago, and Italy was as impatient as such a prospect can 
make her, for the remainder of the performance. The whole translation appeared at the close of the 
last year, but what was the effect or judgment resulting from it, cannot, of course, yet be known. 
The poet's health has of late years been much on the decline, and obliged him to proceed leisurely 
with his occupation. He has passed his sixtieth year, and age and infirmity have made him devout. 
His spiritual exercises occupy a considerable portion of his time, and plunge him into that 
consuming solitude which a more rational religion would teach him to exchange for the active 
duties and social amusements of life.</p>
               <p>This author is not ranked amongst the men of surpassing genius which Italy has 
produced, and, perhaps, ought not to be: but the assiduity of his studies; the consummate skill with 
which he has known where to employ, and how to develope his superior abilities; the sleepless care 
with which he has watched over the rise, and preserved the integrity of his fame; the decorum both 
of his life and writings; have secured for him the undisputed possession of the first place in the 
intermediate class, between the great masters of the art, and those who write to captivate the 
multitude. The English reader a will understand this place by recurring to the author of the 
<title>Pleasures of Memory</title>, and perhaps that gentleman may accept as much of the 
comparison as the just ambition of a poet will allow him to think consistent with the pretension to 
unqualified excellence. This intermediate class, although, as in the present instance, it occasionally 
produces an author, is composed for the most part of those who may be called rather learned readers 
than learned writers. Such a class has sprung up partially amongst ourselves, but with this 
difference, that our critics, although they do not condescend to advance in the regular uniform of 
writers, still appear in print, and that not unfrequently; whereas in Italy they seldom take up the pen, 
and acquire by that discretion a dignity which gives more weight to their oral judgment. These 
persons have received what we call a <emph>regular</emph> education, are familiar with, and 
formed upon, the classical writers, both ancient and modern; and, by an habitual application of the 
prescribed rules to every popular performance, are the selfinstituted, but undisputed, arbiters of 
taste. There are five or six of these in every considerable town; and one set, some of whom are 
perhaps authors, presides over all the provincial critics: not even the writers of a respectable class 
dare to pronounce their opinion without a previous inquiry at the national oracle. A great compiler, 
Tiraboschi for instance, would not have ventured to speak of a contemporary until he knew what 
decision had been pronounced by Bettinelli or Roberti.</p>
               <p>These persons establish, by the union of their suffrages, a reputation which is sure not to 
be ephemeral. But there is yet another class of readers, whom it is prudent to gain before an author 
can promise himself:

<quote rend="block">
                     <p>The life to come in every poet's creed.</p>
                  </quote>

These are the men of cultivated minds, <emph>the men of the world</emph>; a vague phrase, but 
which will be understood, although it cannot be precisely defined. With the combined verdict of the 
former as the guardians of the language, and of the latter as the organ of the feelings of his 
countrymen, the Italian author may be secure that the common readers will follow in a crowd, and, 
like the Romans to Augustus, raise frequent altars to his living merit.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 n="Vincent Monti">
               <head>VINCENT MONTI</head>
               <p>This poet has always enjoyed, and still enjoys a sort of pre–eminence, of which, 
notwithstanding all the world seems agreed upon his claims, he has often been very nearly deprived. 
His subjects have, for the most part, been popular and occasional. He has laid hold of the most 
interesting events of the moment: he has sustained the preponderating opinions, and he has 
invariably advocated the interests of the succeeding reigning powers. With such advantages, it is not 
strange that he should have found many willing and eager readers; nor is it more strange that all the 
various governments, one after the other, should have continued to rank him amongst their 
partisans. It may excite somewhat more surprise to remark the air not only of enthusiasm, but of 
sincerity, with which he has delivered his contradictory panegyrics, and to admire the address, with 
which he appears rather repentant than changeful, and converts the dictates of interest into a case of 
conscience. By turns flattering and irritating every party, he has not only roused the passions of his 
cotemporaries, but has given them a direction towards himself. His real merit, and the advantage 
derived from his powerful pen by the triumphant faction, have protected him from neglect; and that 
prostitution of talents which would have rendered him either odious or ridiculous in England, has 
been less contemptible in a country where there is more indifference, and less intelligence 
employed, in the view of political transactions.</p>
               <p>For three centuries not a single Italian poet had raised his voice against the will or the 
wish of the powerful. Alfieri and Parini had made the first noble exception to this submission, and it 
was more easy to admire than imitate so rare an example. Monti, independent of the difference of 
natural disposition, was not born to the wealth of Alfieri, nor was he thrown into the same juncture 
of circumstances that had favoured the Milanese poet; neither had he been formed by that 
independent education which both the one and the other had enjoyed. In a word, Monti was brought 
up at the court of Rome.</p>
               <p>The charm of Monti's poetry consists in a pleasing union of the soft and the strong. His 
ideas are strikingly apparent, his sentiments are full of fire, his verses are truly melodious, and his 
imagery is highly embellished, and has received the last finishing and decoration of taste. He has, 
indeed, touched nothing that he has not adorned. If his polish is confined to the surface, not only 
himself but his readers are content without enquiring into the depth of his capacity.</p>
               <p>Monti owed the first diffusion of his reputation to his <title>Aristodemus</title>, a 
tragedy which, to use the language of the stage, is a stock play in constant acting, notwithstanding 
the passion and interest are totally confined to the chief character. The dialogue was found to have 
more warmth, and colouring, and energy, than that of Metastasio, who was then in possession of the 
stage; and the audience were not terrified even by the shadow of that harshness, and violence, and 
obscurity, which characterised the tragedies of Alfieri, who was just emerging into notice, and 
regarded as a wild irregular genius, scarcely within the pale of literary civilization. Monti then was 
the tragic writer of Italy, and was confidently hailed as the successful candidate for an eminence as 
yet never occupied.</p>
               <p>He afterwards published two other tragedies: <title>Galeotto Manfredi</title>, which is 
not only far below his <title>Aristodemus</title>, but beneath the talents of the author, and 
<title>Caius Gracchus</title>. Some fine passages constitute the sole merit of the last tragedy, into 
which he has introduced some scenes that the Italians are pleased to call <emph>by far too 
natural</emph> — <foreign lang="ita">assai troppo naturali</foreign>. These scenes were 
expressly imitated from Shakespeare, and succeeded at first — nobody, however, dared to 
applaud them in the subsequent representations. The critical spectators near the orchestra, and the 
closet–judges, having once condemned that which appears to militate against classical 
authority, their sentence is irrevocable: — the people have not a voice; or, if they dare to 
speak, are not heard. The defects of Monti's tragedies are reducible to the insignificance of his 
characters, to the irregularity of his plot, and to a style sometimes too lyrical, sometimes too tame. 
These were discovered by the audience, and perhaps by the poet, for he laid no further claim to the 
throne of Melpomene.</p>
               <p>The work of his which has made the most noise is the «<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Cantica in morte di Ugo Basville</foreign>
                  </title>», published in Rome in 1793, 
when the author was about thirty–five years of age. This poem is even now considered 
superior to the subsequent productions of this fruitful writer, who has never laid aside, and still 
holds the pen. An edition of it has been published in London by Mr. Matthias, with the title 
<title>
                     <foreign lang="fra">La Revoluzione Francese</foreign>
                  </title>, and another appeared at 
Paris with another name, <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Le Dante Ingentilito</foreign>
                  </title>. It 
would be difficult to guess at the motives for these changes, with which it is probable the poet was 
not made acquainted; and it would be more difficult still to justify the usurpation of rights which 
appear to belong only to the author.</p>
               <p>Hugh Basville was a man of letters, employed on a mission at Rome by the National 
Convention. His object was, probably, to sow the seeds of democracy, and to watch the con duct of 
the papal government in the approaching revolution. Others there are, however, who affirm that he 
was only on his return from the court of Naples, where he had been secretary of the French 
Legation, and that he was charged with no commission. This is asserted in one of the numbers of 
the <title>
                     <foreign lang="fra">Gazette des Maires</foreign>
                  </title>, published at Paris by Captain 
de Basville, who has undertaken to justify his father's memory. The Roman populace, however, 
looked upon him as a Jacobin spy, murdered him, and pillaged his house. The capital of the world 
indulged in a savage triumph at this exploit, and the ministers of the pope, by their inactivity to 
punish, were suspected of participating in the crime. But Pius VI was generous enough to save the 
wife and child of Basville from the rage of the multitude. On this occasion Monti wrote his 
poem.</p>
               <p>According to the anecdotes contained in some pamphlets, and, amongst others, in one 
called <title>
                     <foreign lang="fra">Esame su le accuse contro V. Monti</foreign>
                  </title>, published 
at Milan in 1798, a Monti was the friend of Basville; and it is certain, that in the greater part of his 
subsequent writings he shewed himself a friend of the revolution. His poem justified the court of 
Rome, perpetuated the name of his friend, and saved himself from the perils of his late intimacy 
with a Jacobin. The plan of this work is very simple. Basville repents and dies, and is pardoned by 
the Almighty. An angel conducts his spirit across those kingdoms of the earth which had been 
desolated by the wars and crimes of the French revolution. They arrive at Paris at the moment that 
Louis XVI is mounting the scaffold. The spirit of the king, ascending to*heaven, meets the shade of 
Basville, and the angel makes them known to each other. The king questions him, and Basville 
narrates the cause and the manner of his death.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>La fronte sollevò, rizzossi in piedi</l>
                           <l>L'addolorato spirto; e le pupille</l>
                           <l>Tergendo, a dire incominciò: Tu vedi,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Signor, nel tuo cospetto Ugo Basville</l>
                           <l>Dalla Francese Libertà mandato</l>
                           <l>Sul Tebro a suscitar l'empie scintille,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Stolto! che volli con l'immobil fato</l>
                           <l>Cozzar della gran Roma, onde ne porto</l>
                           <l>Rotta la tempia e il fianco insanguinato.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Chè di Giuda il Leon non anco è morto</l>
                           <l>Ma vive e rugge; e il pelo arruffa e gli occhi</l>
                           <l>Terror d'Egitto, e d'Israel conforto:</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>E se monta in furor, l'aste, e gli stocchi</l>
                           <l>Sa spezzar de' nemici; e par che gride</l>
                           <l>«<hi rend="italic">Son lo sdegno di Dio: nessun mi tocchi</hi>»</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Here Basville confesses the crime which brought him to his end, and lauds the 
vengeance of Rome and of the Lion of Judah. But the above quotation suggests another remark, 
which will be found more or less true of all Monti's works; namely, that he has not scrupled to 
insert the ideas, and the turns of expression of former poets in his best verses. The beginning of this 
canto reminds us of that of Dante's Ugolino.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>La bocca sollevò dal fero pasto</l>
                           <l>Quel peccator —</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Poi cominciò: Tu vuoi —</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>

and the last verse is evidently from Petrarch,

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>Son del Cesare mio: nessun mi tocchi.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Monti indeed regards it as a portion of his art, and a proof of his talents, successfully to 
employ the fine thoughts, and the phrases of the great writers. No modern author has, perhaps, so 
freely imitated others as Monti; but no modern author has so frankly confessed his obligations, and 
his gratitude. His notes abound with the passages from which he has borrowed, and he has the 
praise of sometimes improving upon his originals, and of always introducing them in proper time 
and place. So far from accusing him of plagiary, we are rather agreeably surprised by the new 
aspect which he gives to beauties already familiar to every reader.</p>
               <p>The fourth canto of the poem prepares us for the war of the coalesced potentates to 
revenge the death of Louis XVI. The soul of Basville is condemned by the poet to expiate his crime, 
by beholding the horrors of the Revolution, and by wandering without the precincts od Paradise 
until France shall have received the punishment of her regicide:

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Finchè non sia di Francia ulto il delitto.</foreign>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>

According to this plan, Monti had opened an unbounded field for his exertions, and by merely 
following the progress of events, he would have avoided those difficulties, with which the necessity 
of inventing and arranging a series of fictions, has embarrassed the greater part of all poetical 
writers. He would only have had to select the most remarkable traits in the astonishing history of 
our times, and to divide them, ac cording to the rules of his art and the power of his genius, into 
pictures which should command the delight and wonder of posterity. The difficulty of handling a 
cotemporary topic, was not too great for the capacity of Monti, and had he continued his 
<title>Basville</title> to the victory of Waterloo, he might have occupied, next to Dante, that place 
which Virgil possesses in the vicinity of Homer.</p>
               <p>The voyage of the angel with the shade of Basville is taken from that of Dante with the 
spirit of Virgil. The <foreign lang="ita">terze rime</foreign>, a metre perfected by the father of 
Italian poetry, was, in the true sense of the word, <emph>ennobled</emph> (<foreign lang="ita">ingentilito</foreign>) by Monti. It is true that he has not the same harmonious variety, 
nor the same boldness of expression, nor the same loftiness of thought as are found in his model. 
But he is more equal, more clear, more finished in every part: his images have not only the stable 
grandeur, but even the glossy whiteness of Parian sculpture; and although they succeed each other 
with aston ishing rapidity, and force, and boldness, preserve an elegance peculiar to themselves, 
more especially in the terze rime, which no one has ever employed with the same success. It is 
probable that Monti will never be surpassed in this metre: but in the heroic stanza he could not 
come into the field against Ariosto and Tasso; and in blank verse, Cesarotti, Parini, and Foscolo 
have been more adventurous and more successful.</p>
               <p>Monti had scarcely published the fourth canto of his poem (which, such as he left it, 
does not amount to 1500 lines), when the French conquered Lombardy. Perhaps it was fear, perhaps 
it was interest, or more likely still inclination, that seduced him from Rome, and settled him in the 
capital of the new Cisalpine republic. On this occasion he quitted the service of the Duke of 
Braschi, the nephew of Pius VI. Prelates, cardinals, and even Popes, had begun by being secretaries 
like himself, but Monti was a married man — he was a poet, and he was not besides in the 
good graces of his Holiness. He one day presented Pius with a magnificent edition of his poetry, 
and the Pontiff condescended to accept it: but added, at the same time, after quoting some verses of 
Metastasio, <quote>“<hi rend="italic">No one, now a days, writes like that great 
poet</hi>”</quote>.</p>
               <p>Monti was now the poet of the popular assemblies, of the armies, of the democratic 
dinners, which rose together at the institution of the new Republic; and his patriotic hymns have, 
almost alone, survived the innumerable copies of verses, inspired by occasions so animating. But he 
did not confine himself to songs: he wrote with sober severity against the priests: such are his 
<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Superstizione</foreign>
                  </title>, and his <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Fanatismo</foreign>
                  </title>, and his <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Visione</foreign>
                  </title>, in which the shade of Louis XVI is changed from the martyr 
of his <title>Basville</title> into a hideous spectre. Neither his labours nor his devotion could, 
however, obtain for Monti the confidence or even the pardon of the friends of the revolution. We 
learn this from his own lips; for he complains of it, and leaves nothing untried to convince his 
fellow citizens of his sincerity, and begs at least for pity, in the opening of one of his poems, in 
which he brings himself upon the stage, and assumes the imploring pathetic attitude of the father of 
a family.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>Stendi dolce amor mio, sposa diletta,</l>
                           <l>A quell'arpa la man, che la soave</l>
                           <l>Dolce fatica di tue dita aspetta!</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Svegliami l'armonia ch'entro le cave</l>
                           <l>Latèbre alberga del sonoro legno,</l>
                           <l>E de' forti pensier volgi la chiave.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>These were to Monti days of humiliation, and of bitterness, and of danger. The 
legislative council passed a severe and an unjust law against those who, before the Italian 
Revolution, had written in favour of tyranny; and it was seen that this law was directed more 
particularly against the author of the <title>Basvilliana</title>. The low retainers of literature, under 
the pretext of patriotism, now gave vent to their jealousy, and assailed Monti with scurrilities 
equally violent and mean.</p>
               <p>His friends had procured him a place in the commissariat of Romagna: but he was 
acoused of peculation, and carried before a tribunal. — The calumny was proved, and the 
defendant acquitted, but no steps were taken to punish the calumniators.</p>
               <p>Such were the dangers of his position, or such was the inconstancy of his soul, that 
Monti disgraced himself beyond the wishes of his rivals. Pius VI was carried off from Rome by the 
French, and the poet chose this forced migration of his former master for the occasion of an 
invective imitated from that ode of Horace, in which the Roman republic is compared to a ship 
tossed by the wind and waves, and steering for the harbour. No protestant pen has ever traced 
invectives more severe against the Great Harlot than are poured forth by the repentant secretary.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>Di mala merce e di dolor vai carca,</l>
                           <l>O Nave, che dal Tosco al Sardo lito</l>
                           <l>Porti il gran Pescator, che in infinito</l>
                           <l>Mar di colpe ha di Pier rotta la barca:</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Vedi come t'insegue e il dorso inarca</l>
                           <l>L'onda irata? de' venti odi il ruggito?</l>
                           <l>Prendi porto, sollecita il pentito</l>
                           <l>Remo e di tanto peccator ti scarca.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Dante had before called upon the islands of Capraia and Gorgona to block up the mouth 
of the Arno, and drown the inhabitants of Pisa, for their cruelty to the children of Ugolino; and 
Monti now invoked Sardinia, and told it to fly away, that the <emph>last of monsters</emph> 
might not find even a tomb to shelter him,

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l part="F">e dritto fora</l>
                        <l>Non dar di tomba nè d'arena un velo</l>
                        <l>All'ultimo de' mostri.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>

Monti at least revenged himself of Pius for placing him below Metastasio.</p>
               <p>It was a short time afterwards that Suvaroff and the Austrians made themselves masters 
of Italy. Monti fled to France, and the distresses of his exile gave a new vigour and dignity to his 
exertions.</p>
               <p>Mascheroni, a mathematician, much esteemed in Italy, and a writer of verses admired 
for their elegance, had distinguished himself for his enthusiastic love of liberty, and, what was much 
more rare, by his noble integrity of character and purity of manners. He also had escaped, on the 
same occasion, to Paris, where he died. Monti thought this a good opportunity for writing another 
poem, which he called the <title>Death of Mascheroni</title> (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">In Morte 
di Mascheroni</foreign>
                  </title>), on the plan of his Basville. The spirit of his hero is in like manner 
made to traverse the earth, and in his view of the changes of Italy beholds the advantages of liberty 
and the pernicious effects of popular licentiousness. The political aim of this poem is more useful, 
and the subject is better handled, than in the <title>Death of Basville</title>; but the author could 
not refuse himself the satisfaction of consigning to perpetual infamy the names of his demagogue 
persecutors.</p>
               <p>The Italians discover a greater variety and interest in the scenes presented to the notice 
of Mascheroni than in those of Basville. They think the style less pointed, but more rich and more 
graceful, and they look upon the <foreign lang="ita">terze rime</foreign> as less monotonous and 
more harmonious than any of his former specimens. The plan was equally vast with that of his first 
poem, and it was, like <title>Basville</title>, also stopped at the fourth canto: for Bonaparte 
became Emperor of the French and King of Italy, and Monti hastened to publish six cantos of 
another poem: these were to be the first part of a long work which he called <title>The Bard of the 
Black Forest</title> (<title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Il Bardo della Selva Nera</foreign>
                  </title>).</p>
               <p>It must be owned that the conception of this poem is vastly puerile. The author is 
obliged to imagine that there are bards who deal in verse and prophecy still to be found by those 
who look for them; and just such a one as Caesar and Lucan saw in the depths of Germany is 
discovered by Monti in 1805, hidden somewhere in the Black Forest. This bard has a daughter, 
Malvina, who is surprised into a sentimental passion for a French officer, who has been wounded in 
the battle of Albeck. The * victories of Napoleon are chaunted forth by the same officer, who, it 
seems, succeeds in persuading the bard of the advantages of imperial despotism; for he prophesies 
the absolute monarchy of the triumphant warrior.</p>
               <p>This poem is in different metres; in blank verse, in heroical and in lyrical stanzas; a 
mixture which has great success with us, but is far from agreeable to the Italians, who have been 
taught by Dante to run into any embarrassment rather than facilitate the art of poetry.</p>
               <p>Monti left this poem also incomplete; and Napoleon, to encourage the continuation of a 
prophecy so flattering, created him a knight of two orders, and gave him a thousand louis d'ors. The 
emperor also assigned him a pension, and made him his historiographer.</p>
               <p>The foregoing censure of the Bard of the Black Forest should be accompanied with the 
confession that it contains some admirable passages. Such is the description of the night after a 
bloody battle.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>Pallido intanto su l'Abnobie rupi</l>
                        <l>Il Sol cadendo, raccogliea d'intorno</l>
                        <l>Delle cose i colori, e alla pietosa</l>
                        <l>Notte del mondo concedea la cura;</l>
                        <l>Ed ella del regal suo velo eterno</l>
                        <l>Spiegando il lembo, raccendea negli astri</l>
                        <l>La morta luce, e la spegnea sul volto</l>
                        <l>Degli stanchi mortali. Era il tuon queto</l>
                        <l>De' fulmini guerrieri, e ne vagava</l>
                        <l>Sol per la valle il fumo atro, confuso</l>
                        <l>Colle nebbie de' boschi e de' torrenti:</l>
                        <l>Eran quete le selve, eran dell'aure</l>
                        <l>Queti i sospiri; ma lugubri e cupi</l>
                        <l>S'udian gemiti e grida in lontananza</l>
                        <l>Di languenti trafitti, e un calpestio</l>
                        <l>Di cavalli e di fanti, e sotto il grave</l>
                        <l>Peso de' bronzi un cigolio di rote</l>
                        <l>Che mestizia e terror mettea nel core.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>

Monti, in this poem, has with his usual taste profited by the <title>Ossian</title> of Cesarotti and 
the French prose translation of Gray's odes, and of Shakespeare. He does not read English, but he is 
as ardent an admirer of our great dramatist as he is of Dante. The writer has heard him pronounce 
his decided judgment, that the world has produced but <emph>three poets</emph>, properly so 
called; and Homer, with the two just mentioned, form his triumvirate. The two following stanzas 
will be seen to have been copied from the speech of Ulysses in <title>Troilus and Cressida</title>, 
where the necessity of a monarchy is deduced from the pre–eminence of the sun above the 
stars.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>Delle stelle monarca egli s'asside</l>
                           <l>Sul trono della luce; e con eterna</l>
                           <l>Unica legge il moto, e i rai divide</l>
                           <l>Ai seguaci pianeti, e li governa.</l>
                           <l>Per lui Natura si feconda e ride;</l>
                           <l>Per lui la danza armonica s'alterna</l>
                           <l>Delle stagion; per lui nullo si spia</l>
                           <l>Grano di polve che vital non sia.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>E cagion sola del mirando effetto</l>
                           <l>È la costante eguale unica legge</l>
                           <l>Con che il raggiante imperador l'aspetto</l>
                           <l>Delle create cose alto corregge.</l>
                           <l>Togli questa unità, togli il perfetto</l>
                           <l>Tenor de' vari moti, onde si regge</l>
                           <l>L'armonia de' frenati orbi diversi,</l>
                           <l>E tutti li vedrai confusi e spersi.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Monti undertook a translation of the <title>Iliad</title>, and he undertook it confessing 
that he knew nothing of Greek, but copied after the literal interpretations in Latin; the various 
commentators, and the poetical versions of his predecessors. He depended solely upon his talents 
for versification, and the charm of his style. His readers were equally confident with himself: and 
their previous persuasion secured him the first applauses with which his translation was welcomed 
even by the Greek scolars, who were happy to accept [the help?] of so powerful an ally 
in their contest with Cesarotti. It was, however, discovered that a translation made by one who was 
ignorant of the original could not be depended upon. The distrust spread even to those who were 
themselves equally unacquainted with the Greek text; and the censures of the learned were heard 
and multiplied in every quarter. They have by degrees been pushed to an extreme equally 
unjustifiable with the first praises of his translation. Monti had heard of the simplicity of Homer; he 
wished to imitate this quality, which is so much eulogized, and so little capable of definition. To 
accomplish this project, he sprinkled his phrases with Italian <emph>idiotisms</emph>, and he 
moreover was prodigal of words from the Latin, which, although they have a certain classical air, 
and are well chosen, expressive, and clear, and enrich the language, give, however, a prosaic and 
pedantic air, that renders his manner disagreeable and dry. He has almost always faithfully given 
the meaning of Homer, but he has frequently omitted to lay hold of those minute and accessory 
beauties which form in fact the exclusive merit of great writers, and which, as they are rather felt 
than seen, are the despair of the most expert translator.</p>
               <p>Monti has given an agreeable colouring to the pictures of the <title>Iliad</title>; but he 
has not always been sufficiently exact in his representation of him, who is, as it were, the master of 
<emph>design</emph>, and the father of all the great artists. He is simple and he is easy, but he is 
not natural: he has more fire than strength. It must still be allowed, that the verses and style of 
Monti render his <title>Iliad</title> more agreeable than it appears in the meagre translation of 
Salvini, or in the <foreign lang="ita">rifacimento</foreign> of Cesarotti. He may at least pretend to 
the double merit of having done better than others, and of having excited others to do better than 
him.</p>
               <p>As to the general method, his style is founded upon the exquisite example furnished by 
Virgil in his imitations of the Greek poet; and, as far as respects the versification, he has studied the 
translation of the <title>Eneid</title> by Hannibal Caro, which Monti considers as the purest model 
of blank verse, and the true depository of the riches and the elegance of the Italian language. His 
version, like that of his prototype, is, in fact, invariably flowing, and derives its chief excellence 
from periods well rounded, and a cadence always agreeable. The numbers and the accents of each 
verse are <emph>comparatively</emph> neglected. This manner of writing flatters the ear, and is 
not so varied as to be fatiguing, but it is liable to the monotony which offends us in Ovid, and is still 
more striking in a language more melodious and less sonorous than the Latin, and whose heroic 
verses have not the advantage of the hexametral length.</p>
               <p>Monti has also translated Persius, and has given to him a clearness of idea and a softness 
of expression not to be found in the most obscure and the harshest of all the ancient poets. Yet he 
has rendered some satires line by line, and bound himself by the test before applied by Davanzati to 
Tacitus. This translation has ceased to be spoken of, except to cite those notes which were 
composed by the author in 1803, in the height of his entusiasm for republics, and of his detestation 
of the vice and tyranny of the Roman Emperors.</p>
               <p>The talents of Monti were devoted, with a constancy proportioned to the duration of the 
French power, to the praise of Napoleon, his unwearied patron. But neither the attachment of the 
poet, nor the liberality of the Emperor, contributed, in the expected degree, to the reputation of the 
author or to the glory of his imperial Mecaenas. When Napoleon, after the battle of Jena, sent the 
sword of Frederic II to Paris, Monti wrote a poem in one canto, and called it the <title>Sword of 
Frederic</title>. But <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">La Spada di Federico</foreign>
                  </title> had some 
defects, not only of composition and style, but even in the versification, which the partisans of 
Bonaparte themselves could not pardon, and, accordingly, attacked with a success dangerous to the 
superiority of Monti, who ran a second risk of losing his pre–eminence, by a poem which he 
published two or three years afterwards, and called the <title>Palingenesis</title>. This 
<title>Regeneration</title> was the system of Pythagoras demonstrated in the metamorphoses 
produced in the world by the genius of Bonaparte; and the apparent object of Monti was to rival the 
<title>Pronéa</title> of Cesarotti. Monti had not the same excuse as the Paduan poet: he was not 
very aged, nor did he write at the express order of the Emperor. But his <title>Palingenesis</title> 
was not more fortunate than the <title>Pronéa</title>.</p>
               <p>The odes published by Monti on the usual occasions of victories and treaties of peace, 
on the marriages and the births of princes, and which he struck off at a heat with inconceivable 
rapidity, are most of them finished to perfection. Even those which are on the whole but middling 
performances, contain stanzas cited by the Italians as masterpieces in this way of writing.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>Lassù, dov'anco</l>
                           <l>Il muto arriva</l>
                           <l>Gemer del verme che calcato spira;</l>
                           <l>Del Nume al fianco</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Siede una Diva,</l>
                           <l>Che chiusa in negro ammanto</l>
                           <l>Scrive i delitti coronati, e all'ira</l>
                           <l>Di Dio presenta delle genti il pianto.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>The series of Monti's poems would not be completely cited without mentioning three of 
considerable length: <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Il Prometeo</foreign>
                  </title>, <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">La Musogonia</foreign>
                  </title>, and <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">La 
Feroniade</foreign>
                  </title>, of which he has published only the first cantos and some fragments. 
The second of these is an imitation of Hesiod. The allegory of Prometheus furnishes a clear and 
poetical development of the merit and the perilous course of that superior order of beings who 
dedicate their lives to the enlightening of the human race, and displays the ingratitude of the people 
towards the defenders of their liberty, and the despotism which is the closing scene of every 
political drama. <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">La Feroniade</foreign>
                  </title>, a name borrowed from 
that of the nymph cited by Virgil and Horace, and who was one of the Roman deities that had a 
temple in the Pontine Marshes, was a poem composed for Pius VI, who had undertaken to drain and 
cultivate, and people those marshes. The enemies of Monti republished some passages of these 
three poems, to shew that he had substituted the eulogy of his new protectors by the erasure of those 
originally inserted in praise of the Pope.</p>
               <p>The prose of Monti is distinguished for the ease, the clearness, the harmony, and the 
metaphorical richness which characterise his verses: but the style is unequal, and now and then 
infected with <hi rend="italic">Gallicisms</hi>. The poetical diction of Italy has, by the efforts of 
many great writers, retained its purity through the revolutions of five centuries; but the prose has 
been subject to the changes of time, and to the invasion of foreign arms and foreign literature. 
Monti has been lately occupied with a laborious work, meant to supply the void left by the Cruscan 
academicians in their dictionary, and to counteract the prejudices of the too rigorous adherents of 
the old school, and the bold dogmas of licentious innovators. It is thought that in this work, the 
offspring of his cooler reflection, and directed to aims more useful, he will avoid those inaccuracies 
of haste and passion which disfigured his previous performances, and degraded them into mere 
personal controversies. An exception should be made in favour of two or three discourses, 
published when he was professor at Pavia. One of them is much praised, and perhaps not a little 
owing to the subject of which it treats, namely, <hi rend="italic">Of the scientific discoveries 
which foreigners have usurped to themselves, in prejudice of the Italian inventors</hi>. Monti 
shewed his patriotism in this treatise, but much could not be said of his knowledge or of his equity. 
Even his eloquence was more lively than vigorous. He threw down his glove in defiance of all 
foreigners, but more especially of the French, and was backed by his countrymen, who have fallen 
into the absurdity of depreciating the present merit of other nations, by comparing it whith the past 
glories of their ancestors.</p>
               <p>Monti has never been wise enough to laugh at silly criticism, nor was he ever known to 
spare a powerless adversary. Having been rudely attacked, he has always defended himself rudely. 
He seems to have looked upon a censure of his writings as an obstacle thrown maliciously in the 
way of his fortune. In this temper he told the Abate Bettinelli, “It is not the poet that these 
people want to attack; no, it is the historiographer of Napoleon; and they conspire to make me 
appear in his eyes a contemptible writer”.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>Lettera all'Abate Bettinelli, Milano, 1809.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He tried, therefore, to persuade the court and the ministers to prosecute his adversaries: 
but it should be told, that he employed the same influence in the promotion of his friends. Towards 
them Monti is truly the warmest and the most devoted of men, and is ready for, every generous 
sacrifice as long as he feels assured that he has no reason to suspect the loyalty of their 
attachment.</p>
               <p>His violent literary disputes with his distinguished contemporaries, with Mazza, 
Cesarotti, and Bettinelli, have all terminated by a solicitation of their friendship: and he has not 
refused to restore his confidence to others who, having grievously offended him, have entreated to 
be reconciled. It has happened to him to quarrel with, and to pardon, the same individual several 
times.</p>
               <p>The habit of writing on temporary topics may explain, perhaps, the care which he takes 
to acquire renown by efforts which, in the end, frequently terminate in the loss of it. He is afraid of 
the very newspaper writers, and is ambitious of their suffrages. He keeps up a regular 
correspondence with all the men of letters in Italy, and barters with them the usual commodity of 
mutual adulation. He is, however, sincere enough with those young writers who ask his advice, and 
contrives to encourage them without flattery, and to instruct them without arrogance. He repeats 
verses inimitably: he is eloquent in his conversation, which is generally of the softer kind; but the 
slightest contradiction provokes him to a vehement defence of positions which he abandons the next 
day with perfect indifference.</p>
               <p>It is probable that the inconstancy, as well as the momentary eagerness of certain 
individuals, is to be attributed less to education than to nature. The life of Dryden can scarcely be 
compared in a single instance with that of Monti; nor is the poetry, nor even the character of the 
English laureate at all similar to that of the Italian. The above disgraceful quality they have, 
however, in common with each other. Both of them have degraded the literature to which they owe 
their fame, by making it subservient to their private interests, at the expense of truth and of honour. 
Both of them have been systematic flatterers of the powerful and the great, and both of them have 
wanted the requisite consolations of old age.</p>
               <p>Monti has pursued the Austrians with the war of words, after each of their repeated 
defeats. When they re–appeared as conquerors, they deprived him of almost all his pensions; 
but they bargained at the same time for a <foreign lang="ita">cantata</foreign> from his pen, 
which was set to music and sung in the theatre, to welcome their return to Italy. It is neither a 
hazardous nor a severe reflection to assert, that this poet must look back with feelings of bitter 
regret upon sixty years of laborious and brilliant exertions, which are about to end for ever; and 
which have left him in the enjoyment neither of an independent fortune nor of a spotless reputation; 
nor of those fixed principles without the possession of which no one can, without trembling, dare to 
contemplate the closing of his career.</p>
               <p>A splendid example and a warning for an apostate generation:

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="lat">
                        <l>Petite hinc juvenesque senesque</l>
                        <l>Finem animo certum, miserisque viatica canis.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 n="Hugo Foscolo">
               <head>HUGO FOSCOLO</head>
               <p>When the revolution of 1795 gave a shock to principles for ages established in Italy, and 
set in motion the spirits and the interests of the inhabitants of every province, the writers before 
mentioned had all of them published those works which gave them a fixed reputation with their 
countrymen.</p>
               <p>Hugo Foscolo was at that time a youth, but not too young to profit by the friendship and 
the example of his distinguished contemporaries. The total change in the political condition of his 
country, his military education, and the part which he played in public affairs, developed however 
his talents, and formed his character, in a manner quite different from that of his predecessors: 
besides, the circumstances under which he wrote arrived too late to form their style; and being now 
gone by, may perhaps require a course of ages to reproduce.</p>
               <p>Foscolo laid it down for a principle, that Italian poetry had expired with Tasso, and had 
been re–suscitated only in the present day. Hear his own words — «Senza 
l'<title>Ossian</title> del Cesarotti, il <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Giorno</foreign>
                  </title> del 
Parini, Vittorio Alfieri, e Vincenzo Monti, la nostra poesia si giacerebbe tuttavia sepolta con le 
ceneri di Torquato Tasso. Da indi in qua un secolo la inorpellò, e l'altro la immiserì. 
L'<title>Ossian</title> può far dare nello strano; il Parini nel leccato; l'Alfieri nell'aspro; e il Monti 
nell'ornato: ma le umane virtù non fruttano senza l'innesto d'un vizio. I grandi ingegni emuleranno: i 
mezzani scimiotteranno: e coloro che esplorano i propri meriti nelle altrui colpe, si getteranno simili 
a corvi sovra le piaghe de' generosi cavalli».</p>
               <p>This passage, extracted from his Preface to an experiment for translating the 
<title>Iliad</title>, printed at Brescia in 1807,

<note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <foreign lang="ita">Esperimento di traduzione dell'<title>Iliade</title>
                        </foreign>.</p>
                  </note>

 may serve as a specimen of his style and his literary opinions.</p>
               <p>He commenced his career a year before the fall of the Venetian republic, with a tragedy 
called <title>Thyestes</title>. Being angry at the little attention paid by the Venetians to the 
tragedies of Alfieri, and at the corrupted taste which made them prefer and applaud those of the 
Marquis Pindemonte and of Count Pepoli, he resolved that his drama should have only four 
personages; and that the simplicity and severity of his whole composition should rival Alfieri and 
the Greek tragedians. With this hardy project, he contrived that his play should be acted on the same 
night when two new pieces from the pen of the above Marquis and Count were to be represented at 
other theatres of the same town. The courage and the youth of the author enabled him to triumph 
over his rivals, and his <title>Thyestes</title> received more applause than perhaps it deserved. 
The actors published it in the tenth volume of the <title>
                     <foreign lang="ita">Teatro Italiano 
Applaudito</foreign>
                  </title>, subjoining to it an account of its great success, and a criticism written 
in favour of the author. Foscolo himself adopted the extraordinary proceeding of publishing a 
severe censure of his own work, the success of which he attributed solely to its conformity with the 
great models of antiquity. The pamphlet was ill received by the public, and the Venetians painted 
the portrait of the young poet in the drop curtain of the Fenice Theatre, amongst those who had a 
better claim to this distinction. The <title>Thyestes</title> is still occasionally acted, and is 
sustained by the warmth of the dialogue, and the strength of the dramatic passions, but the style is 
so harsh as to be insupportable to the reader.</p>
               <p>The learned of Italy speak neither well nor ill of the <title>Letters of Ortis</title>, 
which, however, has been more frequently reprinted in his own country than any other of Foscolo's 
works, and is certainly much more known on the other side of the Alps. The Germans have 
exhausted upon this little book all the metaphysics of criticism: they have translated it twice; and a 
certain professor Luden has accompanied his version with a whole volume of dissertations. After 
all, it is but an imitation of <emph>Werter</emph>. There is however this striking difference, that 
the object of the Italian is solely political. There is indeed something for all tastes in the politics, 
and the poetry, and the love of <emph>Ortis</emph>. The allusions to the downfall of the Venetian 
republic, and the introduction of living interlocutors, such as Parini at Milan, give a reality to the 
fable which must be highly interesting to the Italians, and is attractive even to strangers. There is a 
melancholy patriotism in every word in which he mentions Italy, that makes the author respectable 
in the eyes of every generous reader. There are some pictures of small objects that evince a 
considerable knowledge of the human heart, and are extremely affecting. The little dog of the lady 
who falls in love with <emph>Ortis</emph> may be mentioned as one. The author is in his proper 
element when he breaks forth into his ethical reflections: how truly he says, “That we are too 
proud to give our compassion when we feel we can give nothing else”.</p>
               <p>The love of <emph>Ortis</emph> is, perhaps, the least interesting portion of the work; 
there is not importance enough attached to his existence, to make it natural that so much importance 
should be attached to his end. It was difficult, perhaps, to give many attractions to the adventures of 
an obscure politician; but it is still possible that those of an age and sex more accessible to the 
tender feelings may be touched by the misfortunes and the heroic despair of the Italian 
<emph>Werter</emph>. But <emph>Ortis</emph> may boast of having been the first book that 
induced the females and the mass of readers to interest themselves in public affairs. This was a 
mighty exploit in a country where one maxim had been for ages the ground–work of 
education for all classes of society, <foreign lang="lat">De Deo parum, de Principe nihil</foreign>. 
It is difficult at this day to find in Italy an edition of the <title>Letters of Ortis</title> altogether 
exempt from those mutilations which the revisors of one kind or another have inflicted on this 
romance. In spite, however, of all their prudent efforts, it has been found impossible to emasculate 
every page which launches forth invectives against the corruption of the old government, against 
the foreign usurpation of the new, and lastly against the treachery with which the French general 
bought and sold the republic of Venice.</p>
               <p>Chiari and Piazza, and other common writers, had before published some hundreds of 
romances, which had been the delight only of the vulgar reader; for those of a more refined taste 
had resorted to the foreign novels. The <title>Letters of Ortis</title> is the only work of the kind, 
the boldness of whose thoughts, and the purity of whose language, combined with a certain easy 
<emph>style</emph>, have suited it to the taste of every reader. It cannot be too often remarked, 
that it is principally the style which in all works attracts the admiration of the Italians; and it may 
here be mentioned, that their critics have laid it down as a rule, that the elements of their prose are 
to be collected only in the period between Dante and Machiavelli. This is the opinion of Alfieri.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See his answer to Calsabigi, in the edition of his tragedies by Didot.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Foscolo has followed this rule in his <title>Ortis</title>, and more scrupulously still in 
the <title>Sentimental Journey</title>, which he has translated with the words and phrases of the 
fourteenth century; not, however, to the prejudice of the conversational ease of our Yorick. This 
work, so popular in all foreign countries, had been twice before translated into Italian; but the 
torpidity of theirt style, and their repeated Gallicisms, had consigned these preceding versions to 
contempt. Foscolo published his translation under the name of Didimo Chierico; and in one of his 
many notes he gives us the following remarks on his native language. <quote>«<foreign lang="ita">Le donne gentili insegnarono al Parroco Yorick, e a me suo Chierico, a sentire, e quindi 
a parlare men rozzamente; ed io per gratitudine aggiungerò questo avviso per esse. La lingua 
Italiana è un bel metallo che bisogna ripulire della ruggine dell'antichità, e depurare della falsa lega 
della moda; e poscia batterlo genuino in guisa che ognuno possa riceverlo e spenderlo con fiducia, e 
dargli tal conio che paia nuovo e nondimeno tutti sappiano ravvisarlo. Ma i letterati vostri non 
raccattano dagli antichi se non se il rancidume, e gli scienziati vi parlano franciosamente. I primi 
non hanno mente, gli altri non hanno cuore; e per quanti idiomi e' si sappiano, non avranno mai 
stile</foreign>»</quote>.</p>
               <p>The preponderance of French power during the reign of Louis XIV and even in that of 
Louis XV, had infected the Italian language with an infinity of French phrases and idioms. The 
consciousness of the extreme corruption induced by the revolution has given rise to a zealous spirit 
of reform, which has itself degenerated into a superstitious worship of the ancients, and has rather 
augmented than diminished the licence of the opposite writers. We consequently find many works 
composed solely of phrases almost entirely obsolete, and distinguished neither for the energy of the 
old writers, nor for the ease of the new. Others, and they are the majority, terrified by the study of a 
language the abundance of whose words, and, the variety of whose combinations, render it almost 
insuperable, affect that sort of style now so common throughout Europe, which they are pleased to 
call philosophical, and which, in fact, is but a jargon neither Italian nor French, but a bad mixture of 
both.</p>
               <p>If, therefore, good writers are rare in all countries, they are more especially so in Italy; 
for they have to connect the generic characteristics constantly inherent for five centuries in the 
Italian language, with the specific characteristics of their own times: and this amalgamation, not 
depending on any fixed rules, must be contrived solely by the individual talents of each author. This 
accounts for the surprising diversity which foreigners are apt to observe in the manner of writing 
employed by the various authors of the same age; and perhaps this same diversity is more 
remarkable in the prose of Foscolo than of other writers. The Italian author also makes it an article 
of faith to vary his style according to his subject. Thus there is no less a difference between the 
letters, the romances, and the orations, than between the history and the epic or lyric poetry of these 
varied compositions. The <title>Ortis</title> and the <title>Sentimental Journey</title> resemble 
each other very little: notwithstanding that the author has followed the same rules of composition, 
and has always preserved the traits peculiar to his style. As for his <title>Discourse for the 
Congress of Lyons</title>, it appears evidently written by the same man, but in a different 
language.</p>
               <p>He wrote this <title>Discourse</title> at the injunction of his government, when 
Bonaparte, in the year 1801, convoked at Lyons the <emph>Notables</emph> of the Cisalpine 
Republic. The directions given to the orator were to pronounce a panegyric; but Foscolo adopted a 
different course. He presented a moving picture of the wretched state of the laws, of the armies, of 
the finances, and of the moral condition of the new republic. The sects, both old and new, that 
distracted their country — the priests, the nobles, the democrats, the partisans of foreign 
usurpation, the adulatory writers, the libelists, the defrauders of the public revenue, the monopolists, 
who profited by the sale of the national property, are all handled with the same severity. The 
following description of the masters of the republic, if it degrades the nation in one respect, exalts it 
on the other hand; for there must be something great in a people which can produce a single man 
who dares, in the cause of virtue, to paint his countrymen in such colours.</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>«<foreign lang="ita">Uomini nuovi ci governavano, per educazione nè 
politici, nè guerrieri (essenziali doti ne' capi delle republiche); antichi schiavi, novelli tiranni, 
schiavi pur sempre di se stessi e delle circonstanze che nè sapeano nè voleano domare; fra i pericoli 
e l'amor del potere ondeggianti, tutto perplessamente operavano; regia autorità era in essi, ma per 
inopia di coraggio e d'ingegno, nè violenti nè astuti; consci de' propri vizi, e quindi diffidenti, 
discordi addossantisi scambievoli vituperi; datori di cariche, e palpati, non temuti: alla plebe esosi 
come potenti; e come imbecilli, spregiati: convennero con iattanza di publico bene e libidine di 
primeggiare ma nè pensiero pure di onore; vili con gli audaci, audaci coi vili, spegneano le accuse 
coi beneficj e le querele con le minaccie; e per la sempre imminente rovina, di oro puntellati con la 
fortuna, di brighe con i proconsoli, e di tradimenti con i principi 
stranieri</foreign>»</quote>.</p>
               <p>The chief cause of this general depravity he attributes to the absence of Bonaparte in 
Egypt, which allowed the French Directory to tyrannise over Italy, and to pillage her provinces, not 
only by their own missions and generals, but by the appointment of magistrates, timid, ignorant, and 
avaricious, some of whom were to be found in that government which had assigned to Foscolo the 
pleasing duties of pronouncing their panegyric.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See his Dedication: «Ai membri del comitato del Governo».</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The praises bestowed by the orator upon the hero who was to remedy their national 
wrongs, magnificent as they are in some respects, are still associated with the boldest maxims, and 
with predictions which are seldom hazarded in the hour of victory. With what satisfaction may 
Foscolo now look back upon the following prophetic warning!</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>«<foreign lang="ita">A ciascuno de' tuoi pregi la storia contrappone e 
Tiberio solenne politico, e Marco Aurelio Imperadore filosofo, e Papa Leone X ospite delle lettere. 
Che se molti di questi sommi, scarchi non vanno di delitti, uomini e mortali erano come sei tu, e 
non le speranze o il tremore de' contemporanei, ma la imperterrita posterità le lor sentenze scriveva 
su la lor sepultura. Infiniti ed illustri esempi hanno santificata oramai quella massima de' sapienti: 
niuno uomo doversi virtuoso predicare e beato anzi la morte</foreign>»</quote>.</p>
               <p>After describing the distress of his country, the speaker, who calls himself <foreign lang="ita">Giovine non affatto libero</foreign>, proposes certain remedies, and those he would 
apply not only to Italy, but to maintain the renown of that hero whose future glory he declares to 
depend principally on the durable independence of a nation which he had rescued from the slavery 
and the disgrace of ages. Foscolo afterwards published this <title>Discourse</title>, with the 
following motto from Sophocles: — <quote>“My soul groans for my country, for 
myself, and also for thee”</quote>.</p>
               <p>This discourse is not more than eighty pages: and notwithstanding it is an historical 
composition, maintains a certain impetuosity and gravity of style which overwhelm and fatigue the 
attention. The events are hinted at, not detailed; the development concerns only their causes and 
their results. This brevity might be agreeable to those who had been spectators of, or actors in, the 
short and transitory scene; but foreign readers, and even those Italians removed by time or place 
from the original action, are left in the dark. It would be difficult to prove that the style of Tacitus, 
which Foscolo has not only copied but exaggerated with, the devotion of a youth enchanted by his 
model, can be well adapted to this sort of composition. The English, who have perhaps run into the 
opposite extreme, will be astonished to hear that this <title>Discourse</title> was particularly 
esteemed by the critics, on account of its close resemblance to the Latin. We should call this 
pedantry: but it appears a meritorious exploit in the eyes of a nation, which, having for two hundred 
years diluted its lan guage to insipidity, now lays it down for a maxim, that for the 
<emph>graces</emph> of style, the early Tuscan authors are to be consulted; and for the strength, 
and, if the word may be used, the nobility, of the language, the Latins are the only safe model. It 
must be confessed, that the origin of the language admits of this union. It is not unnatural that when 
they would discourse of liberty, they should have recourse to the manner of their Roman 
ancestors.</p>
               <p>Bonaparte at the congress of Lyons, changed the name of the Cisalpine into that of the 
Italian Republic. He appointed himself president of this new state, and promulgated a constitution 
which he continued to violate at will up to the other change which converted the Republic into a 
Kingdom, and placed the administration of Upper Italy in the hands of a French viceroy. The only 
effect of Foscolo's discourse was to stop his own military promotion: but the loss of fortune was 
more than compensated by the public gratitude, which pointed to him as the man who had spoken 
the sense of the people, who had told the corageous truth, and had stood forward as the champion of 
national independence. It seems, however, that he continued in the army some time after this effort. 
The date of the preface to his <title>Sentimental Journey</title> shews that he was, in 1805, at 
Calais with one of the Italian regiments which Bonaparte had united to his <title>Army of 
England</title>. His dedication of the works of Montecuculi, published in 1808 and 1809, which is 
addressed to General Caffarelli, minister of war of the Italian kingdom, tells us that he was 
aid–de–camp to that officer.</p>
               <p>Foscolo published his edition of Montecuculi in two volumes, <foreign lang="lat">in 
folio</foreign>, from the manuscripts discovered in the archives of the last Prince Trivulzio, by 
Serassi, the biographer of Tasso; and more recently, by other enquirers. These manuscripts were 
more complete than those of the old incorrect edition, made just after the death of the author, which 
had never been re printed, and was so much forgotten that Montecuculi was known only through the 
French and German translations. The object of Foscolo was more than literary: he wished by the 
example and precepts of an illustrious fellow citizen, to inspire the Italians with a portion of his 
martial spirit, as well as to replace the author in his due rank amongst the best classical writers. He 
placed Montecuculi by the side of Machiavelli, and the compressed commanding style of the great 
rival of Turenne facilitated the labours of his editor in filling up the many blanks of the manuscript. 
Foscolo was commended for these supplements, and for his happy imitation of the original style; 
but he was accused of having been too licentious in his emendations of the text.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <quote>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Ha supplito alle lacune con lo stile del Montecucoli: ma 
Montecucoli nel proprio testo parla spesso con lo stile di F</foreign>
                        </quote>. See — 
<title>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Giornale della Società d'Incoraggiamento</foreign>
                        </title>, anno 
1809.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Montecuculi wrote his commentaries and his military aphorisms when the use of 
artillery was but imperfectly known, and when a great part both of the infantry and cavalry fought 
with pikes and halberds, and the principal object of every war was the attack and defence of 
fortified towns. Foscolo illustrated his author with notes of two kinds; some of them consisting of 
passages from the classics, serving to show the Greek and Roman art of war, and the others relating 
to the system of Frederic II and of Napoleon. By this plan the editor meant to apply each precept of 
Montecuculi to the three principal epochs in the history of military art: the ancient, the middle, and 
the modern period. To each volume he subjoined dissertations written with precisely the same 
object: he calls Napoleon <foreign lang="ita">il maggiore guerriero delle età moderne</foreign>, 
an eulogium which must be allowed far from extravagant, at the time that the two senates of France 
and of Italy declared him the <emph>Thunderer of the Earth</emph> (“Jupiter foudroyant 
sur la terre”), and all the kings of Europe confessed the title to be fairly earned and duly 
bestowed.</p>
               <p>The Viceroy Eugene had about this time won a battle of no great importance, against the 
Archduke John, in Hungary. The French chose to exalt this victory to a parallel with that of 
Montecuculi, who after two years of perseverance, and with an army of seven thousand men, had 
defeated seventy thousand Turks at a time when they were yet formidable in the field: this was at 
the famous battle of San Gothard. The <emph>bulletins</emph> observed that the Viceroy had 
been victorious on the same spot already illustrated by the exploits of Montecuculi, and had rivalled 
the skilful manoeuvres of the Italian marshal. Foscolo devotes one of his dissertations to refute this 
encomium, and proves that neither the circumstances, nor the position, nor the place were the same; 
and he concludes by insinuating that such exaggerations might be injurious to the merit actually 
acquired by the Viceroy.</p>
               <p>Foscolo was now sent as professor of literature to Pavia, to replace Monti who had been 
appointed historiographer. The new professor opened his course of lectures by an essay on the 
<title>Origin and the Duties of Literature</title>. It was his grand position, that “as society 
could neither be formed originally, nor afterwards kept together, except by the use of words, every 
abuse of this distinctive human faculty, must tend necessarily to the corruption of all social ties. 
Consequently, the men of letters, being especially endowed with the power of words, are traitors to 
their duty whenever they neglect by their writings to excite the generous passions, to demonstrate 
useful truths, to add charms to virtue, and to direct the public opinions to the promotion of national 
prosperity”.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <foreign lang="ita">
                           <bibl>
                              <title>Dell'Origine e dell'Ufficio della Letteratura</title>, Milano, 
1809</bibl>
                        </foreign>.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He goes on to place his men of letters as independent mediators between the government 
which applies to force alone, and has a natural tendency to despotism, and the people, who have no 
less a natural inclination towards licentiousness and slavery. He looks for the proof of these 
principles in the history of all nations; and the more he exults in the utility of literature, the more he 
declaims against the vanity and the baseness both of those who sell their abilities to a tyrant, and of 
those who employ them in administering to the odious passions and the capricious follies of the 
multitude. It was an old and constant practice in Italy to insert an eulogy of the actual government 
in the opening discourses of every professor. Foscolo departed from this ceremony, and subjoined a 
note, saying, “that it belongs to history alone to speak in becoming manner of great 
sovereigns”. He then cited a decree of Augustus Caesar, which forbad the small poets and 
orators to disgrace his name by their ephemeral praises.</p>
               <p>The professorships of litefature not only at Pavia, but also at Bologna,

<note place="foot">
                     <p>On this occasion the celebrated Mezzophanti, professor of Oriental languages, and the most 
extraordinary linguist in existence, was deprived of his chair, and reduced to an income of 750 
francs.</p>
                  </note>

 and Padua, were forthwith suppressed by the government. Many other professorships underwent 
the same fate; namely, those for the Greek and for the Oriental languages, for history, for the 
knowledge of medals, and, in short, for all those branches of study not strictly belonging to 
medicine, to jurisprudence, and to the mathematics. Foscolo retained his chair only two months; and 
about twenty–four other professors, who had not involved themselves in the guilt of 
preaching his principles, were also deprived of their emoluments, after many years of literary 
labour. It would be hazardous to say whether the discourse of Foscolo provoked this measure, or 
whether it had been some time in agitation, but, at all events, the Italians were struck with the 
verification of the words of their own Alfieri, who had told them that <emph>absolute monarchs 
hate the historian, and the poet, and the orator, and give preferences to the sciences</emph>.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See the article on Alfieri.</p>
                  </note>

 Perhaps it may not be uncharitable to add, that the scientific, compared with the literary writers of 
every nation, repay with corresponding submission the partiality of royal patronage.</p>
               <p>Padua, Pavia, and Bologna, beheld the sudden decline of the institutions, which had 
been the ancient ornament of their towns. Four and twenty lyceums were founded in the respective 
departments of the Kingdom, with the pretext of reinstating some of the professors ejected from the 
three universities; but it was impossible to find a sufficient number of learned individuals, or 
adequate salaries for all these establishments, in every branch of science and of literature; and the 
consequence of this dispersion, as well as of the multiplied foundations, was, that the place of 
professor was degraded from those high privileges and that respectability of character which had 
made it for centuries an object of Italian ambition.</p>
               <p>The Cavalier Lamberti, a declared adversay of this writer, and one of those before 
alluded to, who possess the reputation of great scholars, examining the works of Foscolo, calls 
them, <quote>«<foreign lang="ita">tenebrose per certo stile lor proprio di oscurità 
misteriosa e d'idee affollate e appena accennate, e d'eloquenza compressa sdegnosamente; quasi che 
questo autore non voglia per lettori che i suoi pari</foreign>»</quote>.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See — in the Milanese Review — the <title>Poligrafo</title>, the articles signed 
Y.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Hippolitus Pindemonte reproaches him with the same defect, but in the tone more of a 
poet than a critic, and less of a censor than a friend. “Your style”, he says, 
“resembles the Rhone, which flows rapidly from the limpid lake of Geneva, and is lost under 
the Alps, to the regret of the traveller, who knows not how it has disappeared, and who finds 
himself obliged to wander on for some distance before he again beholds its azure current, and hears 
the sound of its rapid stream”.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See Pindemonte's epistle in verse addressed to Hugo Foscolo.</p>
                  </note>

 The political topics which have been generally selected for the subject of his performances, have, 
perhaps, induced this writer to leave us to guess that which he did not like to say openly. It is, 
however, equally true that the constant intensity of thought which he requires of his readers must be 
traced either to the peculiar mode in which his idea sare originally conceived, or to his wish to give 
them a new turn. Indeed all his writings bear the mark of meditation, although much forethought 
cannot be discovered in his familiar conversation, in which he gives a loose to all his ideas as they 
first present themselves. A literary lady has described him as p<foreign lang="ita">arlatore 
facilissimo e facondo</foreign>
                  <note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <foreign lang="ita">
                           <title>Ritratti</title> scritti dalla Contessa ISABELLA 
ALBRIZZI</foreign>.</p>
                  </note>

 and this copious eloquence is accompanied with incessant agitation of the limb and body; which, 
however, is, when he harangues in public, converted into an absolute inactivity. It is told of him that 
he has spoken for hours at the councils of war with his hands fixed on the back of a chair, without 
indulging in the slightest action.</p>
               <p>This fact, incredible as it may be to such as have seen Mr. Foscolo only in private 
society, will not be lost upon those who please themselves with discriminating between the different 
modes of intellectual exertion, and who will be obliged to account for so singular a discrepancy by 
recollecting that Foscolo may have deliberately preferred this motionless eloquence. The truth is, as 
we find in his <title>Discourse upon Literature</title>, that he decries the 
<emph>quackery</emph> of the latter orators of Athens by praising the more ancient speakers, 
who harangued in the manner of Pericles, wrapped up in their <emph>clamys</emph>, without 
gesture or melody: «<foreign lang="ita">Peroravano avvolti, all'uso di Pericle, nella 
clamide, senza gesto nè melodia</foreign>».</p>
               <p>The published poetry of this writer is confined to two odes, and a little work called I 
Sepolcri, written when it was forbidden to bury the dead in family tombs.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>Pur nuova legge impone oggi i sepolcri</l>
                        <l>Fuor de' guardi pietosi, e il nome a' morti</l>
                        <l>Contende.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>

According to the provisions of this new law, all bodies, without distinction, were to be interred in 
public cemeteries without the towns, and the size of the sepulchral stone was prescribed, and the 
epitaphs were subject to the revision and approval of the magistrates. The aim of Foscolo in this 
poem appears to be the proof of the influence produced by the memory of the dead on the manners 
and on the independence of nations.</p>
               <p>It may be sufficient to quote a specimen which will be more easily understood by those 
who have visited the church of Santa Croce at Florence.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <l>Io quando il monumento</l>
                        <l>Vidi ove posa il corpo di quel grande</l>
                        <l>Che temprando lo scettro a' regnatori</l>
                        <l>Gli allor ne sfronda, ed alle genti svela</l>
                        <l>Di che lagrime grondi e di che sangue;
<note place="foot">
                              <p>Machiavelli.</p>
                           </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>E l'arca di colui che nuovo Olimpo</l>
                        <l>Alzò in terra a' celesti;<note place="foot">
                              <p>MichaelAngelo.</p>
                           </note> e di chi vide</l>
                        <l>Sotto l'etereo padiglion rotarsi</l>
                        <l>Più mondi, e il Sole irradiarli immoto,
<note place="foot">
                              <p>Galileo.</p>
                           </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Onde all'Anglo che tanta ala vi stese
<note place="foot">
                              <p>Newton.</p>
                           </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Sgombrò primo le vie del Firmamento;</l>
                        <l>Te beata! gridai, per le felici</l>
                        <l>Aure pregne di vita, e pe' lavacri</l>
                        <l>Che da suoi gioghi a te versa Apennino:</l>
                        <l>Lieta dell'aer tuo, veste la Luna</l>
                        <l>Di luce limpidissima i tuoi colli</l>
                        <l>Per vendemmia festanti; e le convalli</l>
                        <l>Popolate di case e d'oliveti</l>
                        <l>Mille di fiori al Ciel mandano incensi:</l>
                        <l>E tu prima, Firenze, udivi il carme</l>
                        <l>Che allegrò l'ire al Ghibellin fuggiasco;
<note place="foot">
                              <p>Dante.</p>
                           </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>E tu i cari parenti e l'idioma</l>
                        <l>Desti a quel dolce di Calliope labbro
<note place="foot">
                              <p>Petrarch.</p>
                           </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Che Amore in Grecia nudo, e nudo in Roma</l>
                        <l>D'un velo candidissimo adornando</l>
                        <l>Rendea nel grembo a Venere Celeste.</l>
                        <l>Ma più beata che in un tempio accolte</l>
                        <l>Serbi le Itale glorie (ultime forse!)</l>
                        <l>Da che le malvietate Alpi e l'alterna</l>
                        <l>Onnipotenza delle umane sorti</l>
                        <l>Armi, e sostanze t'invadeano, ed are</l>
                        <l>E Patria, e, tranne la memoria, tutto.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>This poem contains only three hundred lines, but it called forth pamphlets and criticisms 
in every shape, and from all quarters. The younger writers tried to imitate it: the critics pronounced 
it to have brought about a reform in the lyrical poetry of Italy. The academy of Brescia proposed a 
prize for the best Latin translation, and awarded their premium to the professor Frederic Borgno, 
who soon after published his version in hexameters, accompanied with a dissertation, a passage of 
which may be quoted to shew the tone of Italian criticism.</p>
               <p>“It is the business of lyrical poetry, properly so called, to present to us interesting 
facts so as to excite our strongest feelings, and to promulgate those opinions which tend to the 
prosperity of nations. Any ten verses which do not furnish the painter with images sufficient to 
compose an historical picture, wich do not shake the soul by the noble recollections they recall, by 
the generous passions they awaken, which do not engrave in luminous characters some useful truth 
upon the mind — these verses may, I confess, be admirable in their kind, but they do not 
belong to lyrical poetry. The prophetic portion of the Bible, some of the hymns attributed to Homer, 
Pindar, Catullus in his marriage of Peleus, the sixth eclogue of Virgil, the episodes in the 
<title>Georgics</title>, a dozen of the odes of Horace, six of the canzoni of Petrarch, a few of 
Chiabrera, of Guidi, of Filicaia, those of Dryden, and two of Gray, are really lyrical. All the other 
poetry of Petrarch, and of those called lyrical, may be justly praised, and may charm a greater 
number of readers even than those above cited, but it is necessary to adopt the division of Cicero, in 
his distinction between <foreign lang="lat">poetae lyrici et melici</foreign>. Pindar belongs to the 
first; Sappho, Anacreon, and Simonides, to the second”.</p>
               <p>The Italians are fond of those classifications, and indulge in them more than we would 
esteem profitable to the study of language. But it is also true, that their critics seldom praise even 
their favourite authors with the indiscriminate fury of our eulogists. Mr. Borgno subjoins to his 
notice of Chiabrera, Guidi, and Filicaia, a list of exceptions to their merits which might surprise a 
foreigner, accustomed to think of the name, rather than the works of their authors. According to this 
authority, sonorous words, and a magnificence of verse and of phrase, are substituted by these 
writers for the requisite variety of harmony and of imagery, whilst they are totally deficient in the 
<foreign lang="ita">chiaroscuro</foreign> of poetry, and have chosen subjects which either are not 
national, or, what is as bad, are totally incapable of interesting their nation.</p>
               <p>Mr. Borgno quotes other poetical works of Foscolo, which appear to be in the same 
style, and, amongst others, his <title>Alceus</title>, which describes the political vicissitudes of 
Italian poetry from the fall of the eastern empire to the present day. He alludes, also, to <title>The 
Graces</title>, a poem, in three cantos. Both the one and the other are, however, inedited, and are 
known only by some fragments.</p>
               <p>The blank verses of Foscolo are totally different from those of any other author. Each 
verse has its peculiar pauses and accents placed according to the subject described. His melancholy 
sentiments move in a slow and measured pace, his lively images bound along with the rapid march 
of joy. Some of his lines are composed almost entirely of vowels, others almost entirely of 
consonants; and whatever an Englishman may think of this imitation of sense by sound (a decried 
effort since the edict of Dr. Johnson), the Italian poet has at least succeeded in giving a different 
<emph>melody</emph> to each verse, and in varying the <emph>harmony</emph> of every 
period.</p>
               <p>It is perhaps necessary to be an Italian to feel the full effect of these combinations; but 
the scholar of every country may perceive that Foscolo has formed himself on the Greek model, not 
only in this particular, but in other branches of his art. In fact he was born in the Ionian islands, as 
he himself tells us in some beautiful verses at the end of one of his odes.

<quote rend="block">
                     <lg lang="ita">
                        <lg>
                           <l>Fra l'Isole</l>
                           <l>Che col selvoso dorso</l>
                           <l>Rompono agli Euri, e al grande Ionio il corso,</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Ebbi in quel mar la culla:</l>
                           <l>Ivi erra ignudo spirito</l>
                           <l>Di Faon la Fanciulla;</l>
                           <l>E se il notturno Zefiro</l>
                           <l>Blando sui flutti spira</l>
                           <l>Suonano i liti un lamentar di lira.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
               </p>
               <p>Two tragedies, the <title>Ricciarda</title> and the <title>Ajax</title>, by the same 
author, were stopped by the government after the first representation. They excited a great curiosity 
from motives not altogether poetical. It was reported that Moreau was his Ajax, that Napoleon was 
to figure in his Agamennon, and that his holiness the Pope would easily recognised in Chalcas. The 
known principles of Foscolo facilitated the recognition of these originals, who, after all, perhaps, 
never sat to the poet for their likeness. Whatever were his intentions, he received immediate orders 
to quit the kingdom of Italy, and to reside in some town of the French empire. He accordingly fixed 
his abode at Florence, at that time a department of France.</p>
               <p>Foscolo has lived and written in a state of open war with the writers of the day, and the 
reigning political parties. It is not surprising, therefore, that he has been severely handled in 
publications of every kind, and particularly in the journals, which will be found to contain 
imputations against him not confined to his literary life. He was never personal in his first attacks; 
and he never replied to the personalities of others. He even affected so complete a contempt for 
them as to republish and distribute some of the libels written against himself. Perhaps he is not 
aware that this apparent moderation is any thing rather than a proof of his indifference to 
attack.</p>
               <p>In England these demonstrations of contempt would be suspected, and would be 
ridiculous: and even in Italy Mr. Foscolo has been justly charged with pushing them to an unjust 
exposure of men who were the most disposed to be his literary friends and admirers. He published 
nearly 300 pages in large octavo, upon the translated elegy of Catullus, <title>
                     <foreign lang="lat">De Coma Berenices</foreign>
                  </title>: the whole lucubration being a grave and 
continued irony on the verbal criticisms of the commentators. Some of the learned fell into the 
snare; and Foscolo, who had issued only a few copies, now added a <emph>Farewell</emph> to 
his readers, in which he repays their praises by exposing the mysteries and the abuses of the 
philological art. Those whom he had deceived must have been not a little irritated to find that his 
frequent citations were invented for the occasion, and that his commentary had been purposely 
sprinkled with many of the grossest faults. Neither the merit nor the success of such a pleasantry 
can be intelligible to an English reader: but it should be told that Foscolo, with the same patriotism 
which seems the devouring passion of his soul, contrived this deception partly to warn the 
commentators that it was their duty also, as well as that of other writers, to devote themselves to the 
excitement of generous sentiments in the bosom of their countrymen.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See — <foreign lang="ita">
                           <title>La Chioma di Berenice</title>, Milano, 
1803</foreign>. <title>
                           <foreign lang="fra">La Bibliothèque Italienne</foreign>
                        </title>, a French 
review, published at Turin, and <title>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Il Diario Italiano</foreign>
                        </title> for 
November and December of the same year.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Foscolo is an excellent scholar: his knowledge of Greek is far superior to that of many 
of his most distinguished fellowcountrymen: he writes Latin with facility and elegance. A little 
book in that language, called <title>
                     <foreign lang="lat">Didymi Clerici Prophetae Minimi 
Hypercalypseos, liber singularis</foreign>
                  </title>, has been attributed, and, it is believed, justly, to 
his pen. It appears to be a satire against the journalists, the learned pensioners of the court, the 
Royal Institute, and the senate of the kindom of Italy; but it is an enigma from beginning to end to 
any one not furnished with the key of the individual allusions. This obscurity shewed at least, that 
he did not care to engage the multitude on his side, and that he was indifferent as to the dispersion 
of his own feelings of contempt for the men of letters of the Italian court.</p>
               <p>The lady whose opinions have been before quoted, talks of the literary intolerance of 
Foscolo as the offspring of his reflection, not of his disposition. “A warm friend, but sincere 
as the mirror itself, that neither deceives nor conceals. Kind, generous, grateful; his virtues appear 
those of savage nature, when seen in the midst of the sophisticated reasoners of our days. He would 
tear his heart from his bosom, if he thought that a single pulsation was not the unconstrained and 
free movement of his soul”.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <foreign lang="ita">Intollerante più per riflessione che per natura: amico fervido; ma sincero 
come lo specchio, che non inganna, nè illude. Pietoso, generoso, riconoscente, pare un selvaggio in 
mezzo a' filosofi de' nostri dì. Si strapperebbe il cuore dal petto se liberi non gli paressero i risalti 
tutti del suo cuore</foreign>. See — <foreign lang="ita">
                           <title>Ritratti</title> scritti dalla 
Contessa ISABELLA ALBRIZZI</foreign>.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Although Foscolo had studies under Cesarotti, and had been encouraged by the voice of 
that generous master, he loudly disapproved of the translation of Homer, and more decidedly still of 
the <title>Pronéa</title>. He was a long time nearly connected with Monti, who frequently 
mentions him with applause; and, in his illustrations of Persius, foretells that his young friend will, 
one day or the other, be the first poet of the age. In the last years of the French government, an 
intimacy with Foscolo was not favourable to court promotion. Monti and the future Corypheus of 
the poets became cool to each other, and would not willingly meet in the same society; but either 
reciprocal fear, or the memory of their ancient alliance has not allowed any written attack from 
either adversary. An Englishman wished, when at the Scala theatre at Milan in 1816, to give the 
Death of Ortis as a subject for an improvisatore; but a friend said to him, “It will not be 
chosen: Monti is behind the scenes, and will hear nothing said in favour of Ortis or of 
Foscolo”. The same influence, joined to that of the police, was pronounced fatal also to the 
<title>Apotheosis</title> of Alfieri.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>See note to Stanza LIV, of <title>Childe Harold</title>, Canto IV, page 152.</p>
                  </note>

 There is a story current respecting the last interview of these two poets, which may illustrate and 
contrast the character of both. They were dining at they house of Count Veneri, minister of the 
public treasury: Monti, as usual, launched out against Alfieri, according to the court tone of the day: 
“All his works together”, said he, “are not worth a song of Metastasio” 
“Stop there, Sir”, interrupted Foscolo, “or I will twirl round you and your 
party as well as ever top was whipped by a school–boy”. As far as respects his other 
great cotemporaries, he has never spoken of Pindemonte but with esteem, nor ever names Alfieri 
without admiration. The instructions he received from Parini have mingled a tender recollection 
with the I reverence with which he dwells upon his character, in the letters of Ortis.</p>
               <p>In spite of his opposition to the French, and of his repeated declaration, that the 
representative rights belong only to the landed proprietors, it is easy to discern that Foscolo is a 
pupil of the Revolution. In truth, he imputes the misfortunes of Italy to the cowardice, the 
ignorance, and the egotism of the nobles. He owes his popularity rather to his conduct than to his 
maxims, or even to his works; for the first are not qualified to obtain the favour of the majority, and 
the second are above the common class of readers.</p>
               <p>The admirers of Napoleon may behold in this author a rebellious subject, but a sincere 
eulogist wherever he has thought fit to praise. The truth is, that Napoleon conferred upon Italy all 
the benefit that a country divided and enslaved could possibly expect from a conqueror. To him she 
owed her union; to him, her laws and her arms: her new activity, and her recovered martial spirit 
were inspired by his system. But Foscolo was a citizen of the Venetian republic which Napoleon 
destroyed, and there exist in Italy a very numerous class, who consider the independence of their 
country as the first indispensable step towards her regeneration. Foscolo, as well as some others, 
who, when the Italian republic was degraded into a subsidiary kingdom, were named amongst the 
electoral colleges, contrived never to attend, because he would not take the oath of allegiance. But 
he did not find it impossible to live under the dominion of the French. The Austrians in their turn 
required from him personally an oath of fidelity to their Emperor. Foscolo refused to them what he 
would not grant to Napoleon. But he could not breathe under their depressive system. He became a 
voluntary exile, and his adieus to his countrymen are couched in the language of proud resignation. 
“Let not the minister of the Austrian police continue to persecute me in my Swiss asylum; 
tell him that I am far from wishing to excite the hopeless passions of my fellow citizens. We were in 
want of arms; they were given to us by France, and Italy had again a name amongst the nations. In 
the access of our inflammatory fever, the loss of blood could not harm us, and the death of a single 
man would have inevitably produced changes favourable to all the nations who should have courage 
to profity by the happy juncture. But it was ordained otherwise: the affairs of the world have been 
turned into another and an unexpected channel. The actual disease of Italy is a slow lethargic 
consumption, she will soon be nothing but a lifeless carcass; and her generous sons should only 
weep in silence, without the impotent complaints and the mutual recriminations of slaves”.

<note place="foot">
                     <p>
                        <foreign lang="ita">Senza querele impotenti, nè recriminazioni da servi</foreign>. This was 
inserted in the <title>Lugano Gazette</title>, for April 14, 1815, in an article written to answer a 
book with the title <title>
                           <foreign lang="ita">Memoria storica della Rivoluzione di 
Milano</foreign>
                        </title>, <foreign lang="ita">seguìta il 20 Aprile 1814, Parigi, 1815</foreign>. 
Published by some senators of the kingdom of Italy.</p>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 n="Conclusion">
               <head>CONCLUSION</head>
               <p>It is hoped that the preceding pages may have furnished a general notion of the state of 
literature in Italy during the last fifty years. More extensive limits would have comprised more 
copious extracts from the cited authors, would have noticed other writers, and would have included 
not only a view of the education of the Italians, but of their style and taste, and present productions 
in all the branches of literature; little indeed has been done in comparison of what remains to do, but 
on the reception of what has been already offered will depend whether anything more shall be 
attempted. A great question at this moment divides the learned world in Italy into the partisans of 
classical poetry, and of the poetry of romance. The first, of course, range Homer in the front of the 
battle; and the others, who have adopted the division of Madame de Stael, and talk of a literature of 
the North, and a literature of the South, have still the courage to depend upon <title>Ossian</title> 
for their principal champion. The first would adhere solely to the mythology of the ancients; the 
other party would banish it totally from all their compositions. It would not be very difficult to state 
the true merits of this idle enquiry, on the decision of which may, however, depend the turn taken 
by the literature of the next half century. But this also must be left for another opportunity. In the 
mean time it may be allowed to mention, that the Italians themselves are far from ungrateful to 
those foreigners, especially the English, who evince a desire to be acquainted with their literature: 
but that they are for the most part surprised at our original misconceptions, and do not a little 
complain of the false impressions communicated by the ignorance of those, even amongst their 
expatriated countrymen, who have presumed to be our instructors.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
