<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://backend.bibliotecaitaliana.it/DTD/bibit.dtd">
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Studi su Dante pubblicati sulla Edinburgh Review</title>
            <author>Ugo Foscolo</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>233000 Kb in UTF-8</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Biblioteca Italiana</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace>
            <date>2008</date>
            <idno>bibit000574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>Questa risorsa digitale è liberamente accessibile per uso
                        personale o scientifico. Ogni uso commerciale è vietato</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Collezione BibIt</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Studi su dante</title>
               <title type="part">v.</title>
               <author>Foscolo, Ugo</author>
               <editor id="ed">Da Pozzo, Giovanni</editor>
               <publisher>F. Le Monnier</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Firenze</pubPlace>
               <date>1979</date>
               
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Tutti i materiali paratestuali della fonte cartacea non riconducibili alla
                responsabilità dell'autore dell'opera sono stati soppressi nella versione
                digitale</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction method="silent" status="medium">
               <p>Livello medio: controllo a video con collazione con edizione di
                        riferimento</p>
            </correction>
            <quotation form="data" marks="all">
               <p>I simboli di citazione e di discorso diretto presenti sulla fonte cartacea
                        sono stati rappresentati sulla versione digitale</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>I trattini di sillabazione a fine riga sono stati soppressi e le parole
                        ricomposte</p>
            </hyphenation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="CGB">
               <bibl>Classificazione generi BibIt</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date>800</date>
         </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="eng"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="CGB">
               <term>Trattati</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06-08T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Novadata systems</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Digitalizzazione - OCR</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11-28T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Correzione linguistica</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12-28T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura Sarzi Braga</name>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Codifica XML - Codifica manuale</item>
         </change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02-07T00:00:00.000+02:00</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Carla Deiana</name>
               <name>BIBIT</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>Validazione</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 n="Articolo I">
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="sc">ART.</hi> IX. <title>Dante, with a new Italian
                        Commentary</title>, By <hi rend="sc">G. BAGLIOLI</hi>, Paris, 1818.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>The Vision of Dante</title>, translated by the Reverend <hi rend="sc">H. F. CARY, A. M.</hi>, vol. 18mo, London, 1818.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>M. Baglioli's new work on Dante was announced, in 1816, by subscription, in large
                    quarto, with magnificent paper and characters. The subscription was, it seems,
                    not encouraging; and, after two years expectation, the author has published his
                    work in a more modest form; which, indeed, we think the most fair, as well as
                    the most prudent part. If the book be good, it will be useful to a greater
                    number of readers. If it be bad, the buyers will have less cost to regret.
                    Authors now seem desirous of placing their works under the protection of
                    splendid printing, and to have the hope of being immortalized at least by the
                    continuators of Mr. Dibdin's <title>Decameron</title>.</p>
            <p>M. Baglioli's Dante will form three volumes in large octavo, of which the first
                    is not yet completely printed; but we have now before us nine sheets of it,
                    which contain the text of eight books of the <title lang="ita">Inferno</title>,
                    with the Commentary. This is not enough, perhaps, for a complete criticism of
                    the work; but it sufficiently shows his method, and enables us to determine,
                    that, if he has improved, he has not fundamentally changed the plan of his
                    predecessors. This leads us to give a rapid sketch of the history of the
                    commentators on Dante, and to inquire into the causes of the very little service
                    which they have done to the, poet or the reader. Perhaps our observations may
                    suggest a new method of undertaking, with more advantage, a work which we tahink
                    necessary; not only to Itafy, but to other nations; because it is in the age of
                    Dante, and principally from the influence of his genius, that we may date the
                    commencement of the literary history of Europe.</p>
            <p>The poem of Dante is like an immense forest, venerable for its antiquity, and
                    astonishing by the growth of trees which seem to have sprung up at once to their
                    gigantic height by the force of nature, aided <emph>by some unknown art</emph>.
                    It is a forest, curious from the extensive regions which it hides, but frightful
                    from its darkness and its labyrinths. The first trave llers who attempted to
                    cross it have opened a road. Those who followed have enlarged and enlightened
                    it; but the road is still the same; and the greater part of this immense forest
                    remains, after the labours of five centuries, involved in its primitive
                    darkness. Readers, especially foreing readers, believe, on the faith of the
                    commentators, that they have seen the whole; like the readers of modern travels,
                    who fancy that they know a country from the descriptions of those who have run
                    through it with a roadbook and a dictionary, and return home to publish their
                    tour.</p>
            <p>It is said by Warburton in his Preface to Shakespeare, that the whole a critic
                    can do for an author who deserves his services, is to correct the faulty text,
                    to remark the peculiarities of language, to illustrate the obscure allusions,
                    and to explain <quote>‘the beauties an defects of sentiment or
                        composition.’</quote> Perhaps we may prove, in the sequel, that
                    this observation cannot be universally adopted; — but if it were
                    sufficient in the case of all other poets, it is certain, that, by the most
                    complete and suocessful application of it to the poem of Dante, a critic would
                    perform only half his task. The first part which relates to the emendation of
                    the text, has been happily enough executed in the native city of the poet, by
                    the Academy della Crusca. That learned body, occupied in studying and purifying
                    their language, naturally sought for its radical treasures in the age of Dante,
                    Petrarca, and Boccaccio. These academicians were almost all Florentines, and had
                    abundant means of collecting various readings. The numerous libraries of
                    Florence were supplied with <hi rend="sc">MSS.</hi> of Dante's poem, of which
                    they collated more than a hundred with the early editions. These various
                    readings were discussed by them for the common interest — for the
                    honour of the poet, the language, and the academy; by which means they avoided
                    the obstinacy, the acrimony, and the puerile quarrels which the jealousy of
                    individuals has spread among the commentators of Homer and Shakespeare. They
                    thus spared the time of their readers, and saved literature from some ridicule.
                    This academy was not always so wise. They dishonoured themselves in their
                    hostility against Tasso. But in that case they were ambitious of giving laws to
                    genius; a task for which an assembly of men is peculiarly unfitted. In their
                    emendations of Dante, on the contrary, they needed only a calm and attentive
                    examination, a free discussion, and a mature deliberation on questions purely
                    verbal and grammatical. Academies are in general useful, where the object is
                    only to arrange and preserve the stock of human knowledge. It can be increased
                    only by men of genius — independent of rules and associations, and
                    fearlessly pursuing glory at their own peril. But societies bound by
                    institutions, often obliged to respect and sometimes to flatter governments and
                    powerful individuals, can never display independence of mind, or possess the
                    courage necessary for the exertion of genius. They may, under despotic
                    governments, become instruments in the hands of tyrants for repressing the
                    progress of mind, and narrowing the diffusion of knowledge.</p>
            <p>But to return to Dante. The Academy della Crusca have admitted the best of the
                    various readings into their text, and have placed in the margin all that are
                    probable. Their edition is known by the date of 1595.<note place="foot">
                  <p>It is not improper to inform the general reader, that this edition is
                            disgraced by typographical errors of every sort. It should be left to
                            critics, who are not perplexed by its blunders; and to collectors, who
                            sometimes prefer editions for the celebrity of their mistakes.</p>
               </note> This edition has always been regarded with a sort of veneration; and the
                    best reprints of it are that of Padua by Comino in 1627, and that of Leghorn in
                    1807, by Gaetano Poggiali. Of this last, which is printed with exactness and
                    elegance, and which contains a judicious selection of various readings, we have
                    seen two volumes of text, and a third of notes on the <title lang="ita">Inferno</title>. Whether he has published those on the other parts of the poem,
                    we know not.</p>
            <p>Padre Lombardi having examined an ancient milanese edition of 1478 called the
                        <title lang="ita">Nidobeatina</title>, found in almost every page various
                    readings, which sometimes illustrate, and sometimes embellish the verses, and
                    which he has introduced into his edition, published at Rome in three volumes
                    quarto. But his þartiality to his favourite edition is excessive, and sometimes
                    offensive to men of taste. He openly attacks the Academy of Florence; and he has
                    provoked the pedants. His work is, on the whole, very curious and useful to
                    those who amuse themselves with philology, and who are scrupulous in the choice
                    of words. His principal antagoníst is Monsignor Dionisi, canon of Verona, who
                    has attacked him with the animosity of a verbal critio, with the dogmatic tone
                    of a prelate, and the contemptuous air of·a patrician. Dionisi declares war
                    against the Nidobeatina edition, and all other ancient and modern editions of
                    Dante, without excepting even that of the Academy della Crusca. He has examined
                    many manuscripts unknown to former editors; but he has unfortunately introduced
                    the most manifest errors of copyists into his own text as newly discovered
                    beauties. After having injured Dante as much as Bentley did Milton, he caused
                    his edition to be splendidly printed by Bodoni, which, indeed, insures the
                    purchase of the book by collectors, but has rendered the author magnificently
                    ridiculous.</p>
            <p>So much for the history of emendatory criticism on Dante. As to the second part
                    of Warburton's suggestion, <quote>‘to remark the peculiarities of
                        language,’</quote> the ancient editors, from the sons of Dante,
                    who were the first to illustrate the poem of their father, till the edition of
                    the Crusca, did not consider such remarks as necessary. The Academy did much;
                    but their remarks on the phraseology of Dante are scattered over their
                    voluminous <title>Dictionary</title>. Volpi collected all the peculiar words and
                    phrases of Dante in an <title>Index</title>, with such words and phrases of
                    modern Italian as he thought equivalent, but without observation. Lombardi has
                    done more than all the rest; but his grammatical notes are more founded on
                    rules, than on the genius of the language, though the poem was written two
                    hundred years before the earliest Italian grammar. Volumes might be formed of
                    the various works of literature, the discussions, the conjectures, the long
                    dissertations, which in the last three centuries have been written on words and
                    phrases of Dante, but they are dispersed, either in perishable pamphlets, or in
                    folies buried in libraries.</p>
            <p>The third part of the editor's duty, <quote>‘to illustrate the obscure
                        allusions,’</quote> has been executed with more care than success.
                    All the other great poems in the world, taken together, have, perhaps, not so
                    many allusions as the single work of Dante. He comprehends the whole history of
                    his age — all that was then known of art, literature, and science
                    — the usages and morals of his time, and their origin in preceding
                    ages — together with theological opinions, and the great influence
                    which they then exercised over the mind and actions of men. His allusions are
                    rapid, various, multiplied — succeeding each other with the rapidity
                    of flashes of lightning, which leaves short intervals of darkness between them.
                    He describes all human passions — all actions — the vices
                    and the virtues of tlie most different scenes. He places them in the despair of
                    hell — in the hope of purgatory — and in the blessedness of
                    paradise. He observes men in youth — in manhood — and in old
                    age. He has brought together those of both sexes — of all religions
                    — of all occupations — of all nations — and of all
                    ages; yet he never takes them in masses — he always presents them as
                    individuals. He speaks to every one of them — he studies their words
                    — he watches their countenances. He often paints a great character by
                    his inaction. Sordello, who had led a very active life, and who, after having
                    made every effort for his country, died despairing of the fate of Italy, is met
                    by Dante in purgatory. While a crowd of ghosts, curious about the affairs of the
                    world, followed the poet to learn news from him, Sordello kept aloof.</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Esso non ne diceva alcuna cosa</l>
                  <l>Ma lasciavane andar, sempre guardando</l>
                  <l>A guisa di leon quando si posa.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>— <bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Purg.</title>, <emph>Canto VI</emph>,
                        64.</bibl>
               <note place="foot">
                  <quote rend="block">
                     <lg>
                        <l>‘Scarce moving with slow dignity his eyes,</l>
                        <l>He spoke not aught, but let us onward pass,</l>
                        <l>Eying us as a lion on his watch’.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <p>— <bibl>
                        <title>Cary's Dante</title>, II, 24.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Let it be remarked, that he has not before named Sordello. He gives no reason for
                    his disdainful silence; and he leaves his reader to discover in the chronicles
                    what we have said on the character of this illustrious personage. The poet
                    condenses into three lines, and often into one, the history of a prince's life.
                    In speaking of St. Celestino, who refused the papacy at the suggestion of
                    Boniface VIII, his successor, he describes him without mention of his name.</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Colui</l>
                  <l>Che fece per viltate il gran rifiuto’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Infern.</title>, <hi rend="italic">Cant.</hi> III, 60.</bibl>
               <note place="foot">
                  <quote>
                     <lg>
                        <l>‘I Saw</l>
                        <l>And knew the shade of him, who to base fear</l>
                        <l>Yielding, abjured his estate’.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Cary's Dante</title>, I, 11.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>In the twentieth Canto of the <title lang="ita">Purgatorio</title>, he traces the
                    genealogy of the Capets, their acts and crimes; the influence of the Kings of
                    France on the church and on Italy, from Hugh Capet to Louis, X — and
                    this history, comprehending a period of 347 years, is contained in fifty lines.
                    Dante was declared enemy of all the Capets; and he finishes by invoking the
                    vengeance of God on their heads.</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Oh Signor mio quando sarò io lieto</l>
                  <l>A veder la vendetta che nascosa</l>
                  <l>Fa dolce l'ira tua nel tuo secreto’.<note place="foot">
                        <quote>
                           <lg>
                              <l>‘O Sovran Master, when shall I rejoice</l>
                              <l>To see the vengeance which thy wrath well pleased</l>
                              <l>In secret silence broods’.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </quote>
                        <p>— <bibl>
                              <title>Cary's Dante</title>, II, 92.</bibl>
                        </p>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>In this last verse we find a sentiment as old as Homer, who tells us, that
                        <quote>‘vengeance is the pleasure of the gods,’ <seg type="inciso">and that</seg> ‘a great king digests his wrath
                        in his inmost parts, and hides it till the appointed time of its bursting on
                        the enemy.’</quote>
               <note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <quote lang="grc">Κρείσσων
                                γὰρ
                                βασιλεὸς
                                ὅτε
                                χώσεται
                                ἀνδρὶ
                                χέρηϊ·
                                Εἴπερ
                                γὰρ τε
                                χόλον τε
                                καὶ
                                αὐτῆμαρ
                                καταπέψῃ
                                Ἀλλά γε
                                καὶ
                                μετόπισθεν.
                                ὲχει
                                κότον
                                ὄφρα,
                                τελέσσῃ
                                Ἐν
                                στήθεσσιngr;
                                ἑοῖσι.</quote>
                            — <bibl>
                        <title>Iliad.</title> A, 80, <hi rend="italic">et
                                    seqq.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
               </note> Tacitus thus describes feelings somewhat similar. <quote lang="lat">‘Infensus memoria — et adversum eludentes se quisque
                        ultione et sanguine explebant.’</quote> —
                            <bibl>
                  <title>Ann. IV</title>. 25</bibl>. Homer makes a reflection on
                    human nature. Tacitus blends the same sentiment with the narrative of a fact, by
                    the three words <quote lang="lat">‘Memoria, Ultione,
                        Explebant.’</quote> In Dante, it is the passionate exclamation of
                    a man who has long brooded over his own indignation.</p>
            <p>Shakespeare unfolds the character of his persons, and presents them under all the
                    variety of forms which they can naturally assume. He surrounds them with all the
                    splendour of his imagination, and liestows on them that full and minute reality
                    which his creative genius could alone confer. Of all tragic poets, he most amply
                    develops character. On the other hand, Dante, if compared not only to Virgil,
                    the most sober of poets, but even to Tacitus, will be found never to employ more
                    than a stroke or two of his pencil, which he aims at imprinting almost
                    insensibly on the hearts of his readers. Virgil has related the story of
                    Eurydice in two hundred verses; Dante, in sixty verses, has fmished his
                    masterpiece — the Tale of Francesca da Rimini. The history of
                    Desdemona has a parallel in the following passage of Dante. Nello della Pietra
                    had espoused a lady of noble family at Sienna, named Madonna Pia. Her beauty was
                    the admiration of Tuscany, and excited in the heart of her husband a jealousy,
                    which, exasperated by false reports and groundless suspicions, at length drove
                    him to the desperate resolution of Othello. It is difficult to decide whether
                    the lady was quite innocent; but so Dante represents her. Her husband brought
                    her into the Maremma, which, then as now, was a district destructive to health.
                    He never told his unfortunate wife the reason of her banishment to so dangerous
                    a country. He did not deign to utter complaint or accusation. He lived with her
                    alone, in cold silence, without answering her questions, or listening to her
                    remonstrances. He patiently waited till the pestilential air should destroy the
                    health of this young lady. In a few months she died. Some chroniclers, indeed,
                    tell us, that Nello used the dagger to hasten her death. It is certain that the
                    survived her, plunged in sadness and perpetual silence. Dante had, in this
                    incident, all the materials of an ample and very poetical narrative. But he
                    bestows on it only four verses. He meets in <title>Purgatory</title> three
                    spirits; one was a captain who fell fighting on the same side with him in the
                    battle of Campaldino; the second, a gentleman assassinated by the treachery of
                    the House of Este; the third was a woman unknown to the poet, and who, after the
                    others had spoken, turned towards him with these words:</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Ricorditi di me, che son la Pia;</l>
                  <l>Siena mi fe, disfecemi Maremma.</l>
                  <l>Salsi colui che inanellata pria</l>
                  <l>Disposando m'avea con la sua gemma’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Purgat.</title>, <hi rend="italic">Cant. V, et ult.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <note place="foot">
                  <quote>
                     <lg>
                        <l>‘Ah, when thou to the world shalt be returned</l>
                        <l>Remember me.</l>
                        <l>I once was Pia. Sienna gave me life;</l>
                        <l>Maremma took it from me. That he knows!</l>
                        <l>Who me with jewelled ring had first espoused’.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Cary's Dante</title>, II, 22.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Yet these few words draw tears from those who know the fate of this young woman.
                    Her first desire to be recalled to the remembrance of her friends on earth is
                    very affecting. Her modest requeet, her manner of naming herself, and of
                    describing the author of her sufferings, without any allusion to his crime, and
                    merely by the pledges of faith and love which attended their first union, are
                    deeply pathetic. The soft harmony of the last verses, full of gay and tender
                    remembrances, forms a most striking contrast with the ideas of domestic
                    unhappiness, of death and of cruelty, which must rise in the reader's
                    imagination.</p>
            <p>He has not treated every subject so laconically. In the history of Count Ugolino,
                    and in that of Francesca da Rimini, he paints on a larger scale. There are,
                    perhaps, in the poem, thirty passages of equal energy and extent. But he
                    generally compresses his narration in the manner which we have pointed out. He
                    often speaks of anecdotes, of men and of crimes not mentioned by any
                    contemporary writer; and it is for these reasons that a commentary on his
                    allusions would have been impracticable, if, fortunately for us, it had not been
                    commenced soon after his death.</p>
            <p>He died in 1321; and, in 1334, we find mention made of a commentary by his sons
                    Peter and James, and another anonymous writer. In 1350, Visconti, Archbishop of
                    Milan, formed a commission of six scholars, namely, two philosophers, two
                    theologians, and two florentine men of letters, to compose a commentary on
                    Dante, which they completed. Petrarch, also, is said to have written
                    commentaries on his great predecessor: but of this there seems no evidence. In
                    1373, the republic of Florence elected Boccaccio to explain Dante to his
                    fellow–citizens. He delivered lectures on this subject, in which he
                    poured forth the knowledge which he had accumulated during a long life. His
                    digressions are fine and instructive; his style more sober than in his more
                    known works, without losing the richness and elegance which distinguish him. But
                    he died before he had expounded above a third of the <title lang="ita">Inferno</title>. Florence continued to nominate professors; and her example was
                    imitated by other cities. The Latin commentary of Benvenuto of Imola, who
                    lectured on Dante at Bologna in 1375, is rich in historical anecdotes. The
                    greater part of these numerous commentaries remain unpublished in the libraries
                    of Italy; and only a part of Benvenuto of Imola has been published by Muratori
                    in his <title>Italian antiquities</title>. All these inedited commentaries
                    supplied the editors of the next age with the means of explaining allusions,
                    which, our readers will be pleased to recollect, is the only point of view under
                    which we at present consider the history of the commentators on Dante.</p>
            <p>Among the fathers of the council of Constance, were two English prelates,
                    Nicholas, Bishop of Bath, and Robert, Bishop of Salisbury, who, with Cardinal
                    Amadeo de Saluces, requested John de Saravalla, Prince Bishop of Fermo, to
                    explain Dante to them. He translated the poem into Latin prose, and subjoined
                    notes. We learn, from the Dedication, that he began his work on the Ist February
                    1416, and fmished it in a year and a fortnight. It has never been printed; but,
                    a few years ago, a manuscript copy was extant in the Vatican library; and we
                    mention it only to remark, that, at the time of the Council of Trent, Dante was
                    a writer, of whom no Bishop would dare to avow that he was the commentator. We
                    subjoin a passage from this manuscript, <note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <quote lang="lat">‘Dantes dilexit Theologiam sacram in qua diu
                                studuit in Oxoniis in Regno Angliæ’</quote>. In the next
                            page, he says, <quote lang="lat">‘Dantes in juventute sese
                                dedit omnibus artibus liberalibus, studens eas et Padue, et Bononie,
                                demum Oxoniis et Parisiis, ubi fecit multos actus mirabiles in
                                tantum quod ab aliquibus dicebatur magnus Philosophus, ab aliquibus
                                magnus Theologus, ab aliquibus magnus Poeta’</quote>. It
                            is probable that the Italian Bishop received this information, true or
                            false, from his English brethren, especially as the conclusion of the
                            above passage has much the air of a literal translation from an English
                            original.</p>
               </note>, from which it should seem, that Dante had come to Oxford to pursue his
                    studies in that celebrated school. But we must add, that the Bishop lived more
                    than a century after the Poet, and that he is the only writer who speaks of this
                    journey to England.</p>
            <p>Christopher Landinus, a commentator on Virgil, published also commentaries on
                    Dante. He lived near the time of the discovery of printing, when verbal
                    criticism became a separate study. He was a man of great erudition, who has
                    multiplied quotations, expanded the too diffuse commentaries of his forerunners,
                    and expatiated on the allegories, the theological opinions and the scholastic
                    philosophy of the Poet; but, like his successor in the next age, Alexander
                    Velutello, has done nothing to illustrate the poetical beauties. These
                    commentators have been little read since their own time. About the beginning of
                    the sixteenth century, the popularity of Dante underwent some fluctuations. The
                    exclusive taste for Grecian and Roman literature which flourished under Leo X,
                    disposed the critics of that period to look down upon Dante as an irregular and
                    barbarous writer. Boccaccio and Petrarca had become the sole models of Italian
                    composition — <quote>for taste had already been tainted by
                        effeminacy</quote>.<note place="foot">
                  <p>See Sperone Speroni's <title>Funeral Oration on Bembo</title>.</p>
               </note> The <title lang="ita">Orlando Inamorato</title> and the <title lang="ita">Orlando Furïoso</title> amused more, and fatigued less.
                    The reformation had set Europe on fire, and Dante had dared to condemn even
                    Popes to Hell. In ‘the <title>Paradise</title>,’ St Peter
                    himself utters a sublime invective against the temporal power of the church. In
                    a Latin work on monarchy, the Poet had maintained the superiority of the
                    Emperors over the Popes; and Protestant writers .quoted his authority as
                        <quote>‘one of the Witnesses of the Truth’</quote>.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Bayle, Art. Dante.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Towards 1550, the Jesuits possessed themselves of the education of Italy; and
                    they systematically decried a writer likely to produce effects on the opinions
                    and on the character of youth so irreconcileable with their policy. Three men of
                    genius, however, even at that time, professed their admiration of him. The first
                    was Sperone Speroni, a writer now little read, but considered in his own time as
                    the oracle of philosophy and literature, and still deserving to be regarded as a
                    model of vigour and elegance in Italian prose. Michael Angelo had filled a copy
                    of Dante with drawings, which he lost in a sea voyage.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Vasari, VI, 245.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note> Torquato Tasso being asked who was the greatest poet of Italy, answered
                            <quote>‘<hi rend="italic">Dante</hi>’</quote>.<note place="foot">
                  <p>Serassi, in the second edition of the <title>Life of Tasso</title>,
                            mentions a copy of Giolito's edition of Dante, of which the margins were
                            filled with remarks on the style of the poem in the handwriting of
                            Tasso.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>From 1600 to 1730, Dante had no commentators, and few editions.<note place="foot">
                  <p>From 1473 to the edition of La Crusca, Haim enumerates 44 editions. From
                            1598 to the edition of Volpi in 1727, he only mentions 5. This
                            enumeration must be understood to refer only to rare or important
                            editions; for about 1620, Francesco Cionacci, a noble Florentine,
                            published a catalogue of 452 editions extant in his time. Since the
                            Revolution, editions of Dante have succeeded each other with astonishing
                            rapidity.</p>
               </note> The Spanish government, and the ascendancy of monks, had enervated the
                    national mind; while the popular taste was corrupted by the poetry which then
                    reigned in Spain. Dante, of whom no edition had been allowed at Rome till the
                    middle of the eighteenth century, could at such a period hope for no toleration.
                    It may be observed, that during the same time Machiavel had few editions. The
                    bad taste of the writers called in Italy Seicentisti, began indeed to be
                    purified towards the conclusion of this period; but, from the quaintness and
                    extravagance of Marini, the reformers of literature ran to the opposite extreme
                    of a slavish subjection to rules, either arbitrary or at most of a secondary
                    importance. They wrote as if only to avoid faults; and the nation, broken down
                    by every species of slavery, no longer had the faculty of admiring the free and
                    daring exertion of sublime genius. The Jesuits were indefatigable in their
                    hostility to Dante. Venturi, who made an useful abridgement of the most
                    necessary explanatory notes, accompanied it by critical remarks; in which,
                    agreeably to the maxims of his order, he labours to exaggerate the faults, and
                    to detect the impiety of the poet. Bettinelli in his <title>Virgilian
                    Letters</title>, an ingenious but tasteless book, ridicules Dante as the most
                    barbarous of poets. Tiraboschi, who was also a Jesuit, examines the life of
                    Petrarch with great historical exactness, expatiates with zeal and at length on
                    his merit; and contents himself with a few dates and some very vague criticism
                    on Dante. The same historian who bestows twenty pages on the Jesuit Possevino,
                    employs only four on the private and publio life, on the opinions and works of
                    Machiavel.</p>
            <p>It was after the fall of the Jesuits that Lombardi, airanciscan, incensed at
                    their malignity and false taste, ventured to undertake his commentary on Dante.
                    He was of the same order with Ganganelli, the pope who suppressed the Jesuits.
                    But it was more easy to suppress than to extinguish the literary and religious
                    prejudices which they had established in Italy. Pius VI, then employed in the
                    defence of the doctrines of the see of Rome against Joseph II, Leopold in
                    Tuscany, and against the Jansenism which predominated in the universities both
                    of Tuscany and Lombardy, was not favourable to an antipapal poet. Lombardi might
                    have observed the accomplishment of his author's prophecy —</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Giunta è la Spada</l>
                  <l>Col Pasturale, e l'uno e l'altro insieme</l>
                  <l>Per viva forza mal convien che vada’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Purgat.</title>, <hi rend="italic">XVI</hi>, 119.</bibl>
               <note place="foot">
                  <quote>
                     <lg>
                        <l>‘the sword</l>
                        <l>Is grafted on the crook; and, so conjoined,</l>
                        <l>Each must perforce decline to worse, unaw'd</l>
                        <l>By fear of other’.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Cary's Dante</title>, II, 73.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>But he did not even venture to put his name in the title–page. He
                    ventures only on his initials, with a vignette, exhibiting a portrait of Dante
                    with a somewhat obscure inscription, intimating that he also was in danger from
                    the power which had trampled on Kings and Emperors. We know none of the
                    circumstances of his life which could throw light on this intimation. But it is
                    certain that his friend Angelucci who appeared as the editor of his work, was
                    imprisoned in 1794 for his political opinions.</p>
            <p>In these circumstances we must not wonder at the circumspection with which he
                    conducts that part of his plan which consists in the defence of Dante. We have
                    already spoken of his emendations amÍ grammatical remarks. His explanations are
                    clear and sometimes new, though he does not often venture to quit the beaten
                    track. He had not sufficient taste and sensibility to discern the delicacy, or
                    to feel the tenderness of the historical allusions. The prose of his notes is
                    dry, and, though concise, the want of elegance makes it appear diffuse. After
                    all, it is the most useful historical commentary yet printed on Dante.</p>
            <p>Volpi was a learned man; but Italian was not his principal study. Mr Poggiali has
                    studied it more deeply. The brevity adopted by both, in their excellent editions
                    of Padua and Leghorn, has left no room for narrative commentary —
                    indispensable to the illustration of a poem in which the anecdotes of an obscure
                    age are accumulated, and often only hinted at.</p>
            <p>On the last head of Warburton's description of the critical office —
                    that of explaining ‘the beauties and defects of sentiment and
                    composition — we must at once say, that, in truth, nothing has been
                    done. It is indeed a task, of which the due, or even tolerable execution
                    requires, in the case of Dante, a combination of talents which can hardly be
                    united in the same individual. He who undertakes this part of criticism has two
                    duties to fulfil. The first, and by far the most easy, relates to the general
                    plan of a work — its end, the style, the progress which the language
                    makes under the author — his original inventions and imitations
                    — the degree in which he has improved on his models, or fallen short
                    of them — and the instruction or amusement which he has imparted to
                    his contemporaries or posterity. The second is far more difficult, and, in its
                    utmost extent, impracticable. It consists in a minute exposition of all the
                    separate beauties and defects of a poem, from page to page, often from verse to
                    verse, and sometimes from word to word. The critic must display beauties, so
                    that they shall be felt by those who did not feel them in the poet; and he must
                    explain the causes of pleasure to those who are delighted without knowing how.
                    Minute and argumentative as this analysis may often be, its object would be
                    defeated if it were to extinguish the fire of poetry; and the reader, in
                    reasoning with the critic, must never cease to feel with the poet.</p>
            <p>A critic may attempt, like the celebrated Gravina, to prove that the <title lang="ita">Italia Liberata</title> of Trissino is the finest epic poem since
                    the <title>Iliad</title>; and that the <title lang="ita">Giuresalemme
                    Liberata</title> of Tasso is neither well imagined nor well written. The book of
                    Gravina is a fine exertion of talent. It is written with elegance. His
                    principles are just, his applications happy; and, as long as he confines himself
                    to the analysis of the general plan of celebrated epic poems, he appears to
                    succeed. But, when all is done, the poem of Trissino reposes in libraries; and
                    the reader, whose curiosity leads him to read a page, coldly shuts and replaces
                    the volume. Tasso is reprinted every year. He is always indeed criticized; but
                    he is always read. It is by the examination of particular beauties, continual,
                    varied, inexhaustible, which lead the reader on from page to page, which flow
                    into his heart, and are treasured in his memory, that the merit of the greatest
                    poets must be measured. It is by such beauties that Ariosto compels his reader
                    to go on in spite of inequality and disorder. It is to them that Virgil owes his
                        superiority.<note place="foot">
                  <p>A foreigner of great literary distinction assures us, that, in an
                            attentive perusal of Shakespeare, he finds little to displease him;
                            that, on the contrary, in spite of his preference of the tragic system
                            of the Greeks, he is continually moved; that he meets, in every page,
                            subjects of admiration and meditation. But, when he sees the same
                            tragedies on the stage, the art of the actors, and the illusion of the
                            theatre, serve only to make him see more clearly what he thinks faults.
                            He is not only cooled, but sometimes repelled. The reason which he gives
                            for this difference is, that, in reading, he can feel and see all the
                            beauties of thought and style. He is charmed by originality and variety;
                            his attention is more directed to verses and sentiments, than to the
                            action. But in the theatre, as his ear is not habituated to our
                            pronunciation, he loses the strength and delicacy of the diction. He
                            sees only the outline of events. He follows the action, divested of the
                            attractions of style. When he thus loses all the particular beauties
                            which Shakespeare often draws from the depths of human nature, he
                            returns to his original taste, and once more prefers Sophocles.</p>
               </note> Many critics have, it is true, attempted this minute analysis of a poem.
                    But it has two great difficulties, which have, in general, proved insurmountable
                    obstacles to their success. In the <emph>first</emph> place, it regards the
                    workings of the imagination and the heart, which are minute, rapid, evanescent
                    and innumerable — sufficient to confound the head of the steadiest
                    speculator. In the <emph>second</emph> place; it ends in system, when it does
                    not arise from it; and for that reason seldom fails to deceive the critic and
                    his readers. A system founded on exclusive admiration of the classics, has
                    produced the barren rules of the schools, and prejudices whicli still influence
                    literature. Rules, founded on the practice of Petrarch, in the 16th century
                    raised Bembo and Molza to the rank of poetical models, while Dante was
                    forgotten; and the revival of his fame has occasioned the establishment of new
                    rules for poetry. In a manuscript of Petrarch, published by Ubaldini, there is a
                    single line, in which we find forty–four alterations made in various
                    days, and even years; for Petrarch marked, on the margin of his manuscripts, not
                    only the years, but the months, days and hours, when he retouched his poems.</p>
            <p>The changes in this verse do not appear to the common reader essential either to
                    the thought, the expression, or the harmony. Yet so, on a calm revisal, the poet
                    must have considered them. Every man familiar with the art must perceive, that,
                    during these changes, the heart, the head and the ear of the writer, must have
                    performed many operations. The business of the critio is to discover the reasons
                    which determined the poet finally to fix on the line as it now stands in his
                    printed text. But how difficult it is to find these reasons! and yet, how can
                    the beauty of the verse be explained without them? If we had the manuscript,
                    with the various alterations of the noblest passages of great poets, something
                    might doubtless he done. We have in our possession, the variations in a very
                    fine stanza of Ariosto, which he altered a hundred times. If we should ever have
                    occasion to speak of that poet, we shall avail ourselves of these alterations to
                    illustrate his manner of writing. But, in the other fine stanzas, which seem as
                    if they flowed from inspiration, his mind must have gone through a like
                    progress, though so rapidly, that he was himself almost unconscious of its
                    action. The verses of great poets are always the result of a long series of
                    thoughts, emotions, remembrances and images, compared, combined, rejected or
                    selected. The strength, the quickness, and the number of impressions riade on
                    the mind; the promptitude of recollection; the facility of combining fact with
                    feeling and thought, together with the powers of comparison and selection,
                    constitute the greater part of what is called Genius. A man of genius seems to
                    be inspired, because his mental operations are so much more rapid than those of
                    other men. To develop the beauties of a poem, the critic must go through the
                    same reasonings and. judgments which ultimately determined the poet to write as
                    he has done. But such a critic would be a poet. His ardent and impatient genius
                    would never submit to the cold labour of criticism. Such a man might, however,
                    analyze some passages, and at least describe the sensations with which he had
                    himself perused them; which must surpass, in depth and vivacity, the sensations
                    of an unpoetical mind. Johnson laughs at the notion, <quote>‘that a
                        poet is to be published only by a poet;’</quote> — and,
                    in what relates to emendation, and grammatical or explanatory notes, he is
                    certainly right. Critics may assist us in generalities; but, when we come to
                    particulars, which are the soul of poetry, their aid becomes of little value.
                    Great poets concentrate their ideas, and embody their feelings in images.
                    Critics take them to pieces, in order to ascertain their texture. Poets, who are
                    also critics, often exhibit a strange mixture of analysis and imagery.</p>
            <p>We shall not enter into the question, whether Pope had most taste or genius.
                    Perhaps he was destined by nature for bold invention; but in fact he has, in
                    general, imitated with taste. The same thing may be said of Horace, Vida, and
                    Boileau. Pope, like them, was a critic'as well as a poet. It is a curious
                    observation, that no poet of the first rank has ever spoken of the mechanism of
                    his art, while poets of inferior station have laboriously displayed its rules in
                    verse. Pindar declares, that a great poet, like <quote>‘the eagle,
                        soars by his natural strength, and leaves beneath him the ignoble birds who
                        seem to animate each other by their hoarse cries.’</quote> Horace,
                    on the contrary, is always teaching us how the wings are to be managed. Pope
                    lived in the philosophical age of Bayle and Locke; and English poetry, after
                    shining forth in the originality of Shakespeare, having combined the genius of
                    the Greek, Latin, and Italian classics in Milton, and having displayed its
                    various treasures in Dryden, began to form itself upon the models of the French
                    school. Among the French poets, imagery and feeling are smothered by reflection.
                    Pope could not resist his habit of analysis, even in the translation of Homer,
                    who, of all poets, is least disposed to turn aside to speculate. Perhaps these
                    deviations of Pope from the character of his author, have contributed to the
                    popularity of the English <title>Iliad.</title> But it is not here our object to
                    censure the taste of various ages and nations. It is enough for us to prove, in
                    fact, that Homer, Virgil, and Dante, have, in their pictures, left much to the
                    imagination of the reader; that it is easy to feel their beauties, and very
                    difficult to analyze them; and that, when poetry is made by system, it may
                    display artificial beauties, — but those of nature disappear.</p>
            <p>In the scene where Venus leads Helen to Paris, Homer shows his knowledge of the
                    heart of a woman agitated by a passion which she strives in vain to conquer.
                    Helen regrets her family, and is ashamed of her situation. She resists the
                    suggestions of Venus, bitterly bewails the infamy of her condition, and warmly
                    desires to return to her husband, though she expects only the contempt of
                    Greece. Venus tells her that her return would not heal the animosities between
                    Greece and Asia; that war would still continue; and that Helen herself would
                    perish by a cruel death. It is after this dialogue that Helen, wrapped up in her
                    veil, follows the goddess in silence. The reader is left to feel the struggles
                    of this woman's reason against her passion. Homer does not explain them. He
                    contents himself with saying, at the beginning of the dialogue, that as soon as
                    Helen heard of the danger of Paris, and was reminded of his beauty, her heart
                    was moved; and that, when she discovered that it was Venus. who spoke to her,
                    she was seized with fright —</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘She spoke, and Helen's secret soul was moved;</l>
                  <l>She scorn'd the champion, but the man she loved’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>The first line of this couplet is in Homer, and only tells the fact. The second
                    is added by Pope, to explaig the intention of Helen and Homer. But the whole
                    interest of the succeeding dialogue vanishes with this explanation. The passion
                    of Helen becomes that of a libertine; and her remonstrances against the counsels
                    of Venus seem gross hypocrisy. But the true Helen of Homer, throughout the
                        <title>Iliad</title>, is considered as a woman, who, by her beauty,
                    approaches the divinity. The gods, in forming so beautiful a creature, ordain
                    that she should be admired with a species of adoration. The, war, and the evils
                    of which she is the, cause, are attributed to the will of Heaven. Homer puts
                    these sentiments into the mouth of Priam, rendered the most unfortunate of men
                    by the war, and no longer of an age to be moved by beauty. Not a murmur is
                    mentioned of the Trojans or of the Greeks against the source of their woes. Her
                    husband laments' her fate; and old Nestor, not moved by the same sentiments,
                    speaks of her with the same pity. Paris declares that he had, like a pirate,
                    carried her from Sparta. She never seems to open her mouth without a blush. It
                    was a character very difficult to be painted. Homer has employed in the picture
                    the utmost delicacy of pencil, and the deepest knowledge of human nature. When
                    she bewails the death of Hector, she says, <quote>‘He never reproached
                        me; — he hindered others from reproaching me.’</quote> A
                    sublime sentiment, which describes at once the noble character of Hector, and
                    all the remorse of the soul of Helen. She lives with Paris, from a sort of union
                    of fatality and despair. She loves him; but she desires to escape from him. Her
                    character in the <title>Odyssey</title> agrees with this representation of her
                    in the <title>Iliad</title>. The Helen of Homer is always the same. The
                    reasonings of the critics make her different from herself. The slightest change
                    in delicate features destroys the physiognomy —.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘She scorned the champion, but the man she
                        loved’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>This is the illicit love of a modern lady of fashion; but it is not that of the
                    amorous queen whom Homer saw in his imagination, and perhaps partly also in the
                    manners of his age.</p>
            <p>Othello, justifying himself against the charge of having seduced Desdemona, tells
                    the Senate,</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘She loved me for the dangers I had past,</l>
                  <l>And I loved her that she did pity them’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>He tells the fact, and adds the simple reflection which immediately flows from
                    experience and feeling. In such passages, it is impossible to contemplate
                    without astonishment the genius of Shakespeare, which veils the depth of his
                    observation by the simplicity of nature. The passage is thus translated by
                    Delille —</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="fre">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Elle aimoit mes malheurs; moi j'aimais ses larmes,</l>
                  <l>L'Amour et la Pitié confondoient ses charmes’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>Shakespeare seems only to give to Othello the characteristic features of a savage
                    hero, who repays, with all his affection, those who love and admire him, and
                    with all his vengeance those who betray or despise him. The Senate understood
                    Othello. It may be doubted whether they would have understood, or at least felt
                    the cold generalities which make the metaphysical commentary of Delille. Yet the
                    readers of most of the capitals of Europe, at this day, would probably prefer
                    the couplet of Delille.</p>
            <p>Of all the translators of Dante with whom we are acquainted, Mr Cary is the most
                    successful; and we cannot but consider his work as a great acquisition to the
                    English reader. It is executed with a fidelity almost without example; and,
                    though the measure he has adopted, conveys no idea of the original stanza, it is
                    perhaps the best for his purpose, and what Dante himself would have chosen, if
                    he had written in English and in a later day. The reasons, which influenced the
                    mind of our own Milton woiild most probably have determined the author of the
                        <title lang="ita">Inferno</title>.</p>
            <p>Some years ago, Mr. Hayley published a translation of the three first Cantos of
                    that Poem, in which he endeavoured to give an idea of Dante's peculiar manner,
                    by introducing his triple rhyme. It was written with a considerable degree of
                    spii·it and elegance; but we cannot much regret that he proceeded no further.
                    The difficulties which he had to encounter were almost insurmountable; at least
                    he has led us to think so, by his many deviations from the text. Of these there
                    is a remarkable instance in the third Canto. When the poet enters in at the
                    gate, his ears are matantly assailed by a multitude of dismal sounds, among
                    which he distinguishes</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>‘Voci alte e fioche, e suon di man con elle’.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Voices deep and hoarse,</l>
                  <l>With hands together smote’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>The last circumstance, the most striking of them all, is entirely passed over by
                    Mr Hayley. Mr Pope himself indeed could furnish many a parallel from his far
                    famed translations; and one of his most flagrant transgressions has never, to
                    our knowledge, been pointed out. Penelope, in the <title>Odyssey</title>,
                        (<bibl>XIX, 597 and XXIII, 19</bibl>), twice mentions Troy, the source of
                    all her misfortunes, in a manner the most natural and affecting, giving to that
                    city the epithet of <emph>bad</emph>, and describing it as a place <emph>not to
                        be named</emph>, though, in the hurry of her grief, she herself has just
                    named it. A circumstance so beautiful and characteristic could not well be
                    overlooked; but no notice is taken of it by the translator.</p>
            <p>Cowper asserts it as his opinion, that <quote>‘a just translation of
                        any ancient poet in rhyme is impossible;’</quote> and we must
                    confess that we have never seen one. A translator has no occasion to forge
                    fetters for himself. He has enough to wear already; and, do what he will, they
                    will for ever weigh him down. Mr Pope attempted to cover his with flowers; but
                    he could not conceal them. Sometimes, indeed, he throws them off altogether; but
                    then he ceases to be a translator of Homer. No adventitious ornament —
                    no invention can supply the place of truth and exactness to him who wants to
                    know how men thought and felt in past ages. Who would consent to exchange the
                    story of Joseph and his Brethren, as it is told in our Bibles, for the most
                    elegant version of it by Mr Pope?</p>
            <p>Of such offences we cannot accuse Mr Cary. Throughout he discovers the will and
                    the power to do justice to his author. He has omitted nothing, he has added
                    nothing; and though here and there his inversions are ungraceful, and his
                    phrases a little obsolete, he walks not unfrequently by the side of his master,
                    and sometimes perhaps goes beyond him. We may say in the language of that
                    venerable Father of Italian Poetry,</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Hor ti riman, lector, sopra'l tuo banco;</l>
                  <l>Drieto pensando accioche si preliba’, &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Paradiso</title> X.</bibl>
            </p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Now rest thee, reader! on thy bench, and muse</l>
                  <l>Anticipative of the feast to come:</l>
                  <l>So shall delight make thee not feel the toil’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>Perhaps there is no description so sublime in .the <title>Purgatory</title>, as
                    that of the discovery and expulsion of the Serpent in the Eighth Canto. How
                    delightfully it opens with that passage from which Gray has horrowed the first
                    line of his Elegy!</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Now was the hour that wakens fond desire</l>
                  <l>In men at sea, and melts their thoughtful hearts,</l>
                  <l>Who in the morn have bid sweet friends farewel;</l>
                  <l>And pilgrim newly on his road with love</l>
                  <l>Thrills, if he hear the vesper bell from far,</l>
                  <l>That seems to mourn for the expiring day’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>In the Ninth Canto, the Angel of God unlocks the gate; and the verses, that
                    follow, are not unworthy of Milton.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘As in the hinges of that sacred ward</l>
                  <l>The swivels moved,</l>
                  <l>Harsh was the grating.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Attentively I turned,</l>
                  <l>Listening the thunder, that first issued forth;</l>
                  <l>And “We praise thee, O God”, methought I heard</l>
                  <l>In accents blended with sweet melody.</l>
                  <l>The strains came o'er mine ear, e'en as the sound</l>
                  <l>Of choral voices, that in solemn chant</l>
                  <l>With organ mingle, and, now high and clear,</l>
                  <l>Come swelling, now float indistinct away’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>In no writer, not even in Homer, have the similes more life and variety than in
                    Dante; and they are for the most part given with the truest touches in the
                    translation. We shall select two or three that may convey perhaps a less gloomy
                    idea of him than generally prevails among us.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘As from a troop of well–ranked. chivalry</l>
                  <l>One knight, more enterprising than the rest,</l>
                  <l>Pricks forth at gallop, eager to display</l>
                  <l>His prowess in the first encounter proved;</l>
                  <l>So parted he from us with lengthened strides,</l>
                  <l>And left me on the way with those two spirits,</l>
                  <l>Who were such mighty marshals.of the woild’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Purgatory</title>, 24.</bibl>
            </p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘As on their road</l>
                  <l>The thoughtful pilgrims, overtaking some</l>
                  <l>Not known unto them, turn to them, and look,</l>
                  <l>But stay not; thus, approaching from behind,</l>
                  <l>They eyed us as they passed’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 23.</bibl>
            </p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘When from their game of dice men separate,</l>
                  <l>He, who hath lost, remains in sadness fixed,</l>
                  <l>Revolving in his mind, what luckless throws</l>
                  <l>He cast: but meanwhile all the company</l>
                  <l>Go with the other; one before him runs,</l>
                  <l>And one, behind, his mantle twitches, one</l>
                  <l>Fast by his side bids him remember him.</l>
                  <l>He stops not; and each one, to whom his hand</l>
                  <l>Is stretched, well knows he bids him stand aside;</l>
                  <l>And thus he from the press defends himself.</l>
                  <l>E'en such was I in that close crowding throng;</l>
                  <l>And turning so my face around to all,</l>
                  <l>And promising, I 'scaped from it with pains’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 6.</bibl>
            </p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Then as a troop of maskers, when they put</l>
                  <l>Their vizors off, look other than before,</l>
                  <l>The counterfeited semblance thrown aside’; &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Paradise</title>, 30.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Dante must have loved hawking. He paints his bird always to the life.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘On his feet</l>
                  <l>The falcon first looks down, then to the sky</l>
                  <l>Turns, and forth stretches, eager for the food</l>
                  <l>That wooes him thither’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Purgatory</title>, 19.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>And again,</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Like to a falcon issuing from the hood,</l>
                  <l>That rears his head, and claps him with his wings,</l>
                  <l>His beauty and his eagerness bewraying’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Paradise</title>, 19.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Mr Cary reminds us sometimes of Shakespeare, — oftener of Milton; but,
                    in his anxiety to imitate them, he becomes more antiquated than either; and we
                    hope, that, when he republishes his translation, which, we trust, he soon will,
                    in a larger and more legible character, he will think proper to modernize the
                    language a little, and give more simplicity and sweetness to many parts of it.
                    In that beautiful simile,</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Then seemed they like to ladies, from the dance</l>
                  <l>Not ceasing, but <emph>suspense</emph>, in silent pause,</l>
                  <l>Listening till they have caught the strain anew’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Paradise</title>, X.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>— surely the word <emph>suspense</emph> is obscure and unpleasing.
                    Milton uses it indeed in like manner; but why not avoid, when we can, the
                    perplexity that must always arise from using the same word as an adjective and a
                    substantive? We do not disapprove of the judicious use of old words. Far from
                    it. They are, in their place, most becoming; and, in the present instance, throw
                    a sober colouring over the whole, which we should be sorry to lose. If Dante
                    himself were to appear among us, should we not expect to find his beard and his
                    tunic after an ancient fashion, and much as they are represented in that old
                    painting in the Duomo at Florence?</p>
            <p>But, when Dante is the subject, our readers may require something of a darker
                    complexion than what we have given them; and we shall conclude with two extracts
                    from the <title lang="ita">Inferno</title>. The pathetic story of Francesca,
                    before mentioned, is known to all; and all can, in some degree, form a judgment
                    of the translation.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘When I had heard my sage instructor name</l>
                  <l>Those dames and knights of antique days, o'erpowered</l>
                  <l>By pity, well–nigh in amaze my ming</l>
                  <l>Was lost; and I began — “Bard, willingly</l>
                  <l>I would address those two together coming,</l>
                  <l>Which seem so light before the wind”. He thus:</l>
                  <l>“Note thou, when nearer they to us approach,</l>
                  <l>Then by that love which carries them along</l>
                  <l>Entreat; and they will come”. Soon as the wind</l>
                  <l>Swayed them toward us, I thus framed my speech;</l>
                  <l>“O wearied spirits! come, and hold discourse</l>
                  <l>With us, if by none else.restrained”. As doves</l>
                  <l>By fond desire invited, on wide wings</l>
                  <l>And firm, to their sweet nest returning home,</l>
                  <l>Cleave the air, wafted by their will along;</l>
                  <l>They came —.........</l>
                  <l>Then, turning, I to them my speech addressed,</l>
                  <l>And thus began — “Francesca! your sad fate</l>
                  <l>Even to tears my grief and pity moves.</l>
                  <l>But tell me, in the time of your sweet sighs,</l>
                  <l>By what and how Love granted that ye knew</l>
                  <l>Your yet uncertain wishes?” She replied:</l>
                  <l>“No greater grief than to remember days</l>
                  <l>Of joy, when misery is at hand. That knows</l>
                  <l>Thy learned instructor. Yet so eagerly</l>
                  <l>If thou art bent to learn the primal root</l>
                  <l>From whence our love got being, I will do,</l>
                  <l>As one, who weeps and tells his tale. One day</l>
                  <l>For our delight we read of Landelot,</l>
                  <l>How him Love thralled. Alone we were, and no</l>
                  <l>Sustiioion near us. Ofttimes by that reading.</l>
                  <l>Our eyes were diawn together, and the hue</l>
                  <l>Fled from our altered cheeks. But at orie point</l>
                  <l>Alone, we fell. When of that smile we read,</l>
                  <l>The wish'd–for smile, so rapturously kissed</l>
                  <l>By one so deep in love, then he, who ne'er</l>
                  <l>From me shall separate, at once my lips</l>
                  <l>All trembling kissed. The book and writer both</l>
                  <l>Were Love's purveyors. In its leaves that day</l>
                  <l>We read no more’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="italic">Canto</hi> V.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>The same observation applies still more strongly to the unrivalled tale of
                    Ugolino; which Michael Angelo is said to have delighted in. There is a
                    bas–relief of his on the subject.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘How cruel was the murder shalt thou hear,</l>
                  <l>And know if he have wronged me.........</l>
                  <l>Before the dawn, amid their sleep, I heard</l>
                  <l>My sons, for they were with me, weep, and ask</l>
                  <l>For bread. Right cruel art thou, if no pang</l>
                  <l>Thou feel at thinking what my heart foretold;</l>
                  <l>And if not now, why use thy tears to flow?</l>
                  <l>Now had they wakened; and the hour drew near</l>
                  <l>When they were wont to bring us food; the mind</l>
                  <l>Of each misgave him through his dream, and I</l>
                  <l>Heard at its outlet underneath locked up</l>
                  <l>The horrible tower. Then, uttering not a word</l>
                  <l>I looked upon the faces of my sons.</l>
                  <l>I wept not; so all stone I felt within.</l>
                  <l>They wept; and one, my little Anselm, cried;</l>
                  <l>“Thou lookest so! — Father, what ails
                            thee?” Yet</l>
                  <l>I shed no tear, nor answer'd all that day</l>
                  <l>Nor the next night, until another sun</l>
                  <l>Came out upon the world. When a faint beam</l>
                  <l>Had to our doleful prison made its way,</l>
                  <l>And in four countenances I descry'd</l>
                  <l>The image of my own, on either hand</l>
                  <l>Through agony I bit, and they who thought</l>
                  <l>I did it through desire of feeding, rose</l>
                  <l>O' th' sudden, and cried: “Father, we should grieve</l>
                  <l>Far less, if thou wouldst eat of us: thou gav'st</l>
                  <l>These weeds of miserable flesh we wear,</l>
                  <l>And do thou strip them off from us again”.</l>
                  <l>Then, not to make then sadder, I kept down</l>
                  <l>My spirit in stillness. That day and the next</l>
                  <l>We all were silent. Ah, obdurate earth!</l>
                  <l>Why open'dst not upon us? When we came</l>
                  <l>To the fourth day, then Gaddo at my feet</l>
                  <l>Outstretch'd did fling him, crying, “Hast no help</l>
                  <l>For me, my father!” There he , died, and e'en,</l>
                  <l>Plainly as thou seest me, saw I the three</l>
                  <l>Fall one by one 'twixt the fifth day and sixth:</l>
                  <l>Whence I betook me, now grown blind, to grope</l>
                  <l>Over them all, and for three days aloud</l>
                  <l>Call'd on them who were dead. Then, fasting got</l>
                  <l>The mastery of grief”. Thus having spoke,</l>
                  <l>Once more upon the wretched skull his teeth</l>
                  <l>He fasten'd, like a mastiff's 'gainst the bone</l>
                  <l>Firm and unyielding’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="italic">Canto</hi> XXXIII.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>When such stories are related by such a poet as Dante, ‘the world will
                    not willingly let them die.’ Yet, not very long before he appeared,
                    what a darkness prevailed over Europe! — when there was a
                    high–constable of France who could not read, and when there were Kings
                    who could only make the sign of the cross in confirmation of their charters.
                    Even then, however, as an elegant writer<note place="foot">
                  <p>Mrs Barbauld. We rejoice in this opportunity to express our high sense of
                            her talents. The greatest and most accomplished statesman of the age
                            always spoke of them with admiration. Her songs he could repeat by
                            heart; and her essay <quote>‘against Inconsistency in our
                                Expectations’</quote>, he justly considered as equal to
                            any thing of the kind in any language.</p>
               </note>has observed, the Muses, with their attendant arts (in strange disguise
                    indeed, and uncouth trappings) were not idle in the cloister. Statuary carved a
                    madonna or a — crucifix; Painting illuminated a missal; —
                    Eloquence made the panegyric of a saint; — and History composed a
                    legend. Still they breathed; and were ready, at any happier period, to emerge
                    from obscurity with all their native charms and undiminished lustre.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 n="Articolo II">
            <head>
               <foreign lang="ita">SECONDO ARTICOLO</foreign>
            </head>
            <head>
               <foreign lang="ita">DELLA EDINBURGH REVIEW</foreign>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline lang="ita">(settembre 1818)</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <foreign lang="ita">
                     <hi rend="sc">ART.</hi> II. <title>Osservazioni intorno
                                alla Questione sopra la Originalità del Poema di Dante</title>, Di
                                <hi rend="sc">F. CANCELLIERI</hi>, Roma, 1814</foreign>
               </bibl>.</p>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Observations concerning the Question of the Originality of the Poem
                            of Dante</title>, By <hi rend="sc">F. CANCELLIERI</hi>
               </bibl>.</p>
            <p>The limits of a late Number precluded us from entering, as fully as we would haye
                    wished, into the subject of Dante. We resume it the more willingly, from our
                    having just received a work, published two or three years ago in Italy, but
                    almost unknown in England, having for its object to ascertain, whether this
                    great poet was an inventor, or an imitator only. The continental antiquaries and
                    scholars have eagerly laid hold of a manuscript, said to have been discovered
                    about the beginning of the present century, and affording efidence, according to
                    some persons, that he had borrowed from others the whole plan, and conception of
                    his wonderful work. The question, indeed, is of ancient date; and, long before
                    such value had been set upon this manuscript, was so perplexed and prolonged, as
                    now to call for definitive elucidation. We trust we shall place our readers in a
                    condition to decide it for themselves.</p>
            <p>An extract, or rather a short abstract of an old Vision, written in Latin,
                    appeared in a pamphlet published at Rome in 1801, with an insinuation, that the
                    primitive model of Dante's poem had at length been discovered. Some reader of
                    new publications transmitted the intelligence of this discovery to a German
                    journalist, who received it as of the utmost importance; and from him, a writer
                    in a French paper, (the <title>Publiciste</title> of July 1809), transcribed,
                    embellished, and diffused it over all Europe, through the medium of his
                    universal language. Having nothing to do with politics, every body received it
                    upon the faith of the author of the pamphlet, by whom alone the old manuscript
                    had been read; and it was immediately settled, among the wits and critics of the
                    day, that Dante wals but the versifier of the ideas of others. Mr
                        <emph>Cancellieri</emph>, a professed black–letter scholar, and
                    animated, no doubt, with a laudable zeal for religion as well as literature,
                    published the Vision entire in 1814, on the return of his Holiness to Rome. He
                    accompanied it with an Italian translation, the whole comprising some sixty
                    pages, preceded by twice that number of pages of his own remarks. In this ample
                    dissertation, the question, however, is merely glanced at; — and all
                    that its readers can make out with certainty is, that the learned author had
                    selected this curious subject chiefly to astonish the world by his multifarious
                    erudition, in a book which might have been not inaptly entitled —
                    ‘ <title lang="lat">De rebus omnibus, et de quibusdam
                    aliis.</title>’ It must be acknowledged, however, that, amidst the
                    unbounded variety of his citations, we meet with some things which it is
                    agreeable to know; but they have so little to do with Dante, that we are really
                    but little beholden to him on the present occasion; and have been obliged to
                    refer to many other authorities, in order to disentangle ourselves from the
                    perplexities into which, he had brought us.</p>
            <p>Mr Cancellieri apprises us that there existed two famous <emph>Alberics</emph>,
                    both monks of Monte–Cassino; — but he thought it immaterial
                    to add, that the first was one of the few monks to whom the civilization of the
                    world is not without obligations — he having, in the midst of the
                    barbarism of the 11th century, written treatises upon logic, astronomy, and
                        music.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Mabillon, <title>An. Bened.</title>, vol. 5, b. 65.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note> His works probably contributed more to form the mind of Dante, than the
                        <title>Visions</title> of the other to form the plan of his poem.</p>
            <p>The latter Alberic was born about the year 1100, soon after the death of the
                    former. When in his 9th year, he fell sick, and remained in a lethargy for nine
                    days. Whilst in this state, a dove appeared to him, and catching him by the hair
                    lifted him up to the presence of Saint Peter, who, with two angels, conducted
                    the child across Purgatory, and, mounting thence from planet to planet,
                    transported him into Paradise, there to contemplate the glory of the blessed.
                    His vision restored him to perfect health; — the miraculous cure was
                    published to the world; — the monks received the child at
                    Monte–Cassino; — and, because he repeated his vision
                    tolerably well, and was of a rich family, they devoted him to. Saint Benedict,
                    before he had reached his 10th year. He lived from that time in constant
                    penitence, tasting neither flesh or wine, and never wearing shoes; and the
                    monastery had thus the glory of possessing a living saint, who, by his virtue,
                    confirmed the belief that he had seen Purgatory and Paradise.</p>
            <p>They took care to have the vision of Alberic reduced to writing, first by one of
                    their own lettered brethren, and, some years after, by Alberic himself, assisted
                    by the pen of Peter the Deacon, of whom there are yet remaining some historical
                    pieces which occasionally throw light upon the darkness of that age. We subjoin
                    what he says of Alberio in his own words.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <quote lang="lat">Tanta usque in hodiernum abstinentia, tanta
                                morumagravitate pollet, ut pœnas peccatorum perspexisse, et
                                pertimuisse, et gloriam sanctorum vidisse nemo quis dubitet: Non
                                enim carnem, non adipem, non vinum, ab illo tempore usque nunc, Deo
                                annuente, assumpsit; calciamentai nullo penitus tempore utitur; et
                                sie, in tanta cordis, ac corporis contritione, et humilitate usque
                                nunc in hodiernum, in hoc Casinensi cœnobio perseverat, ut multa
                                illum quæ alios laterent vel metuenda, vel desideranda vidisse,
                                etiamsi lingua taceret, vita loqueretur. (<bibl>
                           <title lang="lat">De
                                        Viris illustr.</title> Casin.</bibl>)</quote>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>If there existed but this one vision before the time of Dante, there might be
                    some ground for presuming that it suggested to him the idea of his poem. But the
                    truth is, that such visions abounded from the very earliest ages of
                    Christianity. Saint Cyprian had visions, — Saint Perpetua had visions,
                    — and both, with many others, were declared.divine by Saint Augustine.
                    The revelations of each turned upon the doctrine which each thought the best for
                    establishing the faith. Accordingly, the creed written for the church over which
                    he presided, by Saint Gregory Thaumaturgus, was dictated to him in a vision by
                    Saint John the Evangelist. But the zeal of the early bishops was soon replaced
                    by the interested views of their successors. About the 10th century, the great
                    object was, to establish the doctrine of Purgatory, in which the period of
                    expiation was shortened in favour of souls, in proportion to the alms given by
                    their heirs to the Church. The monk Alberic describes Purgatory with minuteness,
                    and sees Hell only at a distance. All those visions, having the same object,
                    resembled each other; and whoever will take the trouble to examine the legends
                    of the saints, and archives of the monasteries, will find hundreds, of the same
                    epoch, and the same tenor. It may be said, that Dante either. profited by all,
                    or by none; but, if there be any one to which he can be supposed to be indebted
                    more than another, it is the vision of an English monk, not named by any one
                    that we know, though told circumstantially by Mathew Paris.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Hist. Ang.</title>, ad an. 1196.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note> The English monk, like the Italian, gives no description of Hell, but,
                    like Dante, describes his Purgatory as a mount; — the passage from
                    Purgatory to Paradise, a vast garden, intersected by delightful woods, as in our
                    poet. Both had their visions in the holy week; — both allot the same
                    punishments to the same infamous crimes, with some other points of resemblance,
                    which those who are curious may find in Mathew Paris. The vision related by that
                    historian, suffices to give an idea of all the others; and proves, indeed, that
                    there existed, at that time, a systematic style for working, in this way, upon
                    popular credulity. The English monk also had his vision immediately after a long
                    and dangerous malady, and in a state of lethargy and inanition, which lasted
                    nine days, also followed by a miraculous cure.</p>
            <p>It is sufficiently probable, that Dante had read the history of Mathew Paris, the
                    historian having died before the birth of the poet; and still more probable,
                    that he had read the vision of Alberic. The resemblance which we have pointed
                    out between the visions of the two monks, and the infinity of other visions of
                    the same kind, show that there was then established, in the popular belief, a
                    sort of Visionary mythology, which Dante adopted in the same manner as the
                    mythology of Polytheism had been adopted by Homer. Besides, the discovery of the
                    manuscript of the Vision of Alberic, about which so much noise has been made for
                    the last eighteen years, really took place about a century ago. It is mentioned,
                    but without much stress, by Mazzuchelli, Pelli, and Tiraboschi.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Mazzuch., <title lang="ita">Scritt. It.</title>, vol. I, pag. 290.
                                — Pelli, <title lang="ita">Memor.</title>, pag. 122.
                                — Tirab., <title lang="ita">Storia</title> &amp; c.,
                                vol. 3, b. 4.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note> Mr Bottari was the first who confronted it with the poem of Dante, in
                    the year 1753; and the vanity which turns the heads of so many erudite persons,
                    when they make discoveries to their own infinite surprise, malle him imagine he
                    had discovered, in Dante, diverse close imitations of the manuscript. The
                    following is one of his great instances. Dante calls the Devil
                        <quote>‘the great worm,’</quote> (<bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Inferno</title>, Cant. 31.</bibl>), and therefore he must
                    have copied from Alberio, who saw <quote>‘a great worm that devoured
                        souls.’</quote> Monsignor Bottari was a prelate; the author of the
                    pamphlet is a Benedictine abbot; Mr Cancellieri is a good. Catholic, and all
                    three are antiquarians. How has it escaped them, that the Devil is called
                        <quote>‘the serpent’</quote> in the
                    <title>Scriptures</title>, and that <quote>‘worm’</quote>
                    was constantly used for ‘serpent’ by the old Italian
                    writers? Shakespeare indeed uses it in the same sense, in <title>Anthony and
                        Cleopatra</title>; and Johnson, in his note upon the passage, adduces a
                    variety of other instances, in which the term was so employed. Another alleged
                    imitation is, that in <title>Purgatory</title> an eagle grasps Dante with his
                    talon, and raises him on high, in the same manner as Alberio had been caught by
                    the hair, and lifted up by a dove. — Here, too, three pious persons
                    have forgotten their <title>Bible</title>. In the two chapters of Daniel,
                    retained in the <title>Vulgate</title>, Habakkuk is thus caught and lifted up by
                    an angel; and the prophet Ezekiel says, <bibl>chap. viii, v. 3</bibl>,
                        <quote>‘And he put forth the form of an hand, and took me by a
                        lock of mine head, and the spirit lifted me up between the earth and the
                        heayen, and brought me in the visions of God.’</quote> It is
                    certain that ingenuity and erudition will discover resemblances in things the
                    most different from each other. In the passage of Sterne, which is so beautiful,
                    so original, and so well known, of the recording angel washing out the oath with
                    a tear, we doubt not that Doctor Ferriar would have detected a plagiarism from
                    Alberic, had that ingenious person seen the 18th section of the manuscript. We
                    give an abstract of the passage, for the use of the Doctor's next edition.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <p>‘A demon holds a book, in which are written the sins of a
                        particular man; and an angel drops on it, from a phial, a tear which the
                        sinner had shed in doing a good action; and his sins are washed
                        out.’</p>
            </quote>
            <p>It is possible that Dante may have taken some ideas here and there from the
                    Visions which abounded in his age. There are involuntary plagiarisms, which no
                    writer can wholly avoid; — for much of what we think and express is
                    but a new combination of what we have read and heard. But reminiscences in great
                    geniuses are sparks that produce a mighty flame; and if Dante, like the monks,
                    employed the machinery of visions, the result only proves, that much of a great
                    writer's originality may consist in attaining his sublime objects by the same
                    means which others had employed for mere trifling. He conceived and executed the
                    project of creating the Language and the Poetry of a nation — of
                    exposing all the political wounds of his country — of teaching the
                    Church and the States of Italy, that the imprudence of the Popes, and the civil
                    wars of the cities, and the consequent introduction of foreign arms, must lead
                    to the eternal slavery and disgrace of the Italians. He raised himself to a
                    place among the reformers of morals, the avengers of crimes, and the asserters
                    of orthodoxy in religion; and he called to his aid Heaven itself, with all its
                    terrors and all its hopes, in what was denominated by himself</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l> — ‘the Sacred work, that made</l>
                  <l>Both Heaven and Earth copartners in his toil’.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>‘<emph>Il poema sacro</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Al qual ha posto mano e Cielo e Terra</emph>’.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>
               <bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Parad.</title>, Cant. 25.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>To explain how he executed his vast design, it appears to us indispensable that
                    we should give a slight sketch of the political and religious state of Italy at
                    the period when he wrote.</p>
            <p>Robertson has described Europe, in the middle ages, as peopled with slaves
                    attached to the soil, who had no consolation but their Religion. And this indeed
                    was, for many centuries, the great instrument of good and of evil even in
                    temporal concerns. The feudal lords were restrained only by the fear of Heaven,
                    — and the monarch had no army but such as that military arístocracy
                    supplied. The canon law was the only instrument by which justice could oppose
                    force; and that instrument was wielded only by the clergy. This last
                    circumstance was the chief foundation of the great ascendency of the Popes. A
                    strong yearning after justice and law instigated the people of Italy to become
                    free; and the circumstances of the times were such, that for their freedom they
                    were indebted to the Church. Robertson, however, as well as many others, copying
                    after Machiavelli, has erroneously ascribed the misfortunes of the suoceeding
                    generations to the authority usurped over princes by Gregory VII. The ill
                    effects of that usurpation were not sensibly felt in Italy until a much later
                    period; and the truth is, that Italian liberty and civilization were greatly
                    promoted by it in the first instance; and. advanced by rapid strides, from the
                    age of Gregory to that of Dante, a period of 200 years. The acts of that
                    ambitious Pontiff, however, prolific as they were, of important consequences to
                    his country, require undoubtedly to be kept in view by all who would understand
                    its history.</p>
            <p>The daring schemes which he conceived and executed in a few years, and in his old
                    age, may be said to have been accomplished by the use of the single word
                    — Excommunication. By this talisman, he compelled the sovereigns of
                    his day to acknowledge, that all the lands in their dominions allotted for the
                    support of the clergy, belonged in property to the Pope; — and our
                    England was the first that made the concession. ’Two Italians at that
                    time successively enjoyed the see of Canterbury for nearly forty years.<note place="foot">
                  <p>Lanfranc. and St Anselm, from 1070 to 1109.</p>
               </note> By this notable device, the Church at once acquired a very large portion
                    of all the cultivated lands of Europe: for the monks had very generally employed
                    themselves in clearing and cultivating the soil — received large
                    donations from potentates and kings — and had thus become wealthy and
                    powerful proprietors. By this act of annexation, however, they became the
                    immediate subjects of the Pope; and a great portion of the riches of Europe
                    began, in consequence, to flow in upon Italy.</p>
            <p>The next of Gregory's gigantic measures was, if possible, still more bold and
                    important — and this was the absolute prohibition of marriage to all
                    the orders of the priesthood. He had here to struggle with the inclinations of
                    the clergy themselves, and of the Italian clergy in particular. But when the
                    difficulty was once overcome, the advantage gained was prodigious — to
                    the order itself — to the Popedom — and to the country which
                    was its seat. The great brotherhood of the Catholic clergy, receiving their
                    subsistence directly from the Church — exempted from secular
                    jurisdiction, and now loosened from all the ties of natural affection
                    — must have felt themselves but feebly attached to their respective
                    countries, and looked almost exclusively, as they taught their fellow citizens
                    to look, to Rome as the place which was to give law to the world.</p>
            <p>The last grand project of Gregory was that of the Crusades,<note place="foot">
                  <p>This appears by two of his own letters. <bibl>See <title>Collect. of
                                    Labbeus</title>, <hi rend="sc">VOL.</hi> XXX, <hi rend="sc">NO.</hi> 60</bibl>.</p>
               </note> which, though he did not live long enough to carry into execution, he
                    left to his successor already matured and digested. Then it was that kings
                    became subalterns in command, fighting with their subjects in Asia during half a
                    century, under orders issued from Rome; and Rome and Italy became, of course,
                    the centre of influence and authority. All these advantages, however, would have
                    been of but little value, without freedom; and of this, also, the sovereign
                    Pontiff happened to be the first dispenser: — for Gregory, in his
                    first experiment of excommunication, released the Italians from their oath of
                    fealty to the Emperor, who had previously governed them as vassals.</p>
            <p>It is under these circumstances that we behold, immediately after the death of
                    this Pope, and even in his lifetime, the cities of Italy suddenly improving in
                    population, wealth and power — palaces of independent magistrates
                    rising to view where there were before but hamlets and slaves — and
                    republics starting forth as if out of nothing. The holy war had delivered Europe
                    in general from the slavery of the soil; every man who took up arms for the
                    crusade became free; and the labourer in Italy began to till the earth on his
                    own account. The military aristocracies and monarchies being employed with their
                    armed forces in distant expeditions, had no longer the same oppressive
                    preponderance at home. The maritime preparations for the crusades were
                    undertaken by the cities of Italy — danger nerved the courage of every
                    class — and navigation, by opening the exportation of manufactures,
                    increased industry, wealth and knowledge. Florence, for example, supplied all
                    nations with her woollen cloths; and Milan furnished all the arms used by the
                    crusaders, and the princes of Europe. The latter city, at that period of her
                    liberty, had a population triple what it is .at the present day. It was said the
                    country was depopulated to supply the manufactures in the towns. But how could
                    so many millions have been subsisted without agriculture? It was then that Italy
                    crowded every port with her gallies, and every marked with her merchandise. The
                    wealth thus resulting from commerce, served to divide and distribute the
                    property of the land, and to inultiply the number of those interested in
                    maintaining the laws and independence of their country. The enormous inequality
                    of fortunes disappeared, and the weight of the capitalists was opposed to the
                    ascendency of the ancient nobles. It was then. that the people of Pisa became
                    masters of the Balearic, and discovered the Canary islands — that
                    Genoa was fortified with strong walls in the space of two months —
                    that Milan, and other towns of Lombardy, having seen their children massacred,
                    their houses and churches burned, their habitations rased — and,
                    having been reduced to live two years unsheltered in the fields, —
                    resumed their arms, routed Frederick Barbarossa, who returned with a formidable
                    force, and compelled him to sign the peace of Constance, acknowledging their
                    independence.</p>
            <p>During all this time, it is true that most of those States were engaged in civil
                    wars. But they had arms in their hands; and when the common enemy appeared, they
                    knew how to join in defending their common liberties. The Italians having thrown
                    off the foreign yoke, gave their aid to the Popes, who were constantly occupied
                    in conflicts with the Emperors; and the Church had thus an interest in favouring
                    independence and democracy. But, by degrees, she became tired of using the arms
                    of the Italian States as her defence, though the safest and most natural for her
                    to employ; and, having contributed towards the liberty of Italy, thought she had
                    the right to invade it. Excommunications had then been hurled against friends
                    and enemies, till they began to be less formidable; and the Popes adopted the
                    policy of introducing foreign conquerors, and sharing their conquests. It was
                    then that they and the kings of France became constant and close allies. In the
                    lifetime of Dante, a French prince, aided by the Pope, came for the first time
                    into Italy, usurping the states of old dynasties in the name of the Holy See
                    — promising liberty, and preaching concord to republics, but in fact
                    dividing still more, in order to enslave them. The <foreign lang="ita">Guelfi</foreign> professed themselves supporters of the Church, and the
                        <foreign lang="ita">Ghibelini</foreign> of the Empire, but without much
                    caring for the one or the other. The true question between them was, whether the
                    wealthy citizens or the people should govern the state; and, in the continual
                    danger of foreign invasion, the popular party found its interest in attaching
                    itself to the Church and to France against Germany, whilst the higher classes
                    were more interested in joining the Emperors against the Popes and the French.
                    From the political conduct of Dante when a magistrate, it is evident that he
                    condemned the madness of both parties; for he sent the leaders of both into
                    banishment. But it is also clear that he was more afraid of France than of
                    Germany, and not over fond of democracy.</p>
            <p>The true reason of his exile was his refusal to receive a prince of France sent
                    by Boniface VIII., under the pretext of pacifying their dissensions. After his
                    exile, he openly embraced the Ghibeline party, and composed a Latin treatise,
                        <title lang="lat">De Monarchia</title>, to prove that all the misfortunes of
                    Italy sprang from the false doctrine, that the Popes had a right to interfere in
                    temporal concerns. France having, at the time, contrived that the Popes should
                    reside at Avignon, for the purposes of more absolute control, and Frenchmen
                    having been successively raised to the Holy See, as being more devoted to French
                    interests, our poet addressed a letter to the Cardinals from his exile,
                    recommending strongly that they should elect an Italian Pope.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Giovanni Villani, B. 9, chap. 134.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note> It was with those views, and under those circumstances, in so far as
                    politics were concerned, that he wrote his poem.</p>
            <p>But, notwithstanding the corruption and senseless ambition of the Church, and its
                    consequent unpopularity, Religion still maintained its primitive influence. The
                    first crusade raised almost all Europe in arms, by an opinion, suddenly
                    diffused, that the end of the world and the general judgment were at hand, and
                    that the holy war was the sole expiation of sins. These enterprises had been
                    abandoned during the lifetime of our poet; but the dread of the end of the world
                    continued to agitate Christendom for eighty years after his death. Leonardo
                    Aretino, a historian known for the extent of his knowledge, and the share he had
                    in the affairs of Italy and Europe, was an eyewitness of an event which took
                    place in 1400. We shall give his account, translated <emph>verbatim</emph>.</p>
            <p>
               <quote>‘In the midst of the alarms and troubles of the wars, either
                        begun or impending between the States of Italy, an extraordinary occurrence
                        took place. All the inhabitants of each state dressed themselves in white.
                        This multitude went forth with extreme devotion. They passed to the
                        neighbouring states, humbly craving peace and mercy. Their journey lasted
                        usually ten days; and their food during this time was bread and water. None
                        were seen in the towns that were not dressed in white. The people went
                        without danger into an enemy's country, whither, a few days before, they
                        would not have dared to approach. No one ever thought of betraying another,
                        and strangers were never insulted. It was a universal truce tacitly
                        understood between all enemies. This lasted for about two months; but its
                        origin is not clear. It was confidently affirmed to have come down from the
                        Alps into Lombardy, whence it spread with astonishing rapidity over all
                        Italy. The inhabitants of Lucca were the first who came in a body to
                        Florence. Their presence suddenly excited an ardent devotion, to such a
                        degree that even those who, at the commencement, treated this enthusiasm
                        with contempt, were the first to change their dress and join the procession,
                        as if they were suddenly impelled by a heavenly inspiration. The people of
                        Florence divided themselves into four parties; two of which, consisting of a
                        countless multitude of men, women and children, went to Arezzo. The
                        remaining two took other directions, and, wherever they came, the
                        inhabitants dressed themselves in white, and followed their example. During
                        the two months that this devotion lasted, war was never thought of; but, no
                        sooner had it passed away, than the people resumed their arms, and the
                        previous state of agitation was renewed.’</quote>
               <bibl>
                  <emph>Aret. <title lang="lat">Hist. Flor.</title>
                  </emph>, b. 12., c.
                    1.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Such, in that age, was the force of religion; and Dante, therefore, naturally
                    employed its terrors as the most effective means of touching the passions of his
                    cotemporaries. But religion, in Italy especially, was overgrown with heresies
                    and schisms, which often produced the most sanguinary conflicts. Saint Francis
                    founded his order about the beginning of the 13th century; and preached the
                    faith, according to the doctrines of the Church of Rome, in opposition to the
                    sects which the Italian chronicles of that age call Valdesi, Albigesi, Cattari
                    and Paterini, but more commonly by the latter name. These four sects were all in
                    the main Manicheans. At the same time, St Dominick arrived from Spain, carrying
                    fire and sword wherever his opinions were disputed. It was he who founded the
                    Inquisition; and was himself the first <quote lang="lat">magister sacri
                    palati</quote>, an office always held at Rome, even in our own time, by a
                    Dominican, who examines new books, and decides upon their publication. Before
                    the institution of those two orders, the monks were almost all of the different
                    rules of St Benedict, reformed by St Bernard and other abbots. But, being
                    occupied in tilling the land, or in perusing manuscripts of antient authors
                    — in fine, never going beyond their convents, unless to become the
                    ministers of kingdoms, where they sometimes exercised kingly power, —
                    their wealth, education, and even pride, rendered them unfit for the business of
                    running from place to place, and employing hypocrisy, impudence and cruelty, in
                    the service of the Popes. St Bernard, by his eloquence and rare talents,
                    exercised great influence over kings and pontiffs. He succeeded in firing Europe
                    to undertake the crusade; but, to give durability to the opinions he produced,
                    there was still wanting the pertinacity and roguery of the mendicant friars, to
                    exhibit to the people spectacles of humility and privation, and of
                    auto–da–fe. They had their convents in towns, and spread
                    themselves over the country; whilst the Benedictines were living like great
                    feudal lords in their castles. Hence, the Italians carefully make the
                    distinction of <foreign lang="ita">Monaci</foreign> and <foreign lang="ita">Frati</foreign>. The former were always more or less useful to agriculture
                    — remarkable for the luxury in which they lived — receiving
                    amongst them only persons of condition for the most part — and each
                    congregation having a sort of monarchical constitution, of which the abbot was
                    absolute chief. The constitution of the Frati was, on the other hand, at all
                    tiines more or less democratic. They have always been meddling with affairs of
                    state, and family affairs —</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="lat">
               <lg>
                  <l>‘Scire volunt secreta domus atque inde timeri.’</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>The Jesuits, who have been lately re–established, are also mendicant
                        <foreign lang="ita">Frati</foreign>. Notwithstanding their great wealth,
                    they observed the form, in order to preserve the right of hegging, by sending
                    out their <emph>conversi</emph> (lay–brothers) with sacks, three or
                    four times a year, to beg for their convents. Having been established three
                    centuries later than the others, they took advantage of this, to give refmement
                    to the arts, and to avoid the faults of those who preceded them. Mathew Paris,
                    who was nearly cotemporary with Saint Francis and Saint Dominick, has given
                    pictures of their new flocks, which might be taken for an abstract of all that
                    has been written from the days of Pascal to the present, concerning the Jesuits.
                        <quote>‘The people,’ <seg type="inciso">says he</seg>,
                        ‘called them hypocrites and successors of Antichrist,
                        pseudopreachers, flatterers and counsellors of kings and princes, despisers
                        and supplanters of bishops, violators of royal marriagebeds, prevaricators
                        of confessions, who, wandering over unknown provinces, ininister to the
                        audacity of sin.’</quote> (<bibl>
                  <emph>ad an.</emph> 1256, p. 939,
                            <emph>Edit.</emph> 1640.</bibl>) It is inconceivable what an ascendency
                    was exercised by the Dominicans and Franciscans in the time of our poet over the
                    passions of individuals, the opinions of the people, and the powers of the
                    State. The Franciscan, Fra Giovanni da Vicenza, possessed unbounded authority in
                    Lombardy, changing the laws, leading towns and provinces in his train;
                    instigating the civil animosities of that unhappy people in obedience to the
                    fatal policy of the Popes; and, when harangues and intrigues failed, making
                    himself obeyed by auto–da–fe. By a document published.not
                    long since by Mr Marini, it appears that auto–da–fe were
                    multiplied by the Dominicans, even beyond the wishes and orders of the Court of
                    Rome. It is a brief of Pope Benedict the XI, dated the 11th of March 1304, and
                    addressed to the Inquisitors of Padua, ordering them to reverse their iniquitous
                    sentences, and to go on with their trade of preaching and burning, in such a
                    manner, that the outcries of the people should no longer reach his ears.
                    Benedict the XI was himself a Dominican; and perhaps wished, like many other
                    sovereigns, to profit by the injustice of his agents, without appearing to be a
                    party.</p>
            <p>At the very time that these friars were setting the example of the most infamous
                    vices, they appear also to have originated the most sacrilegious heresies. The
                    Mendicants not only continued to cry up their inmimerable antiquated visions,
                    but invented new ones still more absurd, which they continued to have revealed,
                    sworn to, and believed. The University of Paris was for several years agitated,
                    Europe scandalized, and the Vatican occupied without knowing how to extricate
                    itself, with a long trial of the Dominicans for a singular attempt, aided by a
                    Franciscan fanatick, to substitute the prophetic visions of the Abbé Joachim,
                    with some supplements of their own, for the <title>New Testament</title>. Mathew
                    Paris, either from not being exactly informed of what was passing abroad, or not
                    daring to state all he knew, speaks of this circumstance only in general terms.
                        <quote>‘They preached,’ <seg type="inciso">says
                        he,</seg> ‘commented, and taught certain novelties, which, as far
                        as they were known, were considered mere ravings, and reduced those into a
                        book, which they were pleased to style “<title>the Everlasting
                            Gospel</title>;” with certain other things, of which it would
                        not be wise to say too much.’</quote> (<bibl>
                  <title>Hist.
                        Ang.</title>, ad an. 1257</bibl>). But he has said quite enough to confirm
                    the discoveries subsequently made by writers of every communion, respecting this
                    extraordinary fact, and to make known in what state Dante found the religion of
                    Europe. The Inquisitors, in the mean time, were by no means remiss in burning
                    astrologers, and persons accused of practising the art of magic, though it
                    sometimes happened that an astrologer triumphed over them. Of two cotemporaries
                    of Dante, one, Cecco d'Ascoli, was burned by order of the Dominican Inquisition
                    at Florence;<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Gio. Villani, B. 10, Chap. 39</bibl>.</p>
               </note> and the other, Pietro d'Abano, who was reputed to be confederate with
                    devils, and openly professed astrology, upon being accused at Paris, retorted
                    the charge of heresy upon the Dominicans — summoned them to appear
                    — convicted them of heresy by forty–five special arguments
                    — procured their expulsion and exclusion from Paris for a considerable
                    period — and was himself pronounced innocent by the Pope at Rome.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Michael Savonarola, ad an. 1292, 1299. — Petri Abani
                                    <title>Conciliator</title>, differentia 10</bibl>.</p>
               </note> The people, however, believed in the power of this magician. It is
                    mentioned in the chronicles of that age, and still repeated in the villages of
                    Padua, that Pietro had seven spirits at his command; and that when he was going
                    to be hanged, he substituted an ass in his place. The fact is, that
                    notwithstanding his canonical absolution, Pietro had admitted in his writings
                    the influence of the stars upon human actions, and denied absolutely the
                    existence of demons.<note place="foot">
                  <p>This curious observation was first made by Pico of Mirandola: see
                                    <bibl>
                        <title lang="lat">De rerum Prœnotatione</title>, sect.
                            5</bibl>.</p>
               </note> The philosophy of Epicurus had made some progress among the higher
                    orders in the age of Dante; Guido Cavalcanti, his intimate friend, was pointed
                    out by the people for his Meditations against the existence of God.</p>
            <p>Thus were the grossest abuses of superstition and fanaticism mingled with
                    heretical license, uncertainty of opinion, popular credulity and atheism; and,
                    nevertheless, Religion was still the great centre around which all the passions
                    and interests of mankind revolved. In this singular condition of society,
                    Boniface, in the last year of the 13th century, proclaimed a plenary indulgence
                    to all who should make a pilgrimage to Rome. All Christendom was accordingly
                    attracted towards the holy city; and, during several weeks, 200,000 foreigners
                    were calculated to succeed each other daily<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Muratori, <title lang="ita">Annali</title>, ad an. 1300</bibl>.</p>
               </note> at its gates. To give all possible solemnity and effect to the lessons
                    he proposed to inculcate, Dante fixed the epoch of his Vision of Divine Justice
                    in the holy week of that year, when all Europe thus went forth to ob tain the
                    remission of sins.</p>
            <p>We have thus endeavoured tu fill up some of the <foreign lang="lat">lacunae</foreign> in the work of Mr Cancellieri; and trust we have, at the same
                    time, negatived many of the trite and visionary conjectures that have been
                    hazarded upon the sources whence our poet might have derived the idea of his
                        work.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Romance of Querino</title> — <title>Saint
                                    Patrick's pit</title> — <title>The Juggler who goes to
                                    Hell</title> — <title>The dream of Hell</title>
                                — <title>The road to Hell</title> — and three
                                Tales of the 12th and 13th centuries, to be found in the old French
                                    <emph>Fabliaux</emph>
                     </bibl>.</p>
               </note> There are, however, some recent authors, whose writings are deservedly
                    popular, of whose opinions it may be right to say something. Denina has gone the
                    length of supposing, that Dante borrowed his plan from a masquerade which took
                    place during a public festival at Florence, in which devils and damned souls
                    were represented as characters. This strange drama was exhibited on a bridge
                    over the Arno, which, being made of wood, gave way during the show, and closed
                    the scene most tragically. — Now, it appears from Villani, that Dante
                    had left Florence two years before; and, previously to his departure, had
                    composed the seven first cantos of his poem, which were saved by his wife when
                    his house was pillaged and destroyed by the faction that persecuted him. The
                    manuscript, by Boccaccio's account, was sent to him in his exile, in 1302; and
                    the masquerade of <quote>‘the Damned Souls’</quote> was
                    represented in 1304. The truth, therefore, is probably the very reverse of
                    Denina's conjecture, — that the idea of the show was suggested to the
                    people of Florence by the beginning of their fellow–citizen's poem
                    Tiraboschi and Mr Sismondi, indeed, are both of this opinion; and we may add,
                    that, even in 1295, Dante, in his little work, entitled <title lang="ita">La
                        Vita Nuova</title>, gives distinct hints of the design of his great poem.</p>
            <p>Our poet was the pupil of Brunetto Latini, who, in a sort of poem, entitled the
                        <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title>, supposes himself guided by Ovid through
                    the mazes of a forest, in search of the oracles of nature and philosophy; and
                    from this model it is confidently asserted, that the pupil loses himself in a
                    forest, and takes Virgil for his guide. That Mr Corniani should dilate upon this
                    fine discovery, is very natural — for, of all the historians of
                    Italian literature, he is the most quackish and the most inept. But it is
                    lamentable that it should be repeated with even more confidence by Mr Ginguené.
                    He is <quote>‘astonished, that no Italian before Mr Corniani suspected
                        this to be the origin of Dante's poem;’</quote> — and we
                    are astonished, in our turn, that Mr Ginguené should not know this suspicion to
                    be as old as the year 1400. It may be collected, indeed, from the biographical
                    account of Dante, by Philip Villani, nephew to the illustrious historian of that
                    name; and was advanced more boldly by others a few years after, and at a longer
                        interval.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>Vide Lor. Mehus, <title lang="ita">Vita del Traversari</title>,
                                page 153</bibl>.</p>
               </note> Federigo Ubaldini says, in the preface to his edition of the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title> in 1642 — <quote lang="ita">‘Aver Dante imitato il <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title> di
                        Brunetto Latini.’</quote> Mr Ginguené too, we may say, has been
                    much too favourable in his judgment of the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title>,
                    which is really a very meain and scarcely intelligible performance. Though
                    written six hundred years ago, we suspect there are but few persons who have
                    read it in all that time. Would it be credited, that Count Mazzuchelli, and
                    Father Quadrio, the two Italian writers who have most carefully explored the old
                    authors, had but an imperfect knowledge of the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title>, even while they were busy displiting about it? Both writers,
                    misled by the resemblance of name, mention it as an abridgment of the <title lang="ita">Tesoro</title>, which is in fact the great work of Brunetto
                    Latini, but has nothing whatever, either in conception or matter, in common with
                    the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title>. The <title lang="ita">Tesoro</title>,
                    besides, is written in French, and in prose. Monsignor Fontanini, who is
                    occasionally bewildered by his admiration of what is old, calls the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title> — <quote lang="ita">‘Poesia
                        cristiana, nobile e morale.’</quote> Its orthodoxy we do not
                    dispute. But, for nobleness, we can see nothing but the reverse. And, as to its
                    morality, it consists entirely in a string of maxims, or rather proverbs,
                    without imagery, sentiment, or a single spark of animation. It is moreover
                    disfigured by grammatical inaccuracies, vulgarisms of phrase, and a great number
                    of words, so obscure, as not to be found even in the dictionary of la Crusca.
                    That Academy, which was certainly disposed to do full justice to the efforts of
                    the early Florentine writers, and was instituted for the purpose of examining
                    them with more care, has characterized the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title>
                    in three words — <quote lang="ita">‘Poesia a foggia di
                        frottola’</quote> — (poetry in the trivial ballad
                    style.)</p>
            <p>After all this, we should scarcely have expected to meet with a passage like the
                    following in so learned and correct an author as Mr Hallam.
                        <quote>‘The source from which Dante derived the scheme and general
                        idea of his poem, has been a subject of inquiry in Italy. To his original
                        mind, one might have thought the sixth <title>Aeneid</title> would have
                        sufficed. But it happens, in fact, that he took his plan, with more direct
                        imitation than we should expect, from the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title> of his master in philosophical studies, Brunetto Latini.
                        This is proved by <bibl>Mr Ginguené, B. 2, p. 8.</bibl>’</quote>
                    Even the authority is hastily quoted for this hasty opinion: for though it is
                    true, that, in the place cited by Mr Hallam, and elsewhere, the French critic
                    has made the assertion here imputed to him, it is very remarkable, that, in the
                    succeeding volume, this <emph>certainty</emph> is reduced to
                    <emph>probability</emph>. Mr Ginguené there says only, <quote>‘that
                        Dante gave grandeur and poetic colouring to the ideas of his master,
                        Brunetto, — <emph>if indeed he borrowed any from him; and similar
                            ideas were not dictated to him by the nature of his
                        subject.</emph>’</quote> (<bibl>Vol. II, p. 27</bibl>). And at
                    last this great discovery dwindles into a mere <emph>possibility</emph>, for Mr
                    Ginguené, in giving some extracts from the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title>,
                    is reduced to the avowal, <quote>‘that it is at least
                        <emph>possible</emph> Dante may have profited by it.’</quote>
                        (<bibl>p. 8</bibl>). The truth is, that such inaccuracies and
                    inconsistencies are almost inevitable in treating of a foreign literature; and
                    especially of a literature so copious and peculiar as the Italian. The history
                    of its eminent writers is entangled in the dissensions of the different
                    provinces — the systems of their different schools — their
                    religious opinions, and not infrequently the political interests of their
                    several masters. Hence, in order to appretiate the force or the value of their
                    expressions, it is often necessary to have an accurate knowledge of the
                    different systems of literary education, of manners, of revolutions, of
                    governments, and, often, even of the personal character and design of each
                    writer. In Italy, too, it should be remembered, that there has not for centuries
                    been any political freedom, and that the people have been studiously kept in
                    ignorance. Flattery and satire have accordingly been chiefly in request
                    — while party spirit and imposture have had full play. The number of
                    readers, at the same time, is so limited, as to consist almost wholly of
                    protegés, patrons and rivals: and the men of letters, who might expose
                    imposture, and bring truth to light, have rarely been able to speak without
                    danger. We have already observed, that the Jesuits usurped every branch of
                    polite literature; and that, to serve the cause of the Popes, they
                    systematically decried Dante, with the other noblest geniuses of Italy.
                    Nevertheless, the history of the Jesuit Tiraboschi, is (with very few
                    exceptions) the constant model of Mr Ginguené, who in fact has done little more
                    than impart a more lively colouring to the original design of that learned but
                    prejudiced person. In the execution of this humble task, however, he now and
                    then gets so bewildered as to be unjust to his model: — for example,
                    he actually charges Tiraboschi <quote>‘with having confounded the
                            <title lang="ita">Tesoro</title> with the <title lang="ita">Tesoretto</title>,’</quote> (<bibl>vol. II, p. 8.</bibl>);
                    — while the fact is, that Tiraboschi was the very person who first
                    exposed this blunder of Mazzuchelli and Quadrio, to which we have already
                    adverted. (<bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Storia Lett.</title>, vol. IV, lib. 3, c.
                    5.</bibl>) The French, however, are apt, we suspect, to fall into such
                    perplexities. The Abbé de Sades, in his Memoirs of the life of Petrarca, relates
                    of that poet — <quote>‘that, to avoid a winter passage
                            <emph>over the mountains between Milan and Venice</emph>, he postponed
                        his journey,’</quote> &amp; c. (<bibl>vol. III, p.
                    345.</bibl>) Now, we shall not venture to say what might have been the state of
                    that country anterior to the deluge: but of this we are certain, that in no
                    author, antient or modern, always excepting M. de Sades, is there the least
                    mention of mountains between Milan and Venice — a tract of country so
                    flat, as to be called, in the chronicles of the time of Petrarca —
                        <quote lang="ita">‘La Valle Lombarda’</quote>.
                    — The key to the whole, is that the Abbé had never been in Italy,
                    — and that Mr Ginguené wrote in the same predicament; having never
                    penetrated beyond Turin, where he went as ambassador in the time of the
                    Republic. We must not wonder, therefore, if he should now and then make a slip
                    — But he might have avoided quoting foreign as native authority.
                        <quote lang="fre">‘Pour ne point alleguer ici’ <seg type="inciso">observes Mr Ginguené (<bibl>vol. I. p. 25</bibl>)</seg>
                        ‘d'autorités suspectes; c'est encore dans <emph>les
                        Italiens</emph> que je puiserais:’</quote> And incontinently, he
                    cites a passage of <emph>Mr Andres</emph>, <quote>who certainly writes in
                        Italian, but is <emph>a Spaniard</emph>!</quote> — and, moreover,
                    generally considered in Italy, as neither very well acquainted with its
                    literature, nor very just to it.</p>
            <p>The work of Mr Frederick Schlegel, which has been very lately translated into
                    English, is another instance of the hazards of all peremptory criticism on the
                    character of foreign writers. The German author has entitled his book
                    — ‘<title>Lectures on the History of Literature, aritient
                        and modern.</title>’ He is graciously pleased to represent Dante
                    as <quote>‘the greatest of Italian and of Christian
                    poets,’</quote> — but observes, at the same time, that
                            <quote>‘<emph>the Ghibeline harshness</emph> appears in Dante
                        in a form noble and dignified. But although it may perhaps do no injury to
                        the outward beauty, it certainly mars, in a very considerable degree, the
                        internal charm of his poetry. His chief defect is, in a word, <emph>the want
                            of gentle feelings</emph>’</quote>. Now, the opinion of Mr
                    Hallam is directly opposite to that of this learned Theban. <quote>‘In
                        one so highly endowed by nature’, <seg type="inciso">observes Mr
                            Hallam</seg>, ‘and so consummate by instruction, we may well
                        sympathize with a resentment whích exile and poverty rendered perpetually
                        fresh. But the heart of Dante was naturally <emph>sensible</emph> and
                            <emph>even tender</emph>; his poetry is full of comparisons from rural
                        life; and the sincerity of his early passion for Beatrice, pierces through
                        the veil of allegory that surrounds her. But the memory of his injuries
                        pursued him into the immensity of eternal light; and, in the company of
                        saints and angels, his unforgiving spirit darkens at the name of
                        Florence.’</quote> It would be presumption in us to determine
                    — between Mr Schlegel and Mr Hallam — which has read Dante
                    with more care; but the poem itself, we think, affords sufficient evidence that
                    the English critic has the truer sense of its character — and is most
                    in unison with the soul of the poet, which was fraught even to redundance with
                    ‘gentle feelings’, and poured them out, on every occasion,
                    with a warmth and delicacy perhaps unequalled in any other writer. We must
                    however remind even Mr Hallam, that Dante does not always, in his poem, mention
                    his country with resentment; and, in his prose work, <title lang="ita">Il
                        Convito</title>, he remembers Florence with the most affectionate
                    tenderness. He styles the injustice of his fellow–citizens towards
                    himself, a fault, not a crime — and offers up a pathetic prayer,
                        <quote>‘that his bones might repose at last in the soft bosom of
                        that land which had nursed and borne him to the maturity of his
                        age’</quote>. — We subjoin his own words, for the
                    satisfaction of those who are sufficiently conversant with Italian to feel the
                    beauty of the original, and who will thence readily concur in the truth of our
                    observation. <quote lang="ita">‘Ahi! piaciuto fosse al Dispensatore
                        dell'Universo che la cagione della mia scusa mai non fosse stata! Che né
                        altri contro me avria fallato, né io sofferto avrei pena ingiustamente;
                        pena, dico, d'esilio e di povertà, poiché fu piacere dei cittadini della
                        bellissima e famosissima figlia di Roma, Fiorenza, di gittarmi fuori del suo
                        dolce seno, nel quale nato e nudrito fui fino al colmo della mia vita; e nel
                        quale, con buona pace di quella, desidero con tutto il cuore di riposare
                        l'animo stanco, e terminare il tempo che mi è dato’</quote>.</p>
            <p>Mr Schlegel, however, is not the only person who has imputed harshness of soul to
                    Dante. This, indeed, is a sort of traditional censure, derived from the
                    fastidious critics of the Court of Leo X; for our poet, it must be confessed,
                    was</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="lat">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>......... minus aptus acutis</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Naribus horum hominum .........</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>......... at est vir bonne, ut melior</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Non alius quisquam, at ingenium ingens</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>It is a distinctive trait in the character of the earlier poets, that they
                    continually reveal to us in their writings the .inmost feelings and dispositions
                    of their souls. They, as it were, say to the reader,</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="lat">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Tibi nunc, hortante Camœna,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Excutienda damus prœcordia</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>But, in order to obtain just views of those characteristic feelings, their poems
                    should be read through ana chrough; whereas the generality of critics content
                    themselves with a few popular passages, and judge of fhe rest according to the
                    response of some of those oracles, who, like Cardinal Bembo, have had the art or
                    the good fortune to make their <emph>dicta</emph> pass current as authority.
                    Dante is, perhaps, the poet most spoken of, and least read by foreigners. It
                    may, therefore, be proper to select a few passages from the many that might be
                    found in his poem, to prove that his heart was as much distinguished for
                    gentleness, as for magnanimity and force.</p>
            <p>The haughtiness of demeanour, attributed to him by all the writers from Giovanni
                    Villani to the present day, probably is not exaggerated. He was naturally proud;
                    and when he compared himself with his cotemporaries, he felt his own
                    superiority, and took refuge, as he expresses it himself with so much happiness
                    —</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Sotto l'usbergo del sentirsi puro</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Conscience makès me firm;</l>
                  <l>The boon companion, <emph>who her strong breastplate</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Buckles on him that feels no guilt within</emph>,</l>
                  <l>And bids him on, and fear not.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>Nevertheless, this inflexibility and pride, nielt at onc'e into the softest
                    deference and docility, when he meets those who have claims upon his gratitude
                    or respect. In conversing with the shade of Brunetto Latini, who was damned for
                    a shameful crime, he still attends his master with his head bent down
                    —</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Il capo chino</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Tenea, com'uom che riverente vada</emph> —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Held my head</l>
                  <l>Bent down as one who walks in reverent guise.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>We believe it has never been remarked that Dante, who makes it a rule, in
                    conversing with all others, to employ the pronoun <foreign lang="ita">tu</foreign> (thou), uses the .pronoun <foreign lang="ita">voi</foreign> (you)
                    in addressing his preceptor Brunetto, and his mistress Beatrice. Even Mr Cary
                    has not seized this shade of distinction, and translates</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Sete</emph> voi <emph>qui, ser Brunetto</emph> —</l>
               </lg>
               <p>— by — Sir! Brunetto!</p>
               <p>And art <emph>thou</emph> here?</p>
            </quote>
            <p>Our poet has even carried modesty so far as not to pronounce his own name; and
                    upon one occasion, when he was asked who he was, did not say that he was Dante;
                    but whilst he described himself in such a manner as to give an exalted opinion
                    of his genius, ascribed all the merit to love, by which he was inspired
                    —</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>......... <emph>io mi son un, che quando</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Amore spira, noto; e a quel modo</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che detta dentro, vo significando</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Count of me but as one</l>
                  <l>Who am the scribe of Love, that, when he breathes,</l>
                  <l>Take up my pen, and, as he dictates, write.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>Yet when the beloved Beatrice addresses him, as if to reproach him with his past
                    life —</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Dante!</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Non pianger anco, non pianger ancora;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che pianger ti convien per altra spada</emph> —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Dante, weep not;</l>
                  <l>Weep thou not yet; — behoves thee feel the edge</l>
                  <l>Of other sword, and thou shalt weep for that;</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>he writes his own name, lest he should alter or omit a single word that fell from
                    the lips of her he loved; yet, even for this, he thinks it necessary to excuse
                    himself —</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Quando mi volsi, al suon del nome mio</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che di necessità qui ei rigistra</emph> —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Turning me at the sound of mine own name</l>
                  <l>Which here I am compelled to register.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>This repugnance to occupy his readers with his own particular concerns, (a
                    repugnance of which we have certainly no reason to complain in the authors of
                    the present day), has perhaps imposed upon Dante his singular silence respecting
                    his family. Whilst he records a variety of domestic anecdotes of almost all his
                    acquaintance, and so forcibly paints the miseries of exile, he omits one grief
                    the most cruel of all — that of a father without a house to shelter,
                    or bread to feed his young and helpless children. It is beyond all doubt that he
                    had several sons, and that they lived in a state of proscription and distress
                    until the period of his death. But, for this fact, we are indebted only to the
                    historians. From his own writings it could not be even suspected that he was a
                    husband and a father.</p>
            <p>It is, however, easy to perceive, that he is thinking of his family, when he
                    exclaims, that the women of Florence, in older times, when purity of morals and
                    civil concord prevailed, were not reduced to a life of widowhood whilst their
                    husbands yet lived — or obliged to share with them the sufferings of
                    their exile, without knowing in what place they should find a grave —</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>O fortunate, e ciascuna era certa</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Della sua sepoltura</emph> —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh! happy they,</l>
                  <l>Each sure of burial in her native land.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>It is not alone in his <quote>‘comparisons drawn from rural
                        life’</quote>, as remarked by Mr Hallam, but principally in what
                    he says of social intercourse, and of the brighter days of his country, that we
                    perceive the sensibility and gentleness of his nature. He delights in painting
                    the joys of domestic life, of which he presents a most affecting picture in the
                    15th Canto of the <title lang="ita">Paradiso</title>, whence we have taken the
                    verses just quoted. He does not lament the loss of innocence and simplicity
                    alone, but also of the refined luxury, the courtesy, the chivalrous spirit of
                    gallantry and love, and the tone of high breeding in society, which in Italy, it
                    seems, were then beginning to disappear.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>The ladies and the knights, the toils and ease</l>
                  <l>That witched us into love and courtesy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Le donne, i cavalier', gli affanni e gli agi</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che ne invogliava amore e cortesia</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>These two lines have such a charm to Italian ears, that Ariosto, after having
                    sketched a thousand beginnings for his poem, and decided upon an indifferent one
                    enough., which was printed, finally rejected them all in the second edition, and
                    substituted almost word for word, the verses of Dante, as follows —</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Le donne, i cavalier, l'armi, gli amori</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Le cortesie, l'audaci imprese, io canto</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>But the slight change which it was necessary to make, destroyed the sweet harmony
                    of the original; and the delicate sentiment of regret is wholly lost in the
                    imitation. It is very rarely that the same ideas, or the same words, produce the
                    same effect, when transplanted from the place into which they first dropped from
                    the heart of a man of genius.</p>
            <p>It is curious to see, how little novelty there is, even in the most modern of our
                    elegant distresses. Dante, in the beginning of the 14th century, complains, that
                    commerce having suddenly enriched numbers of mere clowns, society was corrupted
                    and debased by an upstart aristocracy whose insolence and profusion had put to
                    flight all courtesy of heart, and refinement of breeding</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>An upstart multitude, and sudden gain,</l>
                  <l>Pride and excess, oh! Florence! have in thee</l>
                  <l>Engendered; so that now in tears thou mourn'st.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>This is one of the many instances in which our poet mingles with stern justice of
                    observation, a sentiment of plaintive tenderness for his country. It will, we
                    believe, be much more forcibly felt by those who understand the original.</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>La gente nuova e i subiti guadagni</emph>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Orgoglio e dismisura han generata</emph>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Fiorenza, in te! si che tu già ten piagni</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>He has also the generosity to attribute to others the courtesy which was felt
                    with so much nobleness, and expressed with so much sweetness by himself. Upon
                    his entrance into Purgatory, he meets his friend Casella, a celebrated musician,
                    who died a short time before, and whom he deeply lamented.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>Then one I saw, darting before the rest</l>
                  <l>With such fond ardour to embrace me, I</l>
                  <l>To do the like was moved: O, shadows vain,</l>
                  <l>Except in outward semblance! Thrice my hands</l>
                  <l>I clasped behind it; they as oft returned</l>
                  <l>Empty into my breast again: Surprise,</l>
                  <l>I need must think, was painted in my looks,</l>
                  <l>For that the shadow smiled and backward drew.</l>
                  <l>To follow it I hastened, but with voice</l>
                  <l>Of sweetness, it enjoined me to desist;</l>
                  <l>Then who it was I knew, and prayed of it</l>
                  <l>To talk with me it would a little pause:</l>
                  <l>It answered, “Thee as in my mortal frame</l>
                  <l>I loved, so loosed from it I love thee still,</l>
                  <l>And therefore pause; but why walkest thou here?”</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>We shall give neither the sequel nor the original of this dialogue. Even this
                    feeble attempt at translation sufficies to show, that it was dictated to a
                    delicate mind by nature. At the close of their conversation. the poet asks his
                    friend to sing.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>Then I: “If new laws have not quite destroyed</l>
                  <l>Memory and use of that sweet song of love,</l>
                  <l>That whilom all my cares had power to 'suage,</l>
                  <l>Please thee with it a little to console</l>
                  <l>My spirit —</l>
                  <l>“Love that discourses in my thoughts”. He then</l>
                  <l>Regan, in such soft accents, that within</l>
                  <l>The sweetness thrills me yet.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>These lines convey but a dim shadow of the grace and tenderness of the original.</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Ed io: “Se nuova legge non ti toglie</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Memoria o uso all'amoroso canto,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che mi solea quetar tutte mie voglie;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Di ciò ti piaccia consolare alquanto</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>L'anima mia —</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>“Amor che nella mente mi ragiona”</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Cominciò egli allor sì dolcemente</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che la dolcezza ancor dentro mi suona</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>Dante, in the words <quote lang="ita">‘amoroso
                    canto’</quote>, asks his friend generally to sing him some strain that
                    should excite in him feelings of tenderness and love; whilst in Mr Cary's
                    translation, the words <quote>‘<emph>that</emph> song of
                        love’</quote>, seem rather to indicate some particular song, and
                    thereby destroy the beauty and delicacy of the poet's idea; for the touch of
                    courteous and gentle feeling which he imagines in his friend is, that Casella
                    selects a song which Dante had himself written for Beatrice. This is not
                    mentioned in the poem; but we have found the Canzone, of which the opening is
                    given here, among his lyric compositions.</p>
            <p>Perhaps we have not correctly seized the acceptation in which the words
                        <quote>‘gentle feelings’</quote> are used by Mr F.
                    Schlegel. It is difficult for people to understand each other through the medium
                    of a foreign language. We have before us a French translation of the <title lang="ita">Inferno</title>, published a few years since in London, in which
                    the translator complains <quote>‘of not finding enough of
                            <emph>episodes</emph> in the poem of Dante — and this radical
                        vice of the poem, <seg type="inciso">he says</seg>, necessarily fatigues the
                        most intrepid reader’</quote>. Now, in as much as the whole poem,
                    and particularly the <title lang="ita">Inferno</title>, is a tissue of
                        <emph>episodes</emph>, we are obliged to conclude that, in French
                    literature, the word episode meansiomething very different from what is
                    generally understood. We have, however, too many frightful examples before us,
                    to enter into discussions relating to a foreign language. Mr Ginguené, who has
                    treated Italian literature with more zeal and candour, and who was generally
                    better qualified than many who have undertaken the same task, is, we regret to
                    repeat, one of those examples. The simile of Dante (<bibl>
                  <title lang="ita">Inf.</title>, Cant. 1.</bibl>)</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>E come quei che con lena affannata,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Uscito fuor del pelago alla riva,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>si volge all'acqua perigliosa, e guata,</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <note place="foot">
               <quote>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And as a man with difficult short breath</l>
                     <l>Forespent with toiling,' scaped from sea to shore</l>
                     <l>Turns to the perilous wide waste, and stands</l>
                     <l>At gaze.</l>
                  </lg>
               </quote>
               <p>(<bibl>
                     <emph>Cary's translat.</emph>
                  </bibl>)</p>
            </note>
            <p>is translated by Mr Ginguené, <quote lang="fre">‘<emph>Comme un
                            voyageur hors d'haleine, descendu sur le rivage, tourne ses regards vers
                            la mer où il a couru tant de dangers</emph>’</quote>. In the
                    original, the question is not about a traveller at sea, but about a man who
                    saves himself by swimming. He reaches the shore, after having despaired of
                    escape, and when at the very last gasp. The words <quote lang="ita">‘fuor del pelago’</quote> present the man to our
                    imagination as if he had been just vomited up by the ocean; and the concluding
                    verse places him in that sort of stupor which is felt upon passing at once to
                    safety from despair, without any intervention of hope. He looks back upon
                    perdition with a stare, unconscious how he had escaped it. The word <quote lang="ita">‘guata’</quote> which ends the stanza and the
                    sentence, presents all this, as if by magic, to the imagination of the reader
                    — and leaves him in full possession of the image which the poet had
                    conjured up by his genius.</p>
            <p>Such observations may appear too minute and particular; but it is in things like
                    this, that the peculiar merit of Dante consists. He condenses all his thoughts
                    and feelings in the facts he relates — and expresses himself
                    invariably by images, and those images often what the Italian painters call
                        <quote lang="ita">in iscorcio</quote>. Even his largest groupes are composed
                    of a very few strokes of the pencil — and in none does he ever stop to
                    fill up the design with minute or successive touches, but passes hastily on
                    through the boundless variety of his subject, without once pausing to heighten
                    the effect, or even to allow its full development to the emotion he has excited.
                    A single word flung in apparently without design, often gives its whole light
                    and character to the picture. Thus, in the third Canto of the <title lang="ita">Purgatorio</title>, the poet gazes with fixed eyes upon the shades as they
                    move over the mountain. One stands still and addresses him.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>Then of them one began — “Whoe'er thou art</l>
                  <l>Who journey'st thus this way, thy visage turn.</l>
                  <l>Think if me elsewhere thou hast ever seen”.</l>
                  <l>I towards him turned, and with fixed eyes beheld.</l>
                  <l>Comely and fair and gentle of aspect</l>
                  <l>He seemed; but on one brow a gash was marked;</l>
                  <l>When humbly I disclaimed to have beheld</l>
                  <l>Him ever. “Now behold”, he said; and showed,</l>
                  <l>High on his breast, a wound; then smiling, spake,</l>
                  <l>“I am Mandredi”.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>E un di loro incominciò: “Chiunque</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Tu se', così andando volgi 'l viso,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Pon mente, se di là mi vedesti unque”.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Io mi volsi ver lui, e guardail fiso,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Biondo era, e bello, e di gentile aspetto;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Ma l'un de' cigli un colpo avea diviso.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Quando mi fui umilmente disdetto,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>D'averlo visto mai, el disse: “Or
                            vedi”;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>E mostrommi una piaga a sommo il petto,</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Poi sorridendo disse: “Io son
                        Manfredi”</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>Manfredi was the most powerful prince of Italy, and the chief support of the
                    Ghibeline party; and fell on the field of battle in the flower of his age. The
                    Pope had his bones dug up and exposed, in order that they might be <quote rend="italic">‘washed by the rain, and stirred by the
                        wind’</quote>.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <quote lang="ita">Or le bagna la pioggia e muove il vento.</quote>
                  </p>
               </note> It is easy to imagine what Dante felt at the sight of this
                    ill–fated and youthful hero. We look to find a eulogy upon him; but
                    the poet, in his own person, speaks not of Manfredi. It is by the single word
                        <foreign lang="ita">sorridendo</foreign> that the reader is moved to
                    admiration and to pitý. Dante employs but that one touch, to express the
                    magnanimity of a hero <hi rend="sc">SMILING</hi>, whilst he shows the wound that
                    arrested him in his career of glory, — and discovering, in that
                        <emph>smile</emph>, his contempt of the vindictive fury of his enemies.</p>
            <p>We shall add but one example more, to show the difficulty of explaining the
                    beauties of Dante's composition by any general description. The passage we
                    select is from the episode .of ‘<emph>Francesca da
                    Rimini</emph>’, as being most familiar to the English reader, both
                    from its own popularity, and from the beautiful amplification of it which Mr
                    Hunt has lately given to the public. <emph>Francesca</emph> says to the poet,</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Amor, ch'al cor gentil ratto s'apprende,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Prese costui della bella persona</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che mi fu tolta; e il modo ancor m'offende:</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Amor, ch'a nullo amato amar perdona,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Mi prese del costui piacer sì forte</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che, come vedi, ancor non m'abbandona:</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Amor condusse noi ad una morte.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Love, that in gentle heart is quickly learned.</l>
                  <l>Entangled him by that fair form, from me</l>
                  <l>Ta'en in such cruel sort, as grieves me still;</l>
                  <l>Love, that denial takes from none beloved,</l>
                  <l>Caught me with pleasing him so passing well,</l>
                  <l>That, as thou see'st, he yet deserts me not;</l>
                  <l>Love brought us to, one death.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>The whole history of woman's love is as highly and completely wrought, we think,
                    in these few lines, as that of <emph>Juliette</emph> in the whole tragedy of
                    Shakespeare. <emph>Francesca</emph> imputes the passion her
                    brother–in–law conceived for her, not to depravity, but
                    nobleness of heart in him,<note place="foot">
                  <p>The words ‘ <foreign lang="ita">gentile</foreign>’,
                            and ‘ <foreign lang="ita">gentilezza</foreign>’, as
                            used by the best writers, from Dante to the present day, denote rather
                            nobleness of soul than amiableness of manners. <foreign lang="ita">Gentilezza</foreign> is a propensity towards all that is beautiful
                            and generous; and is the alliance of delicacy of sentiment with high
                            courage. Ariosto says, <quote>the lion <foreign lang="ita">ha il cor
                                    gentile</foreign>
                     </quote>.</p>
               </note> and to her own loveliness. With a mingled feeling of keen sorrow and
                    complacent <emph>naïveté</emph>, she says she was fair, and that an
                    ignominious death robbed him of her beauty. She confesses that she loved,
                    because she was beloved: — That charm had deluded her; — and
                    she declares, with transport, that joy had not abandoned her even in hell.</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>— piacer sì forte</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che, come vedi, ancor non m'abbandona</emph>.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>It is thus that Dante unites perspicuity with conciseness — and the
                    most naked simplicity with the profoundest observation of the heart. Her guilty
                    passion survives its punishment by Heaven — but without a shade of
                    impiety. How striking is the contrast of her extreme happiness in the midst of
                    torments that can never cease; when, resuming her nanative, she looks at her
                    lover, and repeats with enthusiasm,</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Questi che mai da me non fia diviso</emph> —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>— he who ne'er</l>
                  <l>From me shall separate.<note place="foot">
                        <p>We think the word <foreign lang="ita">questi</foreign>, in the
                                    original, more evidently conveys the idea that Francesca, when
                                    she used it, turned her eyes towards her lover, who was ever by
                                    her side.</p>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>She nevertheless goes on to relieve her brother–in–law from
                    all imputation of having seduced her. Alone, and unconscious of their danger,
                    they read a love–story together. They gazed upon each other, pale with
                    emotion — but the secret of their mutual passion never escaped their
                    lips.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Per più fiate gli occhi ci sospinse</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Quella lettura, e scolorocci 'l viso;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Ma solo un punto fu quel che ci vinse.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oft–times by that reading</l>
                  <l>Our eyes were drawn together, and the hue</l>
                  <l>Fled from oufaltered cheek: But at one point</l>
                  <l>Alone we fell.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>We are sorry to say Mr Cary has not translated these interesting passages with
                    his usual felicity. The description of two happy lovers in the story was the
                    ruin of Francesca. It was the romance of Lancilot and Ginevra, wife of Arthur,
                    King of England.<note place="foot">
                  <p>Dante calls the author <quote lang="ita">‘Galeotto’</quote>; and, in the manuscripts of
                            Boccaccio, his <title>Decameron</title> is found entitled
                                ‘<title lang="ita">Il principe
                            Galeotto</title>’, apparently to apprise the reader of its
                            being a dangerous book.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Quando leggemmo il disiato riso</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Esser baciato da cotanto amante,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Questi, che mai da me non fia diviso</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>La bocca mi baciò tutto tremante.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>— When of that smile we read</l>
                  <l>The wish'd for smile, so rapturously kissed</l>
                  <l>By one so deep in love; then he, who ne'er</l>
                  <l>From me shall separate, at once my lips</l>
                  <l>All trembling kissed.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>After this avowal, she hastens to complete the picture with one touch which
                    covers her with confusion.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Quel giorno più non vi leggemmo avante.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>— That day,</l>
                  <l>We read no more!</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>She utters not another word! — and yet we fancy her before us, with her
                    downcast and glowing looks; whilst her lover stands by her side, listening in
                    silence and in tears. Dante, too, who had hitherto. questioned her, no longer
                    ventures to inquire in what manner her husband had pu't her to death; but is so
                    overcome by pity, that he sinks into a swoon. Nor is this to be considered as
                    merely a poetical exaggeration. It is remarked by the commentators, that the
                    poet had himself often yielded to the force of love, and that the fear of his
                    own damnation probably mingled with his compassion for Francesca, in producing
                    this excessive emotion. This may be true — but it is but a part of the
                    truth. Dante's whole work, though founded on what may be considered as an
                    extravagánt fiction, is conversant only with real persons. While other poets
                    deal with departed or with fabulous heroes, he takes all his characters from
                    among his countrymen, his cotemporaries, his hosts, his relatives, his friends,
                    and his enemies. Nor does he seek to disguise them under borrowed appellations.
                    He gives, in plain ords, the name and description and character of all those wgl
                    known individuals. He converses with them — reminds them of their
                    former friendship — and still seeks to mingle his sexitiments with
                    theirs. At the same time, he marks impartially the retribution to which he
                    thinks their conduct has entitled them; while, with a singular mixture of human
                    relenting, he is not prevented by their crimes, and consequent punishment in
                    hell, from doing them honour — laying open to them his heart, and
                    consoling them with his tears. If they had attended to those things, we think
                    the commentators might have condescended to mention, that Francesca was the
                    daughter of <emph>Guido da Polenta</emph>, master of Ravenna, Dante's protector
                    and most faithful friend. The poet had probably known her when a girl, blooming
                    in innocence and beauty under the paternal roof. He must, at least, have often
                    heard the father mention his ill–fated child. He must therefore have
                    recollected her early happiness, when he beheld the spectacle of her eternal
                    torment; and this, we think, is the true account of the overwhelming sympathy
                    with which her form overpowers him. The episode, too, was written by him in the
                    very house in which she was born, and in which he had himself, during the last
                    ten years of his exile, found a constant asylum.</p>
            <p>Boccaccio has given an account which greatly mitigates the crime of Francesca;
                    and he insinuates, that still further particulars were known to Dante. He
                    relates, that <quote>‘<emph>Guido</emph> engaged to give his daubrhter
                        in marriage to Lanciotto, the eldest son of his enemy the master of Rimini.
                        Lanciotto, who was hideously deformed in countenance and figure, foresaw,
                        that if he presented himself in person, he should be rejected by the lady.
                        He therefore resolved to marry her by proxy, and sent, as'his
                        representative, his younger brother Paolo, the handsomest and most
                        accomplished man in all Italy. Francesca saw Paolo arrive, and .imagined she
                        beheld her future husband. That mistake was the commencement of her passion.
                        The friends of Guido addressed him in strong remonstrances and mournful
                        predictions of the dangers to which he exposed a daughter, whose high spirit
                        would never brook to be sacrificen with impunity. But Guido was no longer in
                        a condition to make war; and the necessities of the politician overcame the
                        feelings of the father.’</quote>
               <note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <title lang="ita">Opere del Boccaccio</title>, vol. V, towards the
                                end, Florence edition, 1721.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Dante abstained from employing any of those circumstances, though highly
                    poetical. He knew that pathos, by being expanded over a number of objects, loses
                    of its force. His design was to produce, not tragedies, but single scenes; and
                    Francesca, to justify herself, must have criminated her father, and thus
                    diminished the affecting magnanimity with which her character is studiously
                    endowed by the poet.</p>
            <p>To record this stain upon the illustrious family of a benefactor and a friend,
                    may in our eyes appear indelicate and ungrateful; especially as it may be
                    supposed, from his placing Francesca in Hell, that he meant to hold her up to
                    execration. An observation which perhaps has not escaped the learned men of
                    Italy, but which they have never expressed, from the dread of provoking the
                    savage bigotry of their priests, explains this point. Dante constantly
                    distinguishes between the <emph>sins</emph> and <emph>merits</emph> of each
                    individual. <emph>Divine Justice</emph>, in his poem, punishes sin whenever it
                    is actually committed; but <emph>human sympathy</emph>, or pity, laments or
                    extenuates the offence, according to the circumstances under which it was
                    committed. The poet dispenses censure and praise, according to the general
                    qualities of the personsthe good or evil they had done their
                    country—the glory or the infamy they had left behind them. He,
                    however, carefully abstains from laying down this maxim in words, whilst he
                    invariably acts upon it both in the <title lang="ita">Inferno</title> and the
                        <title lang="ita">Purgatorio</title>. In the <title lang="ita">Paradiso</title>, there is plainly no room for its operation.</p>
            <p>From this principle he has deduced, that those who have done neither good or evil
                    in their day, are the most despicable of beings. They are described as</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Questi sciaurati che mai non fur vivi</emph> —</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>These wretches who ne'er lived.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>He places them between Hell, the abode of the damned, and Limbo, the abode of the
                    souls of infants and good men ignorant of the Christian faith; and with singular
                    boldness of opinion as well as style, he says <emph>God's</emph> justice
                    disdains to punish, and his mercy disdains to pardon, those who were useless in
                    their lives.</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Fama di lor nel mondo esser non lassa,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Misericordia e Giustizia li edegna,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Non ragioniam di lor, ma guarda e passa.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fame of them the world hath none,</l>
                  <l>Nor suffers. Mercy and Justice scorn them both.</l>
                  <l>Speak not of them; but look, and pass them by.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>Among those, he has had the boldness to place Saint Celestino, who abdicated the
                    pontificate through weakness, and acquired his titles to canonization in a
                    hermit's cell. He also finds amongst them the angels that in the war of
                        <emph>Lucifer</emph> against <emph>God</emph> took neither side, and thought
                    only of themselves.</p>
            <p>In those who merited that <emph>God</emph> should weigh their lives against their
                    sins, Dante has generally implanted a strong desire of celebrity. The prospect
                    of being named by the poet, on his return to the living, suspends awhile the
                    sense of their pains. Great souls, though expiating the guilt and shamefulness
                    of the heaviest sins, entreat him to mention his having seen them. This he
                    always promises; and often, for the purpose of engaging them to speak with him
                    more freely, pledges his faith that they shall not be forgotten. The shades of
                    those only who in their lives were sunk in habitual crime and infamy, conceal
                    from him their names. It is in the middle abre, between barbarism and
                    refinement, that men most strongly feel this desire of having their names
                    preserved from oblivion. The passions, at that period, have yet lost no portion
                    of their vigour, and are ruled by impulse rather than by calculation. Man has
                    then more difficulties to rouse, and more courage to sustain him; and, rather
                    than be checked in his course, will plunge with <emph>celat</emph> into any gulf
                    that opens in his way. .Of this the age of Dante furnishes examples scarcely
                    credible in an age like ours, in which nothing retains sufficient novelty to
                    make a strong impression, and the objects of pursuit are so multiplied, that no
                    one can excite a commanding interest. It is obvious, however, that the strong
                    passions of less polished times bear men on to great virtues — great
                    crimes — great calamities; and thus form the characters that are most
                    proper for poetry. Dante had only to look round him for characters such as
                    these. He found them already formed for his purpose, without the necessity of a
                    single heightening touch from his own invention. Refinement had not yet produced
                    that sameness of individual physiognomy in the great mass of a nation.
                    Individual originality, now rare, dangerous, ridiculous, and often affected, was
                    then common and undisguised. Poetry, in later times, has succeeded in catching
                    its shades for the purposes of fine comedy — as in the
                        <title>Misanthrope</title> of Molière; and of pretty satire — as
                    in Pope's <title>Rape of the Lock</title>. But all that this species of poetry
                    can do, is to seize that exterior of character which every age and nation decks
                    out after its own fashion; whilst the poetry, whose business is with the human
                    heart, is coeval and coextensive with human nature. Pope, accordingly, no sooner
                    lighted, in an almost barbarous age, upon a poetical personage, governed both in
                    action and in writing by feeling alone, than he produced the <title>Epistle of
                        Eloisa</title>, and proved that he had genius. Many a woman of that day
                    resembled <emph>Eloisa</emph> in her misfortunes and her love; but they left
                    few, if any, letters behind them. Even those of <emph>Eloisa</emph> have reached
                    us only by their connexion with the writings of her lover. At present, the fair
                    sex write much more, and perhaps feel as much less; and accordingly, our later
                    poets, not finding poetical characters at home, are driven to seek for them in
                    Turkey and in Persia; — while the Germans explore the ruins of
                    Teutonic castles — and the Italians prudently confine themselves to
                    the mythology of Greece and Rome. In fine, when nations are in a semibarbarous
                    state, the passions are their strongest laws: what else they have under the name
                    of law, is yet without consistency or force. The.punishment of an injury is left
                    do him who suffered it — and he regards vengeance as a duty. Dante
                    concludes one of his lyric pieces with the following sentiment —</p>
            <quote rend="block">
               <lg>
                  <l>How fair is the honour reaped from revenge!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg lang="ita">
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che bell'onor s'acquista in Jar vendetta.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>How strongly does its application to his own poem illustrate the character of his
                    age! Though terrified, at every step, by the objects which Hell presents to his
                    view, the sentiment of vengeance, as a duty, stops him in his course. His eyes
                    are fixed upon a shade that seems to shun him. Virgil reminds him that they must
                    continue their journey; and asks the reason of his delay. Dante answers,
                        <quote>‘If you knew the reason, you would allow me to remain
                        longer; for in the pit, on which I . fixed my eyes, I thought I beheld one
                        of my kinsmen’. ‘Truly’, <seg type="inciso">rejoins Virgil,</seg> ‘I marked him pointing his finger at
                        you with a menacing and haughty air’. ‘Oh! my
                        master’, <seg type="inciso">exclaims Dante:</seg> ‘he
                        was killed by an enemy, and his death has not been yet revenged by any of
                        those to whom that insult was given; and therefore he disdained to speak to
                        me!’</quote>
               <note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <title>Hell</title>, Cant. 29.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>From those considerations, which we have been tempted to expand perhaps more than
                    was necessary, it is, we think, evident, that the episode of Francesca was every
                    way congenial to the principles, the poetry, and the affections of Dante, as
                    well as to the age in which he lived. To satisfy <emph>Divine Justice</emph>,
                    he, in fact, places her in Hell; but he introduces her in such a manner, that
                    human frailty must pity her. Nature had given to her character the poetic cast.
                    Her story, he knew, was one that could not be concealed; — and he gave
                    the daughter of his friend the celebrity which popular tradition could not
                    bestow. The husband of Francesca was living and powerful when Dante wrote; but
                    the fearless vengeance of the poet devotes him to infamy; and foretels, that his
                    place, named after Cain, among the fi·atricides, awaits him in the very centre
                    of Hell. Indeed, the father of Francesca continued to afford protection to
                    Dante, and not only attended his remains to the tomb, but composed and recited a
                    funeral oration over them. His successors, too, defended the Poet's sepulchre
                    against the power of <emph>Charles de Valois</emph>, and the Church —
                    when <emph>John the XXIId</emph> sent Cardinal <emph>Bernardo di Poggetto</emph>
                    from Avignon to Ravenna, with orders to drag forth the bones of the poet from
                    the repose of the grave, that they might be burned, and their ashes scattered
                    before the wind. — This, indeed, is mentioned only by Boccaccio in the
                    life of Dante; and that piece of biography has been generally regarded as a
                    romance. But the fact, we think, þ completely verified in the works of
                        <emph>Bartolo</emph>, a celebrated civilian, who was living at the time, and
                    alludes to it very distinctly in treating of the law <title>de Rejudicandie
                    Reis</title>. (<bibl>ad cod. 1. 1., <title>cod. de Rejudic.</title> &amp;
                    c.</bibl>).</p>
            <p>The celebrity of the episode of Francesca, and the little light hitherto thrown
                    upon it has engaged us in a discussion, the unavoidable length of which is an
                    additional proof that a commentary upon Dante, which should be useful in a
                    historical and poetical view, still remains to be executed. We hasten now to the
                    close of these desultory observations. But few literary men are acquainted with
                    his lyric compositions; and his prose is scarcely ever mentioned. The elegant
                    treatise written by him, to prove that in a nation, divided by so many dialects
                    as Italy, it must be impossible to adapt the dialect of Florence exclusively,
                    was the principal cause of the little value set by the academy of La Crusca and
                    its adherents upon the prose of our poet. For La Crusca always maintained that
                    the language should not be called Italian, or even Tuscan, but Florentine.
                    Nevertheless, the literary language of Italy, though founded upon the Tuscan, is
                    a distinct language, created by the commonwealth of authors, never spoken, but
                    always written; as Dante had seen and foreseen. His own prose is a fine model of
                    forcible and simple style, harmonious without studied cadences, and elegant
                    without the affected graces of Boccaccio and his imitators. We venture upon a
                    short specimen, extracted from the <title lang="ita">Convito</title>, upon the
                    subject to which we have alluded.</p>
            <p>
               <quote lang="ita">‘Siccome non si può bene manifestare la bellezza
                        d'una donna, quando li adornamenti dell'azzimare .e delle vestimenta la
                        fanno più annumerare che essa medesima. Onde chi vuole bene giudicare d'una
                        donna, guardi quella, quando solo sua naturale bellezza si sta con lei, da
                        tutto accidentale adornamento discompagnata. Sicome sarà questo volgare; nel
                        quale si vedrà l'agevolezza delle sue sillabe, le proprietà delle sue
                        condizioni, e le orazioni che di lui si fanno: — le quali chi bene
                        guarderà, vedrà essere piene di dolcissima e d'amabilissima
                    bellezza.</quote>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote lang="ita">A perpetuale infamia e depressione degli malvagi uomini
                        d'Italia che commendano lo volgare altrui e il loro proprio dispregiano,
                        dico, che la loro mossa viene di cinque abominevoli cagioni. La prima, è
                        cecità di discrezione. La seconda, maliziata scusazione. La terza, cupidità
                        di vanagloria. La quarta, argomento d'invidia. La quinta e l'ultima, viltà
                        d'animo, ciò è pusillanimità. E ciascuna di queste età ha sì gran setta che
                        pochi son quelli che sieno da esse liberi. Della prima si può così
                        ragionare. Siccome la parte sensitiva dell'anima ha i suoi occhi co' quali
                        apprende la differenza delle cose in quanto elle sono di fuori colorate,
                        così la parte razionale ha il suo occhio, col quale apprende la differenza
                        delle cose in quanto sono ad alcun fine ordinate, e questa è la discrezione.
                        E siccome colui che è cieco degli occhi sensibili va sempre secondo che gli
                        altri, così colui che è cieco del lume . della discrezione, sempre va nel
                        suo giudizio secondo il grido o diritto o falso. Onde qualunque ora lo
                        guidatore è cieco, conviene che esso e quello anche cieco che a lui
                        s'appoggia vengano a mal fine. Però è scritto che il cieco al cieco farà
                        guida e cosi caderanno amendue nella fossa. Questa guida è stata lungamente
                        contro a nostro volgare per le ragioni che di sotto si ragioneranno.
                        Appresso di questa i ciechi sopra notati, che sono quasi infiniti, con la
                        mano in su la spalla a questi mentitori sono caduti nella fossa della falsa
                        opinione, della quale uscire non sanno. Dell'abito di questa luce discretiva
                        massimamente le popolari persone sono orbate, però che occupate dal
                        principio della loro vita ad alcuno mestiere, dirizzano sì l'animo loro a
                        quella persona della necessità che ad altro non intendono. E però che
                        l'abito di virtù, sì morale come infellettuale, subitamente avere non si
                        può, ma conviene che per usanza s'acquisti, e elli la loro usanza pongono in
                        alcuna arte, e a discernere l'altre cose non curano, impossibile è a loro
                        discrezione avere. Perché incontra che molte volte gridano viva la lor morte
                        e muoja la lor vita, pur che alcuno cominci. E questo è pericolosissimo
                        difetto nella loro cecità. Onde Boezio giudica la popolare gloria vana
                        perché la vede senza discrezione. Questi sono da chiamare pecore e non
                        uomini. Che se una pecora si gettasse da una ripa di mille passi, tutte le
                        altre l'anderebbono dietro. E se una pecora per alcuna cagione al passare
                        d'una strada salta, tutte l'altre saltano, eziandio nulla veggendo di
                        saltare. E io ne vidi già molte in un pozzo saltare per una che dentro vi
                        saltò, forse credendo saltare un muro, non ostante ch'il pastore piangendo e
                        gridando con le braccia e col petto dinanzi si parava. La seconda setta
                        contro al nostro volgare si fa per una maliziata scusa. Molti sono che amano
                        più d'essere tenuti maestri, che d'essere; e per fuggire lo contrario, ciò è
                        di non essere tenuti, sempre danno colpa alla materia dell'arte
                        apparecchiata, ovvero allo strumento. Siccome il mal fabro biasima il ferro
                        appresentato a lui; e lo mal cetarista biasima la cetra; —
                        credendo dar la colpa del mal coltello e del mal suonare al ferro e alla
                        cetra, e levarla a sé. Così sono alquanti, e non pochi, che vogliono che
                        l'uomo gli tenga dicitori, e per scusarsi del non dire, o del dire male,
                        accusano e incolpano la materia, ciò è lo volgare proprio, e commendano
                        l'altro, lo quale non è loro richiesto di fabricare. E chi vuole vedere come
                        questo ferro si dee biasimare, guardi che opere ne fanno gli buoni e
                        perfetti artefici e conoscerà la maliziata scusa di costoro che biasimando
                        lui si credono scusare. Contro questi cotali grida Marco Tullio nel
                        principio d'un suo libro che si chiama libro del fine de' beni. Però che al
                        suo tempo biasimavano lo latino romano, e commendavano la grammatica Greca.
                        E così dico per somiglianti cagioni che questi fanno vile lo parlare
                        Italico; e prezioso quello di Provenza’</quote>, &amp;c.
                    &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The lyric poetry of Italy was not indeed invented or perfected, though greatly
                    improved, by Dante. It is mentioned by himself in his prose works, that
                        <quote>‘lyric composition had been introduced above a century
                        before, by Sicilian poets, into Italy’</quote>; from which time it
                    was gradually cultivated, down to Guido Cavalcanti, who produced some very fine
                    essays — the fmest until those of Dante, who in that kind was, in his
                    turn, surpassed by Petrarca. But still the germs of all that is most enchanting
                    in the strains of Laura's lover, may be found in the verses which had previously
                    celebrated Beatrice. The following is the opening of the canzone which his
                    friend Casella so courteously sang to him in <title>Purgatory</title>.</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Amor che nella mente mi ragiona</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Della mia donna al soavemente,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Move cose di lei meco sovente</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che l'intelletto sovr'esse dievia:</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Lo suo parlar sì dolcemente suona,</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Che l'anima che l'ode e che lo sente</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Dice: oh me lassa!ch'io non son possente</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Di dir quel che odo della donna mia;</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>..............................................</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Perché il nostro pensier non ha valore</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Di ritrar tutto ciò che dice amore.</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>One of his sonnets begins with these four exquisite lines, — to which
                    nothing equal can be found in Petrarca in his happiest moments.</p>
            <quote rend="block" lang="ita">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Ne gli occhi porta la mia donna amore</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Perché si fa gentil ciò ch'ella mira:</emph>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>Ognun che passa presso lei, sospira;</emph> —</l>
                  <l>
                     <emph>E a chi saluta fa tremar lo core!</emph>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
            <p>Unwearied reading, and a profound knowledge of the Italian language, and of the
                    rise and progress of Italian civilization, are the essential requisites for
                    illustrating the age, the genius, and the works of Dante. It requires active and
                    persevering industry to ransack libraries, and peruse manuscripts of the 13th
                    and 14th centuries, not even yet brought to light. We would further recommend,
                    that the age of Dante should be accurately distinguished from that of Boccaccio
                    and Petrarca. This distinction has never been observed in the literary history
                    of Italy; and the consequence has been, that notions the most different have
                    been confounded with each other. It was about the decline of Dante's life that
                    the political constitution of the Italian Republics underwent a total and almost
                    univeysal change, in consequence of which a new character was suddenly assumed
                    by men, manners, literature, and the church.</p>
            <p>It may be observed, that Dante, notwithstanding the number of his biographers,
                    has not yet had a historian. Among the pieces relating to this poet, either
                    unpublished or but little known, which we have had occasion to see, is an
                    interesting letter, which we shall subjoin with the same orthography in which it
                    may be read in the Laurentine library at Florence.<note place="foot">
                  <p>Those who wish to see the original, may find it in that library, by the
                            following references: <bibl>
                        <emph>Pluteum 29, Codex 8, page
                            123</emph>.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>About the year 1316, the friends of Dante succeeded in obtaining his restoration
                    to his country and his possessions, on condition that he should pay a certain
                    sum of money, and, entering church, there avow himself guilty, and ask pardon of
                    the Republic. The following was his answer on the occasion, to one of his
                    kinsmen, whom he calls ‘Father,’ because perhaps he was an
                    ecclesiastic; or, more probably, because he was older than the poet.
                        <quote>‘From your letter, which I received with due respect and
                        affection, I observe how much you have at heart my restoration to my
                        country. I am bound to you the more gratefully, that an exile rarely finds a
                        friend. But, after mature consideration, I must, by my answer, disappoint
                        the wishes of some little minds; and I confide in the judgment to which your
                        impartiality and prudence will lead you. Your nephew and mine has written to
                        me, what indeed had been mentioned by many other friends, that, by a decree
                        concerning the exiles, I am allowed to return to Florence, provided I pay a
                        certain sum of money, and submit to the humiliation of asking and receiving
                        absolution; wherèin, my Father, I see two propositions that are ridiculous
                        and impertinent. I speak of the impertinence of those who mention such
                        conditions to me; for, in your letter, dictated by judgment and discretion,
                        there is no such thing. Is such an invitation to return to his country
                        glorious for Dante, after suffering in exile almost fifteen years? Is it
                        thus then they would recompense innocence which all the world knows, and the
                        labour and fatigue of unremitting study? Far from the man who is familiar
                        with philosophy, be the senseless baseness of a heart of earth, that could
                        do like a little sciolist, and imitate the infamy of some others, by
                        offering himself up as it were in chains. Far from the man who cries aloud
                        for justice, this compromise, by his money, with his persecutors. No, my
                        Father, this is not the way that shall lead me back to my country. But I
                        shall return with hasty steps, if you or any other can open to me a way that
                        shall not derogate from the fame and honour of Dante; but if by no such way
                        Florence can be entered, then Florence I shall never enter. What! shall I
                        not everywhere enjoy the sight of the sun and stars? and may I not seek and
                        contemplate, in every corner of the earth under the canopy of heaven,
                        consoling and delightful truth, without first rendering myself inglorious,
                        nay infamous, to the people and republic of Florence? Bread, I hope, will
                        not fail me’</quote>.<note place="foot">
                  <p>
                     <quote lang="lat">In licteris vestris et reverentia debita et affectione
                                receptis, quam repatriatio mea cure sit vobis ex animo, grata mente,
                                ac diligenti animadversione concepi, etenim tanto me districtius
                                obligastis, quanto rarius exules invenire amicos contingit. ad
                                illarum vero significata respondeo: et si non eatenus qualiter
                                forsan pusillanimitas appeteret aliquorum, ut sub examine vestri
                                consilii ante Judicium, affectuose deposco ecce igitur quod per
                                licteras vestri meique nepotis, necnon aliorum quamplurium amicorum
                                significatum est mihi: per ordinamentum nuper factum Florentie super
                                absolutione bannitorum, quod si solvere vellem certam pecunie
                                quantitatem, vellemque pati notam oblationis et absolvi possem et
                                redire ad presens. in quo quidem duo ridenda et male perconciliata
                                sunt. Pater, dico male perconciliata per illos qui talia
                                expresserunt: nam vestre litere. discretius et consultius clausulate
                                nihil de talibus continebant. estne ista revocatio gloriosa qua d.
                                all. (i. e. <hi rend="sc">DANTES ALLIGHERIUS</hi>) revocatur ad
                                patriam per trilustrium fere perpessus exilium i hecne meruit
                                conscientia manifesta quibuslibet i hec sudor et labor continuatus
                                in studiis i absit a viro philosophie domestico temeraria terreni
                                cordis humilitas, ut more cujusdam Cioli et aliorum infamiam quasi
                                vinctus ipse se patiatur offerri. absit a viro predicante Justitiam,
                                ut perpessus injuriam inferentibus, velut io benemerentibus,
                                pecuniam suam solvat. non est hec via redeundi ad patriam, Pater mi;
                                sed si alia per vos, aut deinde per alios invenietur que fame d.
                                    (<emph>Dantis</emph>) que onori non deroget, illam non lentis
                                passibus acceptabo. quod si per nullam talem Florentia introitur,
                                nunquam Florentiam introibo. quidni? nonne solis astrorumque specula
                                ubique conspiciam? nonne dulcissimas veritates potero speculari
                                ubique sub celo, ni prius inglorium, imo ignominiosum populo,
                                Florentineque civitati me reddam? quippe panis non deficiet.</quote>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Yet bread often did fail him. Every reader,of his works must know by heart the
                    prediction addressed to him by the shade of his ancestor in Paradise.
                            (<bibl>
                  <title>Parad.</title>, Cant. 17.</bibl>) <quote>‘Thou
                        shalt prove how salt is the taste of the bread of others, and how hard the
                        road is going up and down the stairs of others’</quote>. But there
                    is another passage in which, with designed obscurity, and a strength of
                    expression and feeling which makes the reader tremble, he discovers an exact
                    portrait of himself in a man who, <quote rend="italic">stripping his visage of
                        all shame, and, trembling in his very vitals, places himself in the public
                        way, and stretches out his hand for charity.</quote>
               <note place="foot">
                  <p>See <bibl>
                        <title>Purgat.</title>, Cant. II</bibl>; towards the end.</p>
               </note> It was by such sacrifices he preserved his principles and sustained the
                    magnanimity of his character.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
